Welcome to our fifth lecture
in person for Stanford
deep learning CS230.
Today's lecture is going to
be about deep reinforcement
learning.
I actually switched
the original plan
of talking about neural network
interpretability and LLM
visualization, simply
because you haven't
had the chance to
study attention maps,
convolutional neural networks.
And so it would have been an
overkill to do that week five.
So we're going to talk about
neural network interpretability
and visualization in a
later lecture actually.
But today, our focus will be
on deep reinforcement learning,
which is probably my favorite
lecture of the class.
I feel like I say that every
week, but it's OK, I like it.
The agenda is pretty packed.
We're going to start with deep
reinforcement learning, which
you can think of as the
marriage between deep learning
and reinforcement learning.
Together, the baby is called
deep reinforcement learning.
And we're going to see how
reinforcement learning works
and how neural networks
can play a part in building
reinforcement learning agent.
In the second half
of the class, we
will focus on a very specific
concept called reinforcement
learning from human feedback
that you might have heard of.
It's one of the
core concepts that
really made the
difference between what
you might have remembered
as GPT 2 and ChatGPT.
That's the leap.
That's really the technique
that has democratized access
to LLM because of the
performance improvements
and the alignment with humans.
So we're going to see what
is this concept of RLHF
and how does it
work, and why does it
allow us to align a language
model to human preferences.
Ready to go.
As always, let's try
to make it interactive.
So the motivation behind
deep reinforcement
learning-- and as
usual, you're going
to have all the most
important papers that
are covered in the class listed
at the bottom of each slide.
Reinforcement learning
has grown in popularity.
One of the very popular papers,
called Human Level Control
through Deep
Reinforcement Learning,
is the work from
DeepMind, has showed us
that a single
algorithm/training method
can allow us to train AI that
can play many, many Atari games
better than humans.
Single algorithm,
over 40, 50 games
where it exceeds human
capability, which
is quite impressive when
you thought about the fact
that machine learning
used to be niche,
and you would have to train
a really niche algorithm
to perform different tasks.
Here's an algorithm that can
just learn every Atari game.
A little later, you might
have heard of AlphaGo.
AlphaGo is an algorithm
that was developed
to beat and exceed human
performance in the game of Go.
We'll talk about
it a little more.
The game of Go is a
very complex game.
Some would argue way
more complex than chess
from a decision
making standpoint
and from the possibilities
that can happen on the board.
And so it actually got solved in
2017, again by the DeepMind team
and David Silver's lab.
Later on-- and again, another
great paper from DeepMind
had showed us that
reinforcement learning can also
be used for strategy game.
That might be a touch more
complex than chess or Go.
That might actually
involve multiple players
playing with each other
or against each other.
Some of you might have played
StarCraft, for example.
That's an example
of a game where
it requires a lot of long-term
thinking, short-term thinking.
Another one is DOTA.
Some of you might have
played DOTA or league
of legends, where you
have a team playing
against another team.
Those are examples of games that
involve multiple agents playing
collaboratively.
And it's pretty hard
to develop systems
that can play with each other
against multiple opponents.
And finally, most
recently, this is
2022, so alongside the
release of ChatGPT,
this paper that introduces
the concept of reinforcement
learning with human feedback
applied to aligning language
models with human preferences.
And we'll talk about that later.
So all this to say that
reinforcement learning allowed
us to exceed human performance
in a variety of tasks.
The first one I want us to
think about is the game of Go.
So let's say that you were
asked to solve the game of Go
with classic
supervised learning.
Everything we've seen
together so far, labeled data,
how would you solve
the game of Go
with classic
supervised learning?
What data would you collect?
What would be the
label, et cetera?
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE] data that's
the current [INAUDIBLE].
OK, good point.
Yeah, you look at history
of plenty of games,
hopefully from good players.
You want the algorithm to work.
And you look at x
as the input being
the current state
of the board and y
as the next state of the board.
And this would tell you
what move was selected,
and you learn the
move essentially.
And hopefully, if you do
that across many, many games,
you might see the agent become
more attuned to the game
and develop better strategies.
So really hopefully it's
a professional player.
What are the disadvantages
of that or the shortcomings
that you can anticipate?
Yes?
So the two space types of moves
that the players use maybe
[INAUDIBLE] some other set
of moves that [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah, great point.
You might not see
the entire space
of possible states of the
board, which is what you said.
So you might miss out on a
lot of different strategies.
So the game of Go
is actually a game
with two players,
one player that
uses the black stones
and one player that
uses the White stones.
And iteratively,
they're going to place
those stones on the
grid, a 13 by 13 grid
that you can see on screen
with the goal of surrounding
their opponents.
So you're constantly
trying to surround
the stones of the
opponent, and the opponent
is trying to
surround your stones.
And so you can imagine that for
every intersection on the grid,
there is multiple possibilities,
either there's a black stone
or a white stone or nothing.
And on a 13 by 13 grid, you can
imagine how many possibilities
of a board state there are.
It's impossible to capture all
of that with historical moves
from professional players.
You will just never cover that.
The same thing could be
said in chess as well.
You know that even the
professional players can
plan x number of
steps in advance,
but nobody knows where
the game takes you.
And in the late stages of
the games or the end games,
players always find themselves
playing a different game.
And that's part of the magic
of being good at chess.
So yeah, that's a problem.
What's another
problem or shortcoming
beyond the fact that we can't
observe possibly all the states?
Yes?
You also can't anticipate
what that action would lead to
in the future.
You might not make
the best decision.
Correct.
If I repeat what you said,
well, first, you don't even
know if this was a good move.
So maybe it was not
even a good move.
And you're learning something
that was not a good move,
and you're labeling
it as a good move.
And second, you're actually only
getting partial information,
meaning you don't have
the information of what's
in the person's mind and
what strategy they're
trying to execute.
So your store-- you're
looking at a single example
among a long-term strategy.
And you can't expect the
model to guess what's
the long-term strategy, because
it was just trained on x and y
and matching the inputs
to a possible output.
So you don't really
have any concept
of a strategy at that point.
It looks one off at every
decisions of the model.
Those are really good points.
The other one is the ground
truth might be ill-defined.
What I mean by that is even
the best humans in the world
do not play their
best game every day,
and even their best game
is not the ground truth.
And that creates an issue
because you're essentially
training against a target that
is off by a certain margin.
You're never going to get
better than the best human,
and the best human is
not the best possible--
executing the best possible
strategy at every point.
So you could argue, what if
we get a panel of experts
that we're monitoring,
and those are
the best players in the world.
Even with a panel of experts
that decides every move,
you still have an
ill-defined ground truth.
So that's a big issue.
Too many states in the
game, you mentioned.
And we will likely
not generalize,
which is what you
said, meaning we're
looking at one off situations.
We're not looking at
entire strategies.
And so when we
face a board state
that we've never seen before,
because the model was not
trained on strategy,
it will get stuck.
Yeah.
OK.
And this is an example
of a perfect application
for reinforcement learning,
because reinforcement
learning is all
about delayed labels
and making sequences
of good decisions.
So if you had to remember
in one sentence what's RL,
RL is making good sequences
of decisions-- sequences
of good decisions.
Sorry.
And do that automatically.
Another way to look at
it is the difference
between classic supervised
learning in RL is--
in classic supervised
learning, you teach by example.
In reinforcement
learning, you teach
by experience, which is
also a different concept.
You're not just showing cats
and non-cats to a model,
you're actually letting the
model experience an environment
until it figures out what
were the best decisions it
made and learns from them.
Some examples of reinforcement
learning applications,
I'm going to mention them.
We have gaming, of course,
that we already covered.
What are other applications
of AI where we need
good sequences of decisions?
Yes?
Autonomous driving.
Yeah, correct.
I mean, in driving, you
could argue RL could work,
and there's some RL going on.
But what you mean,
I think, is you
have some of a dynamic
planning algorithm that
allows you to strategize.
If you see a red
light ahead, you
might start slowing
down over time.
But maybe it will turn
green, so you might not
slow down completely.
This is an example of a strategy
that you need, of course.
Yeah?
Robotic controlling.
That's a great example, also
related to autonomous driving.
But imagine you want to teach
your robot to move from point A
to point B, the number
of good decisions
that the robot needs to
make in terms of moving each
of their joints is tremendous.
It's actually super
unlikely that a robot
would move from A
to B if it's not
trained to make good
sequences of decisions.
What else?
The biggest one
nobody mentioned yet.
It's not a great application.
I don't like it, but it
happens to be the biggest
one of reinforcement learning.
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE] where they
suggest [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah, advertisement.
Yeah, marketing.
You're right.
So yeah, we talked
about robotics.
Advertisement is
another example.
Advertisement is a long game.
Companies are showing you
multiple ads before you buy.
And in fact, the reason
reinforcement learning
is important is because they're
planning a strategy that
might lead a buyer to
execute a purchase over time,
and it requires a
long-term thinking.
So there's a lot of
reinforcement learning applied
to marketing, advertisement,
real-time bidding processes, et
cetera.
OK.
Clear on what RL is
and how it differs
from classic
supervised learning?
OK.
So let's put some vocabulary
around that concept.
In reinforcement learning, you
have an agent and the agent
interacts with an environment.
As the agent interacts
with the environment,
the agent will perform
certain actions
that we will denote at,
where t is the time step.
And the environment
will show you
states that transition from time
step t to time step t plus 1.
So subject to an action
at, an environment
may transition from
st to st plus 1.
You can think of the game of Go.
I take the action of putting my
black stone on a certain grid
intersection, and the
environment has changed.
It moved from-- the
state has changed.
It moved from state at time
step t to time step t plus 1,
where my stone is on the grid.
After that state update
happens, there's two things
that the agent observes.
The agent observes
an observation
that we will note
ot and a reward rt.
OK.
So those are the
vocabulary words.
And of course, the
goal of the agent
will be to maximize the rewards.
One thing to about
the observation--
we'll talk about
it a little more.
The observation sometimes
is equal to the states.
Can someone guess why we might
need two concepts instead
of a single concept?
Why is it important to have
a state and an observation?
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yes, correct.
So in some cases,
the environment
may not be fully
transparent to the user.
And so for example,
in chess or in Go,
the observation is actually
equal to the state.
You see everything
on your board.
All the information
is available to you.
If you play League of
Legends or StarCraft,
you know the concept of--
I think in English, it's
called a cloud or a fog.
I think it's the fog.
You only see certain
parts of the map
until you have
explored everything,
or until your
friends are visiting
the other parts of the map.
And so the observation
is actually
less information than the
states of the environment.
OK.
And then the last piece of
vocabulary is the transition.
When I refer to a
transition, I'll
refer of the process
of getting from state t
to state t plus 1, which
means we're in state t,
the agent takes an action at,
it observes ot and a reward rt,
and it transitions to
the next state st plus 1.
Question?
Regarding [INAUDIBLE],
are there any [INAUDIBLE]
the state is too
large to [INAUDIBLE]?
Wait.
What do you mean?
You mean, is there-- are there
examples of environment where
the state is so large that the--
Either the environment is
too large or [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah, possibly.
For computational reasons?
Yeah.
Yeah, you might have games--
I mean, look at
open World Games.
Truly, you could argue--
I don't know.
There are some games where
you might press start
and you see the
entire environment.
But who cares of what's
happening 20,000 kilometers West
of you if you're in
a certain location.
That might not
influence your strategy.
So you might actually put some
trust circle or some circle
in which you observe,
which you think
has 99% of the information
you need, possibly
for computational reasons.
That's a good point.
OK.
Let's get to a practical example
of a reinforcement learning
algorithm and
develop it together.
This example is called recycling
is good because recycling
is good, but also because it's
a simple example illustrative
of reinforcement learning.
So let's say we have a small
environment with five states.
There is a starting state marked
in brown, which is state 2.
It's our initial state.
And then on the right side--
sorry.
On the left side, you have
state 1, which is a garbage.
And it's great to
get to the garbage
because you're going to be
able to put in the garbage
the stuff that you
have in your hands.
You're trying to throw
away some garbage.
And the garbage can
happens to be there.
And so we would expect
there to be a reward.
On the other side, if you
actually go to the right,
you might pass by state
3, which is empty.
You might pass by state 4,
where there is a chocolate
packaging that is left on the
ground that you can pick up,
and it's good to pick it up.
And then on stage 5--
state 5, you have
the recycle bin,
which is more valuable
than the garbage can
because you can
recycle and you should
get better rewards for that.
So that's our game.
In this game, we
define a reward that
is associated with
the type of behaviors
that we want the
agents to learn.
And the reward is as follows.
That's just one example.
Plus 2 for throwing your
garbage in the normal can,
plus 1 for picking up
the chocolate packaging,
and plus 10 if you manage to
make it to the recycle bin.
Is it clear?
Now, the goal will be--
and that's the case in
reinforcement learning often
time to maximize the return.
We'll define
formally the return.
But think about it as
maximize the amount of rewards
that you get as you go
through this journey,
and you make your decisions.
In this specific game,
we have five states,
and there's three
types of states.
In brown is the initial states.
We have normal states, and we
have in blue, terminal states.
When you get to a terminal
state in reinforcement learning,
it will typically end the game.
It will end one
episode of the game.
You'll move to another episode.
You'll get back to the
starting state or initial state
and you'll redo another episode.
The possible actions
for agent here
are going to be fairly
simple, left and right.
And we're going to add
an additional rule that
is important, which is that
the garbage collector comes
in three minutes.
And it takes a minute to get
from one state to the other.
Why is that an important
rule to add to the game?
Can you guess?
Yeah?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
Otherwise, you just go back
and forth between stage 3
and stage 4.
You just collect a bunch
of chocolate packaging
and you never make
it to the bin.
And so it's not what we want.
Yeah.
OK.
So how do we define
the long-term return?
The long-term return
is going to be
defined as capital R,
which is the sum of rewards
with a discount.
Discount is a very
important concept
in reinforcement learning.
It's also a very natural
concept to think about.
Can you think of what the
discount would represent in
for humans?
Do you have an example
of what it could be?
Yeah?
The value of money and time.
Huh?
Yeah, the value
of money and time.
Exactly.
Or the energy that
a robot might have.
Things like that.
Yeah.
You would rather
get a $1 now than $1
in 10 years knowing that there
is some inflation, for example.
That's the example
of a discount.
And reinforcement
learning is the same.
Let's say you have a strategy
that takes so much time.
You need to discount it because
your robot might lose energy
as it going through
it, for example.
Discounts can vary, but
they stay between 0 and 1.
So what is the best strategy to
follow if gamma, the discount,
is equal to 1, meaning
time doesn't matter here
if it's longer or shorter, just
want to maximize the return?
Best strategy to follow?
And let's give it a try.
Someone who hasn't spoken yet.
Yes?
It just bounce around.
Bounce around.
But remember, the
rule of three minutes.
You can't bounce around
because you will not
get to the terminal state before
the time allotted is done.
But that would be a good idea
if this rule was not true.
What else could you do?
Any idea?
It's an easy one,
though, not too hard.
Best strategy for
gamma equals 1.
And give me also the maximum
reward you would get.
People are sleepy today.
Yeah?
Recycle.
Go recycle.
Go to the recycle.
Right.
Yeah.
That's right.
Thank you.
Right.
And then what's your-- sorry.
What's your total reward?
11.
Yeah, that's right, 11.
So that's where we
get terminal state,
and we grab our reward of 11.
Very good.
Now, assuming 0.9
for gamma, we're
going to complexify
things a little bit.
I'm going to walk you through
a very simple algorithm that
allows us to determine
the best strategy.
And we will put our
numbers in a matrix.
So for instance, we'll
define a Q-table.
And Q stands-- it's a
value function where
the name Q-learning, Q-star.
You might have heard
all of these things come
from Q-learning.
And so let's say we
have a Q-table, which
has the size of number of
states times number of actions.
So five rows, two
columns, in our case.
Every entry of the
Q-table is essentially
representing how good it is
to take action A in state B.
Do you agree that if we had
a table with these numbers,
essentially we
solved the problem?
Meaning at any point, the agent
can just look in the table.
I am in state 3.
Let's look at column 1.
That would tell me
the value of action 1.
And let's look at column 2.
It would tell me the
value of action 2.
So I have everything I
need to make my decisions.
So that table is
really the thing
you want to find
in this exercise.
Now, the way we
will find the table
is using backtracking algorithm,
where we might actually
codify the environment as a
tree and traverse the tree.
So here's what it looks like.
I start in S2 and I have
two options ahead of me.
I can go to the left where
I will get a reward of 2.
It's an immediate reward.
The immediate reward
is not discounted.
It's an immediate reward.
Remember the formula for
R. The immediate reward R0
is not discounted.
That would take me to S1.
It's a terminal state, so
there's nothing to do after.
Second option, I go to the
right, and I get a reward of 0.
That's my immediate reward,
and I end up in state 3.
State 3 is not a terminal state.
So I can go and do the
same exercise from state 3.
In state 3, I have two options.
I can go to the left where
I would see a reward of 0,
and I will end up in S2,
or I will go to the right,
and I will get an
immediate reward of plus 1.
It's an immediate reward.
We're not discounting it.
I will end up in S4.
And from S4, again, I
have two options, back
to the left to S3
with 0 reward, or
to the right with the
amazing reward of plus 10
and the terminal state of S5.
So that's my map of
immediate rewards.
That's not my discounted return.
So what we're going
to do now is we're
going to backtrack
up the tree in order
to compute the
discounted returns.
Actually, if I'm
in S3 right here,
I see that I can get an
immediate reward in S4
of plus 1, and I want to
compute my maximum return that I
can get from when I'm in S3.
My maximum return is that in
S4, I could get a plus 10.
But I need to discount that.
My discount is 0.9, so
I multiply 10 by 0.9.
What it tells me
is that from S4,
I can expect 9 plus 1, which
I get as an immediate reward
from moving from S3 to S4.
I can update this number to 10.
Meaning from S3, the
best you can hope for
is a discounted return of 10,
which is 1 plus 0.9 times 10.
Everyone follows?
Now, let's do the same
exercise one step before in S2.
In S2, I have an immediate
reward of 0 for going to S3,
or an immediate reward
of 2 for going to S1.
S1 is not going to be worth it.
We already know that
because when I'm in S3,
I can actually expect 10,
which I have to discount.
0.9 times 10 gives me 9 plus 0
immediate reward from S2 to S3.
That tells me that the
discounted return from state 2,
which is our
initial state, is 9.
Everyone follow?
Just a simple backtracking.
Now, I can copy
back this, so S3.
I know that when I'm in S3, I
can expect a 0 immediate reward
to--
sorry.
If I'm in S2, I can
expect 0 immediate reward
plus a discount times the plus
9 that I could expect in S3.
And so that gives me values
that should cover everything
that we have in this Q-table.
So I do that backtracking.
I copy paste all of that into
my Q-table all the way up here,
and this is what I get.
We essentially finished
the game at this point.
We [INAUDIBLE] at
a certain role.
So let's say I'm
in state number 3.
I look on the third
row of that Q-table.
And I see that I
have two options.
If I go back to S2, ultimately
my discounted return
will be 8.1.
If I actually go
to S4 on the right,
I will get 10
because I will get 1
plus 0.9 times 10, which is 10.
So this is a toy
example, but it tells you
that if you were
able to backtrack
through the entire
environment, you
will be able to build
a massive Q-table
and you will be able to
give it to your agent
to make its decisions.
Yeah?
What is the [INAUDIBLE]?
Sorry.
Can you repeat?
What is the time remaining
from the [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah.
Here, I'm simplifying.
I'm not considering
the time remaining.
But in practice, you--
if I remove the time
component, so I remove the fact
that there's a three-minute
deadline before the garbage
collector comes, then this would
be slightly more difficult,
because you would have to do
a time series, essentially,
of adding the discount times
the reward that you collect.
Yeah, but I'm simplifying
here, and that's
why I use the three-minute rule.
Any question on the Q-table?
Super.
OK.
So this was the Q-table.
And in fact, we can put
together our strategy
for gamma equals 0.9.
The best strategy
is still the same.
You go to the right.
And you can expect
a return of nine.
Now, one of the most important
concepts in reinforcement
learning is this equation on
the board called the Bellman
optimality equation.
Oftentimes, you'll see it noted
as Q star of state s and action
a equals r plus gamma times
the max of that same function
applied to s prime, a prime.
Let me explain this
equation for you,
because it's super important.
This equation is called
the optimality equation
because your optimal Q-table
will follow this equation.
If you have finished
the game, this equation
can be applied to any
state action pair,
and it will still be true.
The intuition behind
why the Bellman equation
is the optimality
equation is that if you're
in a-- if you have the
perfect Q function, Q-table,
and you're in a certain state
and you perform a certain action
a, you will observe a reward.
And this reward will--
you have taken an action.
So you would be in a new state.
And from that new state, you
could repeat what you just did.
And because you've done
the backtracking and stuff
like that, you will
get this equation
to be true because
it's the reward
plus discount times
the best next action
that you could be taking.
Does that make sense?
Any questions on that?
That's exactly the backtracking
that we did by the way.
Immediate reward plus discount
times the best possible action
that you can take in
the next state, s prime.
The last concept I'll cover
in terms of vocabulary
is the policy.
The policy is the function
that given your state,
is going to tell you what to do.
And in Q-learning, the
way this policy is defined
is argmax of Q star
across the action.
So essentially what it
says is, look in the table
and look at a certain state s.
You want the policy, which
is what you should do.
It's the function that
tells you our best strategy.
You just look at the
two possible actions,
which one has the highest Q
value, and select that action.
That's it.
This is a very simple
example, but it's
the core of Q-learning
that later on you
will use policies widely.
There's a lot of reinforcement
learning algorithms.
But this concept of
understanding the policies,
the function telling us our
best strategy in Q-learning,
it's the argmax of the best
q-value in a given state.
It tells you which
action to take.
That's the core thing
you need to understand.
So remember this
Bellman equation
because we're going
to reuse it in a bit.
The main issue with this
approach of a Q table
is that state and action
spaces can be super large.
And having a matrix that you
discover through backtracking
and where every time you
want to do an action,
you have to look up the given
states, the possible action,
it becomes impossible.
Imagine you using this algorithm
for the game of Go, where
there's so many states, there
are so many possible actions.
You can put your stone
anywhere on the board.
You can imagine how
big this matrix becomes
and how impossible it is to use.
So that's our problem.
And that's the moment where
deep learning comes into play.
So let's look at it.
Actually, before I
go there, I'm just
going to cover some vocabulary.
We said the environment, the
agent, the state, the action,
the reward, the total return,
and the discount factor.
We learned all of that.
We saw that the Q-table is the
matrix of entries representing
how good is it to take
action a in state s.
And the policy is
the function that
tells us what's the
best strategy to adopt.
And the Bellman
equation is satisfied
by the optimal Q-table.
So let's get to deep
Q-learning, which
is what I was
about to say, is we
are going to frame the
problem slightly differently.
So instead of using
a Q-table, we're
going to use the fact
that neural networks are
universal function
approximators.
And we're going to define a
Q function that's essentially
a neural network, so
that the function can
take a state s and an
action a and tell you how
good that action is in state s.
So instead of a
lookup in a matrix,
you just run a forward
pass in a neural network,
and it gives you the answer.
That feels like a better
solution for games
where there's a lot of
states and a lot of actions.
So here is a same
problem statement.
In the past, we
looked for a Q-table.
And this time, we will
look for a neural network.
One of the things
we're going to do
is to define the output
layer to have two outputs.
So given a certain
state as input,
think about it as a one hot
vector encoding the state.
So this one is the
example of state 2, 01000.
If you pass state 2 in this Q
function with multiple layers,
it will give you two outputs,
one output that corresponds
to Q of s action right, and
the other one Q of s action
left, because it's
the two actions.
If we had more
actions to take, we
would just increase
the output layer,
and we might have many more
neurons in the output layer.
So the big question
is, how the hell
are we going to
train that network?
Because we're not in
classic supervised learning.
We don't have labels.
So this one is a hard
question, but what would you
do given-- we don't have
traditional x and y pairs.
How are you going to train
these neural network?
Because remember
at the beginning,
this neural network
will give you garbage.
It will take a state s and it
might tell you go to the left
or to the right, but
it's completely random.
So how are you going
to tune it to the level
where it makes really
good decisions?
Yes?
We assume based on
prior knowledge.
Assume based on some
Tell me more.
If you have-- people
will [INAUDIBLE]
if you have some
idea [INAUDIBLE].
So what are the things we know
about this problem right now?
What are the rules of the game
that we could use in order to--
I'm seeing what you say.
You say we could estimate
what good looks like,
but based on what?
We reduce [INAUDIBLE].
OK, so reward structure.
You're saying that's one
thing we have in every game.
We have a reward
structure for every state.
That definitely should
be used in order
to estimate the good-- what
a good decision looks like.
Yeah, the problem is
not in every state
you will see a reward.
And if you look at
many games like Go,
you might not see a
reward until 50 moves.
So what do you do in this case?
Yes?
Can we run through
a bunch of actions
and see what the output
is, and get more data
to train the neural net?
Yeah.
So you could.
You're actually bringing
up a tree search.
You go down the tree, you
do every possible action,
and then you backtrack.
Not every possible action.
So which actions?
Trying to spread it out.
OK.
That's-- we're getting there.
So first possibility is
we just go down the tree.
In the game of Go, you could
put your stone everywhere.
So the tree already start
by a 13 by 13 options.
And then it's
exponentially grows.
Impossible.
It's intractable.
But what you said is, what if
there are certain actions that
are more likely than others?
Do we need actually to
explore the entire tree?
What's this?
What are you using when
you're saying that?
How do you determine
what action might
be better than another one?
Expected return.
We're getting close.
Yeah.
But how do you know
the expected return
without going through
the tree ones, at least?
You can estimate [INAUDIBLE].
OK, you can estimate
it using what?
Is it an equation?
Yeah, maybe.
So that's exactly what
we're going to do actually,
but we're going to use
the Bellman equation.
Because there are two things
we know about this problem.
We know the reward structure,
which you brought up.
And we also know that the
perfect Q function will
follow the Bellman equation.
That we know as well.
At the end, the Bellman
equation should be respected.
Meaning for every
state, if you want
to know the Q value of that
state given an action, the way
you will get that is you will
look at the immediate reward
plus a discount times the best
Q value from the next state
across all actions.
That equation will be respected.
So those are the
only information
we have, and we're going
to use them drastically
to define our labels and mimic
a classic supervised learning
approach.
So here's what we have.
We have our neural network.
We have Qs to the left
and Qs to the right that
represent how good it
is to go to the left
in that state versus the right.
And then I've pasted
the Bellman equation
on top right of the screen.
We're going to define
a loss function.
So let's say for the
sake of simplicity
because those are
scalar values that we'll
use L2 loss, quadratic loss,
that compares a certain label
y to a certain Q value of a
state in a certain action.
So what we would like is to
minimize this loss function,
meaning y, and the Q value for
a given action in a given state
is as close as
possible to each other.
And we're going to leverage the
reward and the Bellman equation.
So let's do two things.
Right now, we don't have a y.
So in supervised learning, you
will have a picture of a cat.
If there's a cat,
the y is 1 or 0.
Here, we don't have a y.
So we have to come up with an
estimate of a good y, at least
better than random.
So let's say at
this point in time,
when I send a state
s in the network,
it turns out that Q
of going to the left
is higher than Q of going to the
right, which means that today,
at that moment, the
Q function tells me
it's better to go to the
left than to go to the right.
That is random at the beginning.
It's completely random.
So what I'm going
to do is I'm going
to use as my target value y the
immediate reward that I observe
on the left, plus gamma times
the best Q value that I can get.
So the best action that I
could take in the next step
based on my current Q value.
That's very important.
So remember, this target is off.
It's not a perfect target,
but it's better than nothing.
Meaning not only it
tells us, hey, there
is a good reward to the left.
We should consider
that in saying
that might be a good
move because we're
seeing an immediate reward.
But on top of that, we also know
that at the end of training,
the Q value should follow
the Bellman equation.
So why don't we set the target
as the Bellman equation?
So we add the discounted
maximum future reward
when you are in the next state.
So you were in state s.
You go to the left.
Now, you're in
state s next left.
And you look again
at your Q values,
and you select the best one.
Then you add that number here.
So there is actually two
forward paths in that process.
There's one forward path where
you send the state s in Q.
And you look at the two
options, left or right.
And you're like, OK,
I'm going to the left.
And then you're like, I'm
going to compare that value
to a target y.
But to get that target y, I
need to do another forward path.
So I take my action left.
I perform it.
I get an s prime state, s next.
And I send that s next
into the Q-network.
I look at the two
options I have.
I pick the best one and I add
it here with the discount.
So fundamentally, what's
happening is the following,
is we have a Q-network that's
random at the beginning.
It has never
observed the rewards.
We just know that at some
point, it will get to the Q--
it will get to a perfect policy.
It will get to a
perfect Q function.
But the best we can do right
now is to say as a guide
to our agent, we will look
at the immediate reward,
and we will look at the
Bellman equation, which
should tell us a better estimate
than where we are right now.
And we will try to catch
up to that estimate.
And then we do that
again and again.
So remember, every time
your Q gets better,
it gets better for the
next state as well.
So the Bellman equation
tells you estimated
with the second forward path.
And you just keep getting
better and better as you're
observing more rewards.
Can I just go into
a loop in which
the next state [INAUDIBLE]?
How would you describe the loop?
Right now, imagine this
going to the right,
like the next, state
going to the right.
Yeah.
For going to the right,
you again need the target.
Yeah, you would
stop at that point.
So what-- yeah, that's
a good question.
I'll show you how we
fix certain things,
but you do only one step.
Meaning you have your
Q-value at this point.
And it tells you go to the left.
And you just want to target y.
So what you do is you put left
and you look at your next state.
You forward propagate
your next state.
You look at the two options.
You pick the best.
You don't go further.
You just use that one step.
You look one step
ahead essentially.
You don't look
multiple steps ahead.
You could, but it would be more
computationally heavy to do
one more step again, and so on.
Yeah?
It seems like you're
learning to function locally.
Some [INAUDIBLE]
information about the reward
is coming from what the reward
would think [INAUDIBLE].
So if people know how fast that
[INAUDIBLE] is, the [INAUDIBLE].
It will typically be a function
of the environment, the state
space, how long it
will take to converge.
But you're perfectly right that
as the Q function gets better,
the estimate y also gets better.
So the two things
get better together,
because the y is based
on the Q function.
And if the state
space is massive,
you might have a very difficult
time training this model.
There's better approaches
that we'll see later.
Yeah.
Right.
There was a question there.
So if you-- I'm sorry.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
So here I'm just saying-- let's
say when you send state s in Q,
the left happens to
be higher than right.
But the same happens
on the other side.
Let's say the left
is worse than right.
Then what you will do is
you will define your target
y as the reward that you
observe on the right.
Plus, from the next
state of having
gone to the right, what's
the best action and what's
the Q value for that pair?
And then it will give you
the target for that scenario.
So one complication
with this training
is that when you want
to differentiate L,
so you want to perform
a backup propagation,
you want to take
the derivative of L
with respect to the
parameters of the network,
you want y to be a fixed thing.
Because in supervised learning,
y is not differentiable.
It's just a fixed number 0
or 1 or a certain number.
So here, we're
going to simplify.
And we're going to
say this term that
is dependent on the Q network.
So technically, this
term has parameters.
So if you actually differentiate
it, it will give you a value.
We'll just hold it fixed.
So we say, we do
use our Q network
to perform an estimate
of our y, but we will not
differentiate it.
We will say it's not--
it's fixed.
Yeah?
Is that why we discount
this [INAUDIBLE]?
Because, going back to
the reason we discount,
it's like the value of time.
It's like you
probably want to say
if you can win the
game in 10 moves,
win it in 10 moves
rather than 100 moves.
Or if you can get $1
today, get $1 today
rather than in 10 years.
All of that is why we
have a discount here.
And the discount
is a hyperparameter
that you would define as
well, that would influence
the strategy of your agent.
Can you show once more how
the 4 pass the [INAUDIBLE]?
We're going to see that after.
I'm going to do a concrete
example, because it's
a little complicated.
Yeah?
It's the law function, right?
Qo s to the y?
No.
It's a good point.
It's not that.
It's just of Q of--
it's a 2 by 2.
It's a 1 by 2.
So you have left and right.
I was just going
down the first case.
So I put the state left.
Yeah?
What if there's law that's
not fixed [INAUDIBLE]?
What if the rewards
are not fixed?
I mean, in most games we're
going to see right now,
the rewards are
going to be fixed
by the designer of the game, the
human that's designing the game.
In practice, you could have a
separate function that actually
comes up with the reward.
We're going to see
an example later
in the lecture, where
the reward might
be different in
different scenarios.
And there's a function
or a sometimes
called a critic that
determines what's
the reward in a certain state.
OK, this is the--
one last question.
And then we'll move
because we're going
to see a concrete example.
It's going to be clear.
So when we like hold
it fixed for backprop,
is that what differentiates
this from iterating through all
of the possible [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah.
So instead of doing the
backtracking down the tree
and going over
everything, we're saying--
we're going to limit ourselves
to just picking the best
action based on our current
understanding of the network.
You see, my network is kind
of intelligent, not great.
We're in the middle of training.
It says that I should
go to the left.
And then if I look at the next
state when I'm in the left,
it says, I should
go to the right.
I will trust it because
it's the best I have,
best estimate I have,
but I will discount that.
And then if you
keep repeating that,
it turns out that not only
your estimate gets better,
but your model gets trained, and
then ultimately both together
get to an optimality equation.
So it's a funky concept, right?
But you get it.
We're going to see examples.
OK.
So then once you have been
able to use the Bellman
equation to estimate
your targets,
you perform a classic
back propagation.
And you update the
parameters of the network,
and you repeat that process.
Here is-- concretely, if you
were to code it in pseudocode,
here is what it would look like
to train a neural agent using
Q-learning.
We start by initializing
our Q-network parameters.
So initialization.
It's random at first.
Then we will loop over episodes.
As a reminder, episodes are
one full game from start
to terminal state.
Within an episode, we're going
to start from the initial state
s and we're going to
loop over time steps
until we reach a terminal state.
So within one time step,
here is what we will do.
We'll forward propagate the
state s in the Q-network.
We will execute the action a
that has the maximum Q value.
We will observe a
reward and we will also
observe a next state s prime.
We will use that s prime to
compute our target y by forward
propagating s prime
in the Q-network
and then computing
our loss function.
And based on that, we
will use gradient descent
to update the parameters
of the network.
It should be simpler
looked at like that, right?
All right.
So this is the
vanilla Q-learning.
So to summarize,
again, the one--
the main difference is that
we don't have a target.
And we use our own network
to estimate the targets.
And the rewards are what's going
to help us get better over time.
By the way, it's OK if you
don't understand everything.
This is an entire class at
Stanford, an entire quarter
of studying that type of stuff.
So we're trying to get
the basics within an hour
and a half, two hours.
OK, let's go a little
further now together
and apply that to
an actual game.
So here's the game.
It's called Breakout.
We want to destroy
all the bricks.
Who has played
breakout in the past?
Only a few.
OK, good.
So you have a paddle that
you control and you are
trying to destroy the bricks.
If the ball gets past
your paddle, you lost.
And if the bricks are
all destroyed, you won.
That's it.
Let's do it together.
What is the input
of our Q-network?
What would you use as input?
Remember-- yeah?
The entire screen.
Entire screen.
OK, let's do that.
So I take-- I define
that as the state s,
which is the input
to my Q network.
What's the output
of the Q-network?
Yes?
For the input, do we have
to do that on screen?
Good question.
We get there.
I'm going to ask you.
But do we have to look
at the full screen?
The answer is no,
but we'll see why.
What's the output?
Yeah?
The game score.
No, but we're going
to talk about the game
score in the back.
Like the cool fix
gradient polymer.
Yeah, let's talk about
the output first,
and then we'll talk
about the stuff we
can get rid of on the inputs.
But what's the output?
Yeah?
It's the movement
of the fix points.
The actions?
Yes.
Yeah, the actions.
So yeah, it will be
the Q values associated
with the actions in state s.
Remember, it's a Q function.
So the output is-- we
need one value for left,
one value for right
and one value for idle.
You could make this game
more complicated and say,
we have eight actions.
We have a little bit to the
left, a lot to the left,
a lot more to the left, if
you had multiple buttons.
But let's simplify
and say three actions.
Either you don't move,
you move to the left,
or you move to the right.
So these are the outputs.
So now, let's get to the
question of the screen.
Do we need the entire screen?
So you were saying
something earlier.
Right.
So you will get [INAUDIBLE].
OK.
So you say you need the
tray and the bricks.
I would argue you need more
because there's the walls.
And I guess that you could--
if you're an expert player,
you could where the walls are.
But generally, you need
a little more than that.
What would be obviously
things we can get rid of
and why would we do that?
The background, probably
the walkthrough at the top.
OK, the score at the top.
Who would remove the
score at the top?
But half.
Why would you not remove it?
[INAUDIBLE]
Why would you remove it?
Because the point [INAUDIBLE].
OK.
You want to always win.
So the score doesn't matter.
It's true.
We would remove the score.
So you could actually
crop the top.
You could also crop the bottom.
I mean, if it passed
the paddle, you
don't care about the few
pixels at the bottom.
You could get rid of them.
It is not always true.
There are games where
the score matters.
And in fact, I like
football, soccer.
In soccer, if you're 1-0
up, you can park the bus.
So your strategy is dependent
of the score that you have.
You wouldn't park the
bus if you're losing 1-0.
Parking the bus, meaning
you ask every player
to come back and defend.
If you're losing, you would
actually do the opposite.
You would go all out attack.
So in certain games,
you want the scores.
In others, you don't want.
And so it's part of the
designer, the AI engineer that's
working on that to determine
what information we need
and what we don't need.
What else could we do to
reduce the dimensionality
of the problem and make
our computation faster?
Probably just
remove the channels.
Yeah, remove the RGB channels.
So we do grayscale, essentially.
That's true.
Here, you actually
don't need the colors.
It's just nice as a user for
user experience purposes.
You don't need-- I don't think
there's different points based
on the bricks that you destroy.
It's all the same.
Actually, funny
enough, this algorithm
was used by DeepMind to
play a lot of Atari games.
And they did a
single pre-processing
where they removed the
channels because they
said it doesn't matter.
Turns out in one of the games,
I think it was SeaQuest,
I forgot which one, the fish
disappeared when you do that.
And so that game didn't work.
The agent couldn't crack it.
Because they thought that
the same pre-processing could
apply to every
game, but actually,
they had to make a slight tweak.
Question.
If you remove RGB to
reduce the [INAUDIBLE],
and then you also didn't
want to [INAUDIBLE].
Correct.
All right.
So just to recap,
you could do it
even better by using a
low-dimensional representation
of this game that
describes the game.
It's true.
But because we want to use
a single algorithm for 50
plus Atari games, we'll say
the human sees the screen,
we'll just give the screen,
and it will probably
scale better, essentially.
But you're perfectly
right, if you
were working on only that game.
OK.
So let's do that.
We'll do pre-processing.
There's one last thing
that nobody mentioned,
which is history.
Because in fact, if you
get only one screen,
you don't know where
the ball is going.
So actually, you
can solve the game.
And the way you fix
that is by giving
a history of multiple screens.
For example, four screens,
so that you see the direction
that the ball is going in.
So our preprocessing function
is called phi of s, let's say.
And phi of s is a mix of--
you might do-- convert
to grayscale, reduce
the dimension, the
height and width
and also add the
history of four frames.
And that should be enough.
It turns out in
most games you will
need the history, a
little bit of history
to where the ball is going.
In this example, the opposite
would be the velocity vector
of the ball.
Yeah, you could replace--
exactly.
You could replace the
history, so multiple screen,
by just adding the gradients
or the velocity of where
the ball is going.
That's true.
But would it scale
to every game?
It turns out this-- because we
know humans look at the Atari
machine, and they
look at pixels,
this would be more likely
to scale to every game.
Think about a game where--
actually SeaQuest is a good
game or Space Invaders,
where you have multiple
enemies coming at you.
Then you would need to
change your pre-processing
to take into account the
velocity of all these enemies,
so it wouldn't
work the same way.
While if you actually
give the pixels,
you actually, from
the pixels, get
the velocity of all your
enemies and the direction
they're going in.
So this is our pre-processing.
I'm going to refer
to it as phi of s.
And our deep Q-network
architecture,
because we're
working with pixels,
is going to be a
convolutional neural network.
Don't worry if you haven't
learned it yet in the class,
but it's a bunch of conv
and ReLU activations.
And then we end with a
fully connected layer
that gives us the three Q values
for the different actions.
So nothing special here.
Now, we're going to go back
to our vanilla training.
So this one that we
saw together earlier.
And we're going to look at tips
to train reinforcement learning
algorithms.
Those tips are not
specific to Q-learning.
Some of them are applied to
a lot more than Q-learning.
And they're very
important to know.
And they're part of the
reason reinforcement learning
has worked better in
the last few years.
So one of the things
that's pretty simple
that we forgot to do is the
pre-processing that we just did.
So anywhere I had
an s, I'm going
to instead run s through
the pre-processing step.
I'm going to use phi of s.
So I initialize instead
of s with phi of s.
I start from the
initial state phi of s.
And then I forward
propagate phi of s.
I get the Q of that
pre-processed state in action a
and et cetera, et cetera.
And then when I
get my next state--
so let's say I look at my
current pre-processed state.
I forward propagated once.
I see the three Q values, in
our case, the two Q values.
One of them was better than
the other action, right?
Then I get my next
state S prime.
I want to pre-process
that state as well.
OK.
So that's pretty
straightforward.
You just replace all of that.
The second thing
we forgot to do is
to keep track of
the terminal states.
In our pseudocode, there is
no concept of terminal state.
It's pretty easy to add.
You would probably just
do an if else statement.
You would create a Boolean
to detect terminal state.
So let's say your Boolean
is terminal equals false.
And then as you loop over the
time step of a single episode,
every time you're
going to check,
is the state that I'm going
in based on the action I'm
taking a terminal state?
If it's a terminal state,
then get out of the loop.
There's nothing else after.
The one thing that you
need to be careful of
is if it's a
terminal state, then
your target is not
the Bellman equation,
it's just the immediate reward.
Remember, you get to
the terminal state.
You get a reward of 10.
There is no Bellman
equation to apply it.
It's just 10.
It's immediate reward.
There's no discount, et cetera.
OK.
So these are fairly
easy changes.
Now, we're going to look
at a new method that will
enable more data efficiency.
It's called experience replay.
One of the-- a couple of
issues with the way we've
been training so far
is one, the correlation
of successive screens.
So imagine in the
Atari game, you
have the ball that's
in the top left corner
and it's traveling to the
bottom right of the screen.
You have many, many time steps
that are essentially the same.
It's all the ball traveling
in the same place.
So you're actually
training repetitively
on something that is
not that meaningful.
You don't need to
just train on a batch.
The equivalent in
supervised learning
is let's say you're trying to
differentiate cats and dogs,
and you train on a
mini batch of cats.
Then you train on a
mini batch of dogs.
mini batch of cats.
Then you will never converge.
It will just index too
much on cats and then index
too much on dogs.
So you want to add some
experience replay concept
that we'll see in order to
create more mixes in the data
and get more diversity.
The other thing
that is important
is in our current
training process,
we are not reusing our data.
Like you experience something.
You immediately train on it.
You never see it again, unless
you re-experience the same thing
sometimes in the future, which
might or might not happen.
Experience replay
is going to help
us to keep
experiences in memory,
and maybe retrain on
them on a regular basis,
so that one experience might
be useful multiple times, which
intuitively makes sense.
Maybe you do an experience,
you get an amazing reward,
and you don't want to forget it.
You want to retrain the
model on a regular basis.
It's more data efficiency.
So here's what it looks like.
The current way we were
training was we're in a state--
I'm just going to state
instead of pre-process state,
but it's pre-processed.
We're in a state s.
We perform action a.
We get a reward r and we
get into the next state.
From that next state, we
perform another action a prime.
We get a reward r prime
and we get into a second,
and so on and so on.
And each of these would
be called one experience.
It's one iteration
of gradient descent.
It's one experience.
So right now we're training
on these experiences.
So the training looks
like I train on E1.
I update my parameters.
Then I train on E2.
Then I train on E3.
I update my parameters.
Those are highly
correlated because they're
part of the same episode.
And as I was saying, with the
ball traveling in one direction,
that might actually not
be that helpful to train
on all of these.
So instead, what we'll do is
we'll use experience replay
where we will collect
our first experience,
but instead of
training on it, we
will put it in a memory
called the replay memory
D. We'll put it in there.
And then at every step, we
will sample from that memory
to decide what to train on.
So of course, at the
beginning, if we just
have one experience
in the memory,
we will train on
that experience.
But over time, you will see
that we get more diversity
and reuse out of
our experiences.
So for example, let's
say I experience E2.
I put it into memory.
And then instead
of training on E2,
I'm going to randomly
sample from the memory.
I might get E1 or
I might get E2.
Then I experience E3, and
I put it in the memory,
and I might get
one of the three.
This is the vanilla
experience replay.
In practice, there
is more methods
like prioritized sweeping,
which might tell you
which experience
you want to weigh.
Maybe some experiences
had a higher gradient.
So you want to prioritize
them more often.
Things like that.
So all in all, this is
what our training looks
like with experience replay.
We experience E1.
We train on E1.
Then the next training
iteration is not on E2,
it's on a sample from
E1 and E2, either or.
The third experience is then
put in the replay memory,
but we don't train on it.
We train on a sample from
whatever is in the replay
memory, and we repeat.
And that is more sample--
more efficient.
It allows more reusability
and less cross correlation
in our training batch.
OK.
So that's called replay memory.
And you can use it with
mini batch gradient descent.
Note that you still
experience in the direction
that the game is played.
We still go and take
the action as expected.
We just don't necessarily
update our model parameter
based on the action
that we ended up taking.
We put it in the replay memory.
We may train on it later.
OK.
So here is how it modifies
our vanilla setup.
We've added an
experience from state
s to state s prime
to the replay memory.
Let me walk you
through it again.
Within one time step, we
forward propagate our state
into the Q-network.
We execute the best
action given the Q-values.
This gives us a
reward and next state.
The next state is pre-processed.
And then instead of
training on that,
instead of training, we
just add that transition
to the replay memory.
And instead, we sample randomly
a mini batch of transition
from the replay memory.
And we train on those.
And we redo the same
thing again and again.
Yes?
As the replay memory play
biased towards the start
of the game for
everything, are you
more likely to
replay start game?
If you're learning something,
you would sometimes
want [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah.
You would within one episode.
But if you play
multiple chess game,
your replay memory will
get already bigger.
So then you would see
some end game, some middle
of the game, some early games.
And in practice,
it's actually useful
because you might imagine that
in a chess game, all of us--
let's say, if you're
a beginner, you
see a lot beginning
of the games.
You actually-- people
that are beginners,
they're good at openings,
but they're bad at endgames
because they don't get to
play a lot of endgames.
Well, that type of
approach could be useful.
You can retrain on
endgames more often.
And a more advanced version
of the replay memory
would also weigh the
experience in the replay memory
based on how much the
gradient is going to be.
So if you have an
experience that actually
was super insightful,
you can wait
higher so that you prioritize
grabbing it and retraining
on it, essentially.
So let's say you
blunder in chess.
You might actually want to resee
that blunder later so that you
don't do it again.
OK, so these were all
the different methods.
Another one that's very
intuitive and very important
is when--
during the training process,
our agent gets stuck,
gets stuck in a local minima.
Here is how it would
work in practice.
You start in initial
state S1, and you
have three states ahead of you.
If you take action
a1, you go to state 2,
which is a terminal state.
If you take-- and you
get a reward of 0.
If you take action a2, you get
to S3, also a terminal state,
and you get a reward of 1.
And if you get action a3, you
get to state 4 terminal state
with a reward of 1,000.
So of course, to
us, it's obvious
that we would want to
explore the state number 4.
It's pretty obvious.
In practice, let's
say you update--
you initialize your network.
And in the first forward
path, that's what you get.
First forward path,
the network is random.
You get Q value.
For action 1, 0.5.
For action 2, 0.4.
For action 3, 0.3.
What does that mean?
It means the agent is saying,
I'm going to go to action 1.
So I take action 1 and I see
an immediate reward of 0.
Because it's a terminal state,
the Bellman equation thing
doesn't happen.
I just have the
immediate reward,
which becomes my target y.
And so I perform a
gradient descent update
to say this Q value
should have been 0.
So I convert this Q value to 0.
Now, second try.
This time, the Q value
is saying take action 2.
It's the highest Q value.
I take action 2.
I have an immediate
reward ahead of me.
That's one.
Because it's a
terminal state, there
is no second discounted
future reward term.
So I just take y equals 1.
I perform my gradient descent
update and this converts to 1.
And then third time, the agent
is still saying go to a2,
go to the-- take
action A2 reward of 1.
Good.
That's what you predicted.
Nothing to do.
Just keep going.
We're done with training.
We're stuck.
We never visit the state we
actually wanted to visit.
So that wouldn't work for us.
We will never visit that state
using our current algorithm.
Does that make sense why we
wouldn't ever visit that state?
In practice, this
is a big issue.
The analogy of this concept of
exploration versus exploitation
is when every day you take your
bike and you cross a campus,
you have a favorite route.
And it turns out that the
more you take that route,
the better you get every time.
It get a little faster.
Maybe your turn is
faster or something,
or you can predict
how many people
are going to be
at that roundabout
and you know how to
take it in the wide way.
So you go faster.
We've all done that.
That's exploitation.
You exploit what you already
know and you get better at it.
But maybe there's another
route that you're not
thinking of that's pretty--
instead of going North
from campus, you go South.
And maybe it might be better.
You will never
see it because you
don't have the courage
or the patience to do it.
That's the difference between
exploration and exploitation.
In practice, a good model
would be able to handle both,
to exploit 22 to
exploit, to explore
when it needs to explore.
The way we do it in
practice in our pseudocode
is to inject some randomness.
So for example, when we
are looping over time step
with probability epsilon, let's
say 5%, take a random action.
So from time to
time, on average,
one time every 20 times,
you take a random action,
it will allow you to
visit maybe a new path.
The analogy in chess is you
might use a creative move
from time to time that
might be worse today,
but might allow you
to learn something
and to get better over time.
Yeah?
Is that-- the example
you've just covered,
could we resolve that by
just setting the initial Q
values to infinity?
Setting the-- couldn't
we resolve this problem
by setting the initial
values into infinity?
Well, the problem if you set
the initial values to infinity--
so you would say, instead
of randomly initializing
your network, you
initialize it in a way
that the outputs are
equal to infinity.
Yeah.
So that we wouldn't
get the issue
of where the Q value
of actionscript states
are with that.
Well, in practice, if the
three Q values are infinity,
then you can't make a
decision on the spot.
So you're saying just
pick one randomly?
Because if the
three are infinity,
you can't decide which
one to take, right?
Right.
And also, if it's infinity,
and the reward is 1--
I mean, if it's a really large
number and the reward is 1.
Your gradient is going
to be massive, right?
So it's going to--
I guess the loss function
is going to be massive.
And I don't know.
I imagine it will be
really hard to train it.
But in practice, you start
with a random initialization
because this might
be one example.
But if in the game of
chess, actually, the reward
is 1 at the end
and 0 all the time.
Or maybe the reward
is 1,000 at the end.
And when you lose your rook,
it's a negative reward.
You can't predict what the
reward structure is going to be.
You want an agent that
is able to adapt to it.
And it's better to
find a method that
can scale to different
environments, essentially.
OK.
So this was epsilon
greedy action, which
is adding some randomness
with probability epsilon,
take a random action.
OK.
So adding all our
techniques because we
get good at training
reinforcement learning
algorithms, this
is what we have.
We initialize our
Q-network parameters.
We have a random network.
We initialize our
replay memory D.
And then we loop over episodes.
We start from an initial state.
We create a Boolean that allows
us to detect terminal states.
With probability epsilon, we're
going to take a random action.
Otherwise, we're going
to follow what we know,
which is forward propagate
the state in the Q-network.
Take the action that
has the highest Q value.
That allows you to observe
a reward in the next state.
Take that next state.
Forward propagate it again.
And then instead of--
oh, no.
Sorry, sorry.
Observe that next state.
Add it to the replay memory.
Sample from the replay memory,
and then train on that sample.
And in the process,
you will need
to do another forward
path because you
need to estimate
your target y using
the immediate reward
plus the Bellman equation
plus the discounted
future reward.
OK, are you experts
at Q-learning?
OK, good.
Sounds good.
And here is where
we get at the end.
You can claim proudly,
you have trained an Atari.
It's not that complicated as you
can see, other than the Bellman
equation piece.
It turns out the
agent has discovered
that it can send the
ball on the back,
and it's actually much easier
to finish the game like that,
which is quite interesting.
A good player would know
that you can dig a tunnel,
and you can finish the game
without too much issues.
Yeah?
How do you quantify the results
of the edge of the repository?
How do you quantify
when the game has ended?
How good the model becomes
after the [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah.
Well, first, you
would start seeing
the model get two good
rewards as it play,
like it manages to get
really good rewards.
While earlier, it might not.
And so that's probably your best
guess for how good the model is.
In practice, if
you're AlphaGo, you
can also test it against the
best humans in the world,
and you can observe that they're
losing against the model.
But then you have a bunch
of different chess engines,
and some of them are way,
way better than others.
They have different structure.
Maybe they're both based
on reinforcement learning.
And at the end, they maximize
both of their rewards.
Right.
So how do you know which model
is actually doing better?
You can get them
to play together.
So you have no idea.
You just have one.
No.
You could actually
monitor the loss function.
And look at, is the
Bellman equation respected?
If the Bellman
equation is respected,
then your model is
really, really good.
And then we're going
to see an example
of competitive self-play,
where you get the model to play
against other models.
And then over time,
as you watch them
play for thousands
and thousands of time,
you can tell which model
is ahead of another one.
You can then copy,
paste the best model
into the other
models, and then make
them play again for many times.
And because you have the
epsilon greedy approach,
one of the models
is naturally going
to get better than the others
because of the randomness
that you add.
OK, let's look at
a few examples,
and then we'll spend
20 minutes on the RLHF.
Here are other examples.
This is Pong, which is 1V1.
SeaQuest, which is
an underwater game.
And then the one that's
maybe more of you
know, Space Invaders,
very popular game as well.
So the impressive
thing that they showed
is that you can actually
solve many games
with the exact same algorithm.
No tweaks, which is
quite impressive.
Let's go a little further and
talk about advanced topics.
Here is a game called
Montezuma's Revenge.
This game is particular
because you're controlling
a little character right here.
And this character is
trying to go and grab,
let's say, this key right here.
And it has some
obstacles or some enemies
that it needs to take care of.
What do you think is going to
be an issue if we apply what
we just learned to this game?
What makes this game
especially hard in comparison
to, let's say, chess or Go?
Yes?
The reward is very delayed.
Yeah.
If you start with a
random network, what
are the chances that the
network is going to figure out
that-- to get to
the key, it actually
should go in the
opposite direction.
It should go in the
It should jump down here.
It should catch the rope.
The rope will probably allow the
character to go to the ladder.
It goes down the ladder.
It has to go jump up this enemy.
My guess is it's in an enemy.
I'm not sure, but I think it's
an enemy because of the color.
And that in gaming,
if it was green,
it might not have been an
enemy, but it's gray or red,
it might be an enemy.
And then go up the
ladder and grab the key.
The chance is very
low that the agent
is going to make that successive
good decisions to get there.
You're right.
Why is it easier for a human
to actually solve that game?
Intuition.
Intuition, prior knowledge.
So for example, when
you look at this game,
even if you have
never played it,
my guess is you would know
you can go down the ladder,
because you what a ladder is.
Or you can see this little
rope and you're like,
I'm going to catch the rope.
I'm going to jump and
go to the other side.
And you look at
this little monster
and you're like, I better
not touch this monster.
Or if anything, I will
jump on top of it,
because you've played
Mario, let's say.
So all of this is
human intuition.
Sometimes you would call as
a baby survival instinct.
You throw the baby in the
water and suddenly it flips
and it can swim.
Those are things that
are, to a certain extent,
encoded in our DNA.
But at the very least,
encoded in our experience
of doing other things that have
nothing to do with this game.
And so the problem here is
called imitation learning is,
is there a better way
to start our network
than a random initialization
that allows the network to,
for example, guess
that this is a ladder?
And it turns out
that if the network
knows that, it will be more
likely to get to the reward
first, and then learn
from that reward
and then get better over time.
The other part that can also
use human knowledge, which
is what we're going
to see together,
is reinforcement learning from
human feedback, where you have
an analogy here, which is you
can train a language model,
and it might be completely
misaligned with what
actually humans care about.
How does reinforcement learning
help in those situations?
That's going to be the
next topic in the last part
of the lecture.
OK, let me show you a few
other results quickly.
Today, we talked about
DQN, deep Q-learning.
In practice, there is a
lot more reinforcement
learning algorithm, but
you got the gist of it.
You got the concept of making
good sequences of decision,
epsilon greedy, exploration,
exploitation, terminal state,
starting state.
All of that, you got.
The one algorithm
that is very popular
right now is called PPO,
proximal policy optimization.
There is one that is even
more popular right now.
That's actually from a year ago
at Stanford called DPO that we
won't study in the class.
One of the things to
know about PPO, just
to go over it really
quickly, and I
pasted two important papers from
Schulman et al a few years back,
just TRPO and PPO, is that it
is not a value-based algorithm.
So in Q-learning, you
learn the Q values
and then you define your policy
as the argmax of the Q values.
In PPO, you'll learn
the policy directly,
which is a more
probabilistic method.
It also works well
with continuous spaces.
If you look at
Q-learning we learned,
one output for one action.
If you actually have a game
that has continuous action,
like autonomous
driving, where it's not
like just turn the wheel to
the right or to the left,
it's what degree you
turn it, it's continuous,
then DQN would not
work well, or you
would have to granularized the
number of actions a little bit
to the right, a little
bit more a little more,
which would not
be really useful.
Instead you would use PPO.
Yeah?
We learn that the immediate
reward for a game like Go
is 0 for most steps.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
So a question is, how do you
define the reward in DQN?
Different reward structure
will lead to different types
of agent strategies.
But you're right.
For the game of Go, you could
actually define the reward as 1
if you win and 0
if you don't win.
That's it.
Every move will be 0 until
the last move is a win.
In chess, you might actually
do intermediate reward
because you want to tell
the agent that it's is
good to kill the opponent's
pieces to get rid of them.
You could also do
end-to-end and say
I don't give any
intermediate reward.
I just give a
final reward, which
might be more
complicated to train on,
but it might actually lead
to a more optimal strategy.
Because, in fact,
you could actually
win without taking any
piece from your opponent.
So other things about PPO
is it's more probabilistic.
It has a concept of an expected
advantage, which at every step,
instead of telling you
how good that action is,
it will tell you how much
better it is than random--
than the current state.
How much better would it be to
do certain things versus what
you would have done otherwise?
I'm not going to go
into the details.
It's all in the paper, but those
are things that are important.
Here are a few examples of PPO.
So this example on the left is
from OpenAI a few years back,
where you can see it's a
continuous space, where
the agent is being
bullied a little bit,
but it's trying to
grab the rewards.
But it's also subject
to external forces
that are throwing balls at it.
It's a little bit mean.
You can imagine that this is
a continuous space, meaning
you're controlling
the nodes, you're
controlling the
joints of the agent,
and you're controlling
the forces, the angles.
And so that's why PPO would
be better in that case.
Super.
Here is a competitive
self-play, which I really like,
where you have agent
play with each other.
And this is the Sumo game.
Push the opponent outside the
ring and you get a reward.
So actually, it's
interesting because you're
seeing some emergent
behavior, which
is they attack
each other's feet,
or they lower their center
of gravity to be more stable,
for example.
Yeah?
Is this the exact same
one from [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah.
It's versions.
Sometimes different
initializations, for example.
But it has to be [INAUDIBLE].
So no, but good question.
So oftentimes what OpenAI
would do back in that time
is they would create
copies of the same model.
They would initialize
them differently.
And they would let them learn.
And it turns out
one of the models
we get better than the others.
And then they will copy
again that model to the rest
and do the same thing again
and again, pretty much.
Yeah.
It's kind of funny, isn't it?
That's a good catch.
That's a good goal.
I could watch that for hours.
OK.
Very little awkward, you
have to say, but it works.
OK.
So I'll let you watch the video.
It's going to be shared.
But here is another set of games
that are even more complicated
that I mentioned
early on, OpenAI Five,
which you can think of an
equivalent of League of Legends,
DOTA, where you have 5v5 game.
So you have to collaborate,
et cetera, which makes--
adds literally one additional
degree of complexity.
And StarCraft--
AlphaStar from DeepMind
is an example of where
the observation is not
the entire state.
You have fog.
And so that adds another
layer of complexity.
We're not going to see
that together today.
I would encourage you to look
at the AlphaGo documentary
on Netflix if you haven't.
Who has seen it already?
Nobody.
OK.
Well, you can now watch it with
a different AI understanding
reinforcement learning.
And at some point
in the documentary,
you will see that AlphaGo makes
a very odd move, a very creative
move.
And people are like, I
don't understand that move.
Even the top researchers
or the best players
would say in the video, they
don't understand that move.
It turns out that move is
very unintuitive for humans.
Because as humans, we
are trained to maximize
our chances of winning.
Literally, if I can eat
all your pieces in chess,
I will eat all your pieces.
And if I can surround your
stones in go as much as I can,
I will do it.
The agent is just
programmed to win.
So that move actually
looks counterintuitive,
because the agent doesn't
care about winning by one
or winning by a 20 stones.
It just cares about winning.
And that move specifically
puts the agent in a good place
to win by a small margin.
So that's an example of an
insight that you will learn,
you understand from
this class, and you
will see in the documentary.
OK.
I think we have 10 minutes.
I'm just going to introduce
a reinforcement learning
from human feedback because
it's a more modern topic that
is very trendy right now.
It's important to know.
And so let's look
at it together.
We're going to start by
recapping how language models
are trained in a nutshell.
And then we'll see what
supervised fine-tuning
looks like.
We'll talk about how do we train
a critic model, a reward model.
And then finally,
what RLHF looks like
and why is it so
trending in the news.
So our training objective
for language models
is next token prediction.
We've already talked about
it in a formal lecture.
The idea is that I
will get some inputs.
I'm reading Wikipedia, let's
say, or some of a text online.
And I read a sentence and
I predict the last token.
And I do that again and again.
So for example, deep learning,
and then deep learning
is, deep learning is so,
deep learning is so cool,
and that's it.
So you get the idea.
You always predict
the next token.
And then over time,
it forces the model
to explicit emerging behaviors.
And it understands
the connections
between those concepts.
And it's really good
at generating texts.
We compute a loss function.
You're actually going to study
this loss function in C5.
So I'm not going to
talk about it right now.
But you perform a
gradient descent loop.
And this is how you get your
first pre-trained language
model.
You can pre-trained
language model.
You can call it on
a text or a prompt.
And it will
continually generate.
And you call it again
and again and again.
And it generates,
generates, generates.
Everybody's comfortable
with that, right?
OK.
So that's how we train
a language model,
but there is a
couple of problems.
The first problem is
that online data does not
reflect helpfulness.
So to give you a
concrete example, what
you might find in
the training set
is something like deep
learning is so cool.
When actually what you
might find in practice
is people asking what
is deep learning.
So the data is not
really reflective
of you want an
agent to be helpful.
And that's a problem
because the model
was trained to continue text
rather than answer questions.
And in practice, you would
see it's a big problem.
Another problem is the
model has no concept
of good, polite or helpful yet.
And to give you a
concrete example,
you might actually ask a
pre-trained language model.
My laptop won't turn on.
What should I do?
And then the model responds
because it has read it
on Reddit or on
Wikipedia, is laptops
sometimes don't turn on
because of power issues,
which is not what you ask.
You ask, what should I do.
And in fact, a
better answer would
have been check your charger
if it's properly connected
or the outlet works.
If that's fine, try holding the
power button for 10 seconds.
If it still doesn't start,
the battery or motherboard
may blah, blah, blah, blah.
That's a better answer.
That's what you want a
language model to do nowadays.
And the model can
give you factual text
because that's what
it's been trained on.
But it doesn't understand being
helpful or having an answer that
looks like a human-like answer.
So our solution to it
will start with using
supervised fine-tuning,
which is going
to be learning from human
written demonstrations
of helpful behavior.
And then we'll get to
even further and use
RLHF, which will optimize not
only for human written sentences
or paragraphs, but
for preferences.
And the word preference
is the keyword.
Let's talk about how we can
improve our pre-trained model
with supervised fine-tuning.
I'll take that we
want to align models
with human written responses.
And the step one that
we're going to use
is to build a data set.
Let's build the data sets of
human prompt response pairs.
So what actually
OpenAI is going to do,
I'll explain it
in a second, is it
might collect some
of the prompts
that we all use,
and then ask humans
to respond to those prompts
and put that in a data set.
It might also ask
separately experts
to write really good prompts
and then answer those prompts.
It's a fully human
made data set.
And then we'll use that
data set to fine-tune
our pre-trained model.
And by now, you've learned
fine-tuning in the online video.
So you know what I'm talking
about using supervised learning.
So what it looks like is I
take my pre-trained model
that I just told
you how we train.
And then I give it a prompt,
explain deep learning
to a beginner.
And I also will
concatenate to it
a response, a good response
written by a human.
Deep learning is a type
of machine learning
that uses neural.
And then I expect the model to
come up with the word networks.
So it's literally
do whatever we need
to train the pre-trained model,
but we do it on human written
prompt response pairs.
And if you do that
many times, then you
use the same loss function,
how far the model's response
is from a human response.
You do that many
times, and you will get
SFT, supervised fine-tuning.
But it has some shortcomings.
One of the shortcomings
it is data that
is extremely costly to collect.
In fact, I believe in the first
version of that InstructGPT.
There was only 13,000
prompt response pairs.
And it turns out it did
really well, despite that.
The second aspect is it's
unlikely to generalize well
because you're-- again, you're
not doing reinforcement learning
here.
You're doing
supervised learning.
And so you're just
showing a set of examples,
13,000 examples that
you want to learn,
but it's what tells you that
it will generalize to an unseen
prompt that will come
up from your user base.
And so this
approach, SFT, really
teaches the model to imitate
good behavior from humans.
And that's the key.
It's imitation.
It is not preference
optimization.
To do preference
optimization, that's
where we're going to
train a reward model.
And we're going
to do proper RLHF.
So let me talk to you
about the RM, reward model.
And then I'll tell you
about RLHF in a nutshell.
The problem of RLHF is to
align not with human responses,
but with human preferences.
So what's going
to happen is we're
going to train a
separate model to predict
which responses humans prefer.
And we're going to call
that model the reward model.
It's a separate model from
whatever we've trained before.
The model is going to
use data from labelers.
So you're going to show
labelers two or more responses
to the same prompts.
And those responses will
be sampled from the SFT.
So your best model
right now is the SFT.
You will sample three
or four responses.
And you know how
we sample, right?
You can tweak the temperature.
You can select not only the
top priority word, the top--
the softmax layers,
number one word, but you
can sometimes sample
differently and you
will get a variety of answers.
And then you will
ask a human labeler
to say answer B is better
than answer C, and answer
C is better than answer A, and
answer A is equal to answer D,
let's say.
They will be asked which
response they prefer
and it can get more complicated.
It doesn't have to be
just a simple ranking.
You have multiple Likert
scale methods and so on.
But the point is
that you will collect
those pairwise comparisons that
we'll call preference data,
and you will use it to
train a reward model, which
is initialized from your SFT.
So your SFT is here, it's
your best model to date.
And you're going to
modify the last layer.
So the softmax layer at the
end of a language model, that
will tell you this is the
token we should output,
or this is the word
we should write.
Instead of that, you'll
get rid of that layer.
You'll put a scalar
value as output.
You'll put a linear layer
with a scalar value that
will represent the reward head.
It will predict
the reward, which
is a proxy for the
preference of the human.
The way you train that
reward model is you
give it a batch of two.
You give it a prompt
x with a response
A and the preference
of the user.
And you give it the same
prompt with a response
B from the SFT with the
preference of the user.
So here the user is
saying, response A
is better than response
B. And so if you actually
were sending that in this model,
you will get a predicted reward
for the preferred answer and a
predicted reward for the least
preferred answer.
That allows you to train
using a loss function
that I'm not going to cover
given our time sensitivity.
The loss function will
encourage the model
to assign higher rewards
to preferred responses.
So you're trying to
dissociate the higher
reward, better
preference from the lower
reward for lower preference.
And it turns out that if
you do that many times,
you will have a
reward model that,
given a prompt and a response,
will be approximating
human preference.
So you've just
trained a critique
that represents your humans.
It's a proxy for
what humans prefer.
It's been trained on a
lot of human preferences.
The reason it's better to use
a model than actual humans
is because we can use it
widely on all sorts of inputs,
and it can scale from
a data standpoint.
Also note that this
method is better than SFT
because it's way easier
to ask humans what's
your preference between
those two things,
and to ask them to come up
with answers to prompts.
It takes way less time.
And if you've used
ChatGPT, you've
probably been asked
before to tell them
which response you prefer.
Yeah.
So once trained,
the reward model
replaces the human
as the evaluator
during reinforcement
learning from human feedback.
And reinforcement learning
from human feedback
is very comfortable for you now.
I will show you what
it looks like given
the Q-learning
algorithm we learned.
But essentially,
we have first start
the model, what good
behavior looks like with SFT.
And then we built
a reward model that
can tell us how
good an answer is
according to human preferences.
And the RLHF approach is where
we will let this model practice,
get scored by the reward
model or the critic,
and update itself to produce
higher scoring answers.
So more preferred answers.
And it's the same as the
games we've seen together,
but some things differ.
So I just pasted
here the exact setup
that we've learned together
for reinforcement learning.
The differences
are the following.
Our objective is still to
maximize the expected reward
that is produced by the
reward model aligned
with human preferences.
The agent is the language
model being fine-tuned.
The environment is the
space of possible prompts
and continuations.
It's any text that
you can encounter.
The state is the specific
prompt plus the tokens
that were generated so far.
The next state is
one more token added.
And the action is
the next token that
is chosen by the agent
or the model, which is,
of course, determined
by the policy.
And then the reward is
estimated by the reward model
that we trained to
represent human preferences.
In this case, one episode
is one full prompt.
So imagine that you get a
prompt and you start generating.
And you go through this
reinforcement learning loop.
And you observe the rewards.
And then you try to
maximize the future rewards.
And then at the end of
training, you end up
with having your pre-trained
model turn into an SFT
and your SFT turn into a
way better model using RLHF.
OK.
So a few things to
note to end on this.
The model does not get a
reward at every single token.
It gets a reward at
the end of a sequence
when the completion is finished.
Because reward model
was asked to rate
prompts and responses together.
So you need to finish
the generation in order
to see what's the reward.
And so again, going
back to making
good sequences of decisions,
that's exactly it.
You want the model to
make enough good sequences
of decisions so that the
response is preferred
by the critic, which
represents a proxy
to the human preferences.
So all intermediary
rewards are typically 0.
And that makes it a very
sparse reward episodic tasks,
just like a game of
chess where you only
get a reward when you
finish, assuming you're not
defining intermediary reward.
So you only know if you
did well at the end.
And you have to then
use that information
to update your network and
get a better proxy for it.
Super.
There's a very nice video.
We're not going to play
it for the sake of time,
but I will send it online.
It's from four days ago.
A former Stanford
student, [INAUDIBLE],
who is very thoughtful
and articulate
and was explaining four days
ago, why reinforcement learning
can be terrible at times, and
that human minds work way more
efficiently.
And so I would encourage you
to watch this four-minute video
because he's very clearly
outlining why reinforcement
learning is still not
great, even if it's the best
thing we can use in many ways.