Welcome to lecture 9 already.
I hope everybody had
a good fall break.
Today, we're going to talk
about neural networks,
both convolutional neural
networks and transformers.
And we're going to unpack it
to see what's going on inside.
This lecture used to be called
neural network interpretability,
but I've broadened the scope
because there is a section now
where we talk more
about frontier models.
And the interpretability
or visualization methods
have not quite been
figured out for most models
that you play with out there.
So think about this
one as research areas,
what we know from
convolutions, and what
we're trying to figure
out for frontier models.
We're going to start with a
very packed agenda with a case
study where I'm going
to ask you a question
and let you brainstorm a
little bit all together
on how you would try to
understand what's happening
inside of a frontier model.
In the second
section, we're going
to look at the example
of convolutions
specifically and try
to interpret everything
possible about convolution.
Meaning, we're going to look
at input/output relationship.
We're going to look
at a specific neuron
inside and try to interpret it.
We're going to look also
at a specific feature maps
and try to understand
what they do.
I will present many
methods to do that.
Those methods are
real, and they've
been used for convolutions.
But again, they're
not the methods
that you might see frontier
labs use for today's language
or vision, large models.
However, they're
going to bring you
the skills that will
allow you to understand
the methods for frontier
models as researchers
are trying to figure them out.
The second half
of the lecture is
going to focus more on the
modern representation analysis.
We're going to talk about
scaling laws, capability
benchmarking, data
diagnostics, and then I'll
end on a few closing remarks.
Are we ready for this one?
Lots of visualizations
in this lecture.
So first question for you all.
Let's say the case study
is, you are a model trainer,
and you're working on a 200
billion parameters model
at a frontier lab.
And overnight, a new checkpoint
passes training sanity check,
but a few issues arise.
Things like the model is getting
worse on reasoning benchmarks,
some safety evals are
failing, and there's
a weird spike in, let's
say, latency for tool use
when you actually use this
model for an agentic workflow.
Your VP is wondering what's
happening, and they ask,
what is going on?
And what are you going
to look at first?
So what I want you to
discuss for a minute
or so think about it
first, and I'll open up,
is what are the type of
evidences that you would look,
want to inspect before
even touching the code
or retraining the model?
What are the things that
you want to look at?
Jumping.
There's no single answer.
So I want to everything
you're going to look at OK.
So error analysis.
You said, I will look at
the reasoning benchmarks
and find the examples
where the model is failing.
Specifically, try
to find patterns
in order to pinpoint
what the issue might be.
And then same
thing on the safety
evals where you want to see
what type of safety issues
are arising.
Is it everywhere?
Is it specific to something?
Yeah, I agree.
Error analysis in general.
What else?
Remember you're
the model trainer.
So you're training this model.
You're supposed to be
watching certain things when
you're training.
What can be interesting?
Yeah.
With sanity checks, you
mean the loss in frequency.
And all of this, right,
it starts passing.
Yeah.
Let's say not
necessarily passing,
but those are great examples.
So you're mentioning, yeah,
as you're the model trainer,
you would be watching
the training loss.
And you want to see.
What are you going to look
for in that training loss?
Convergence.
OK.
You probably want to make
sure that it's smooth.
You don't want big spikes.
How about the validation loss?
What is your expectation
on the validation loss?
Should go up.
Yeah, should probably follow the
same curve as the training loss,
but is likely slightly higher
because you're probably
performing slightly less
well on the validation set
than on the training set.
If you're seeing
spikes, it might
mean there are some issues.
What else are you looking at?
Yeah.
Take a look at this
round of training data
see how it's performing.
So this batch, you mean?
Yeah, so you're looking at
this round of training data,
maybe the last round of
data that we trained on,
there were some
issues in that data.
Maybe that data was
probably poisoned or biased
toward a certain category of
data that we're failing on.
You're totally right.
Yeah.
Maybe that specific checkpoint
is doing poorly compared
to the previous checkpoint.
And so you pinpoint
where the issue arises
during the training.
What else are you looking at?
Yeah.
I'm worried about
the overnight thing.
It's pretty fast.
I wonder if this is in line
with a hardware issue there.
OK.
Because it's overnight
and it seemed
everything was good
up to yesterday
and now there's an
issue, maybe you're
saying there's a hardware issue.
Yeah, we could
check actually is--
yeah, latency has
been pointed out.
So maybe the
hardware has failed.
Yeah, you're right.
What else?
So a lot of the answers
are global answers.
You're looking at
the model in general.
You're not looking at specific
portions of the model.
What would if you were to
inspect the model more precisely
from the inside?
And this one's a language model.
So you can think about the fact
that it's a language model.
Yeah.
I mean, it's something I
would do is just recently
examine differential equations,
look at what has happened
over the past 10
points before this one
to see the model getting
to perform better or was
it not, just to see if
there was hardware issue
or there would be a problem.
Yeah, you're right.
You want to look at
different checkpoints
and see where did
we fail and might
be able to trace
back to that moment
and figure out
what the issue was?
So, for example, maybe your
initialization was actually
pretty good and the first
checkpoints were doing well,
but suddenly at some
points, the model
saturated in a certain way.
Maybe you're seeing exploding
gradients or vanishing
gradients in certain moments,
and you want to pinpoint that.
Yeah.
What else?
We're adding so many
methods right now,
but I want to hear what else
you have for language models.
What other things
can you visualize
for language models that might
mean something's going wrong?
Yeah.
And if you really want
to go deep into it,
you can actually plot
the attention maps
The attention maps.
Yeah, yeah.
Fair enough.
You've learned
about transformers
in the online videos,
the attention maps, which
are representative
of the relationship
between different tokens.
They might not
make sense to you.
You might actually be plotting
certain attention maps
and be like, this token has
nothing to do with that one,
but the model seems
to think it has.
And you might be able to
identify certain issues
with the attention maps.
What else beyond
the attention maps?
What?
Yeah.
I don't know myself, but
running a sensitivity analysis
might be helpful to
see where with what
parameters are [INAUDIBLE]
So you mean-- tell me more
about the sensitivity analysis.
What would you fix, for example,
and what would you change?
Probably the parameters.
Honestly, right now I don't
what parameters to touch
and how to that, but it seems
logical to access the analysis
so you realize
what is happening.
How the parameters
actually [INAUDIBLE]
OK.
Yeah.
But I like the idea of
sensitivity analysis.
You might try to
figure out which
hyper parameter went wrong.
Is there something wrong
with our optimizer?
Is our learning rate
schedule poorly tuned?
Maybe scaling laws.
That we can play with compute.
We can play with data.
We can play with model size.
And one of those
might be going wrong.
Maybe an analysis would allow us
to identify the model is fine.
It just needs to
be trained longer
or the model is actually
too small for the amount
of data we're giving it.
That type of stuff would come
with either doing a sensitivity
analysis or comparing what
we're doing to the scaling laws
that we from other models.
We're going to look into that.
OK.
Any other ideas?
I have a question.
So these 200 billion parameters,
where does the number come from?
Probably these parameters,
we don't need them.
Might be.
So you're saying I gave you
200 billion parameters, which
is a very large model
even as of today.
It might be overparameterized.
That's a good
question because it
depends on what it's been
trained on, how much data
we're feeding it,
how much compute.
It's all relative to each other.
But yeah, it's a large model.
So I would expect
a lot of compute
and a lot of data along with it.
In fact, a lot of
these models might be
built as a mixture of experts.
You've heard about
mixture of experts.
One thing that could happen
is that some of the experts
are failing, and you might
be inspecting if experts
are in fact failing or the
routing module is always
selecting the same
expert because it's just
found an expert that is
really good and generalized
and the other experts
are not being used.
That might be
another issue as well
that might be related
to the model capacity.
Because if the model is
not using all its experts,
it's probably not actually
operating as a 200 billion
parameter model.
It's operating as
a smaller model.
So generally, this is
to motivate the lecture.
We're going to look into
all of these together today.
And we'll start
with convolutions
because they're very visual.
For the convolutional part,
we're going to go super deep.
But then for the
frontier models,
I'm just going to get
broader and give you
the areas of research.
So the answer to the
question I asked typically
would fall under four
buckets, every solution
that we looked into together.
One is training and scaling.
So people are looking at loss
curves at things gradients,
learning rates, mixture of
experts, routing, scaling laws.
We're going to talk
about all these.
The second category
is representation
and internal aspect
of the model.
You mentioned. attention
heads and maps, embeddings,
nobody mentioned embeddings
but you could actually
visualize embeddings
and see, does it
make sense to you or these
tokens close to each other
as you would expect?
Meaning the model's mental
understanding of language
is correct.
And then neuron level behaviors.
Although that's really
hard with a large model.
And nobody has quite
figured it out yet.
And then the other category
might be data and distribution.
Maybe the actual benchmark
that we're looking at
has been contaminated.
Meaning the model either it's
doing too well on that benchmark
or it doesn't mean
anything, or it's
doing poorly for
a certain reason
because the data distribution
used in the test set
is completely different from
the training or validation set.
And then it might be
failing at different levels.
You can run benchmarks
on the language model.
You can run benchmarks on
the agentic workflow that
is using that language model.
And because you want
the language model
to be used in agentic
workflow, those
are two levels that
you need to inspect.
So, for example,
when a frontier lab
says our model is doing
really well for tool use,
what they mean is
the language model
has been tested on upstream
tasks in a workflow,
and it's actually good at tool
use against their benchmarks.
So those are different levels
of capability analysis.
So let's talk
about convolutions.
We're going to dive deep
inside convolutions.
And then we'll go back up
and look at frontier models.
So first case study
for convolutions.
Let's say that you have built
an animal classifier for a zoo.
And they are very
reluctant to use your model
without any human
supervising because they
don't understand the decision
making process of the model.
How can you alleviate
their concerns?
How can you give them intuition
about the decision making
process of the
model so that they
feel like the
models doing things
that feel natural and human?
Just to simplify,
let's say you have
a convolutional neural network,
and there's a softmax layer,
and it's supposed
to identify animals.
So the number of
classes or many animals.
Yeah.
If you were to
write a quick Python
code to give them some
intuition, how would you do it?
Yeah.
Thanks very much.
First, with the
softmax is how we're
going to eventually
get at the end result,
probabilities what
the animal is.
And then the next thing I will
explain is how with the CNN,
each layer of our CNN is
getting more in depth,
I guess, features of the image
of the animals are showing.
And then maybe if I have time, I
can try and use different images
and try to figure out what
each layer [INAUDIBLE]
OK.
Good.
So just to recap, the
zoo is not I native.
So you have to explain
certain things.
You're going to tell
them what softmax is.
So we're going to have a
probability for each animal
classes.
That's how it works.
And on top of that,
you also mentioned
you might talk
about convolutions
and say here are how
features are identified,
here is how a filter
scans through the image.
And we're expecting
this to learn.
So you're going to
educate them first.
That's totally right.
The second thing you
mentioned is maybe
you run a data set search.
So you can try to
build their intuition
by showing them animal
pictures and showing
that the model is doing well.
And yeah, I agree those
are good approaches.
We're going to see how
to do a proper data set
search large scale.
But what else can you do that's
going to give a little bit
more confidence?
Because this is explanation,
but it's not proof
that the model is looking at
the right place systematically.
Yeah.
You display some of the hurdles
and demonstrate [INAUDIBLE],
and show all the small
features that [INAUDIBLE].
So you say, ideally,
you would give them
intuition at a filter level.
This filter we know it's
responsible for finding
the legs of an animal.
That's what you're saying.
So how would you do that?
Well, maybe I don't know
enough but it's not supposed
to bring out the [INAUDIBLE]
Good intuition.
You're asking, is it as
simple as just printing out
the weights that are
identified or the feature map
that results of that filter?
Unfortunately, not
usually, because that
might be true for
the first layer.
But as you get
deeper, things mix up
so much that if you were
just to print the filter,
it wouldn't make any sense.
Pretty much.
But there are other methods
that we're going to see.
So your intuition is right.
We're going to try
to give them that.
Something simpler,
input/output relationship.
How would you show that
the output is actually
related to the right portions
of the inputs for this dog,
for example?
Yeah.
Recall a confusion matrix.
[INAUDIBLE]
Confusion matrix
across a lot of data.
You would find true
positives, false, et cetera.
Yeah.
Correct.
Something else.
You have a critical
layer of your network
and then you show how it
completes over different layers
to show how from the
first layer is taken.
That doesn't give us [INAUDIBLE]
So similar to what
he said, you want
to give them intuition from the
inner workings of the network.
And you're saying,
how about we mask
the latter parts of
the network and we
treat every intermediary
layer as an output,
and analyzing the
output makes sense.
Yeah, we're going to
look at that actually.
Yeah those are more advanced.
What I was looking for
is even much more basic.
If you want to show the
relationship between an input
and an output of a CNN
or any vision model,
you might take the score of
the dog in the output layer.
And what is exactly
this quantity?
What is your intuition for
what this quantity means?
If you take the derivative of
the score of an animal class
with respect to x, with
x being the input image--
yeah.
How does the score
of dog vary when
you change things around some?
How does the score of dog change
when you move pixels around?
Which is what you want.
You want to be able to-- if you
can do that, you would indicate
that which are the pixels of the
image that if we change them,
it changes the score of dog.
If you can print
that, then you would
be able to show this is
where the model is looking
at when it's predicting a dog.
So yeah, if you actually
calculate this derivative,
you would get something like
that where some of the pixels
are going to be brighter,
meaning their gradient is higher
and some of the pixels
are going to be darker,
meaning we move that
pixel and it didn't
modify the score of dog at all.
That's a very quick way to look
at which pixels in the input
were relevant for
the score of dog.
Now why should we select
the score of dog pre-softmax
versus post-softmax?
It's usually a very
common misconception.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
So what's the issue
with the scaled version?
It's more representative
of the actual score.
Class of dog.
So what you said is
the post-softmax score
is not only dependent
on dog; it's also
dependent on all
the other scores.
So you could actually
take a pixel, move it,
and it happens to modify
the score of a panda
because there's a panda in
the background or something.
And it would influence
what you're trying to show.
But you're only looking at dog.
You just want the score
of dog to be influenced.
So that's why in this
method called saliency maps,
we use the pre-softmax
scores that
is only representative
of the class at hand
that you're analyzing.
OK.
So you could do that.
And actually if you were to,
in the past, not anymore,
but you could use that for a
quick segmentation sanity check
because the pixels
that are brighter,
the gradients that
are brighter are
representatives
of the pixels that
should be overlaid on the dog.
And in fact, if you
do the saliency maps
and you realize that the pixels
that are bright when you compute
that gradient are
all over the place,
it's probably that
the model is not even
looking at the right place.
It's just getting lucky.
OK.
So this first method,
saliency maps,
now have that in your toolkit.
Very easy to implement.
You just write a Python script.
You perform the
gradient calculation.
You print it.
It's a matrix of pixels
that are brighter or darker,
and you're done.
One of the main issues
with saliency maps
is that it's looking at
just a pixel level, which
doesn't make too
much sense if you
want to interpret semantically
where the model is looking at.
The model will never
see a cat or a dog
with one pixel being
different than the rest.
It would be too discontinuous.
So instead, there's
another method,
I'm not going to
go into the detail,
but I linked the paper,
which is way more common,
called integrated gradients.
And integrated
gradients, the idea
is that instead of doing that
directly by taking the ds of dog
over dx, we're going to
take an image of the animal,
and we're going to
generate many pictures that
are taking a dark, completely
black zero's pixel all the way
to the animal, the final image.
And then we're going to look
at the path of gradients
across all of these updates.
And it's going to be
way more interpretive.
I'm not going to go
into the details.
But integrated gradients is just
an extension of saliency maps
that happens to use a different
formula with an integration
and is way more common.
If you look at it
practically, this
is an example from
the medical field.
Here is an image of a retina.
And if you perform the
integrated gradients,
you would see that the
original image, the annotation
for the lesions are exactly
where the model is looking
at when it's giving
you a probability
that there is a lesion.
So the second method called
integrated gradients.
Let's push it a little further.
The next case study is that
you want to now tell them
a little more about the decision
process of the model with--
I guess let me rephrase.
The saliency maps looked
at the pixel level.
What you can do in order to
give a better intuition, which
was mentioned earlier,
is another approach
called occlusion sensitivity,
which is actually
way more intuitive and simple,
where you could actually
take the dog image and
paste it into the CNN,
and you would get
a score of a dog.
You could also overlay a dark
square, so zero out or mask
partially the input image
and give it to the same CNN
and track the modifications
on the score of dog
that you're tracking.
If you actually do that, you
can plot a probability map
of how is the score
of dog changing
as I move the dark
square through the image?
So let's do it together.
I'm going to say that this
one, when you actually
put the dark square on the top
left of the image, the score
of dog is unchanged.
It's still very high.
Now you move the square a
little bit to the right,
and you see that it's still
very high, the score of dog.
You do it again,
still very high.
Now, the square is partially
occluding the face of the dog,
and you should see
the score of dog drop
if the model is, in
fact, looking at the dog.
And you perform that many times.
So you scan through the
image with your dark square,
and you plot what we
call the probability
map of the true class
for different positions
of the gray square.
Does that make sense?
So pretty simple,
computationally expensive
though.
Just have to rerun the image so
many times through the model.
Here are practical
examples to look at.
The first one, the true label
is a Pomeranian cute dog.
And you see that
the model is failing
to recognize the true class
when the square is overlapping
with the center of the
face, which makes sense
because here the true class
that we're tracking is not dog.
It's Pomeranian.
And I could see how if
you occlude the face,
it's hard to get the
breed of the dog.
The second example, the true
label is a car wheel-- sorry,
I hadn't shown you that.
The true label is a car wheel.
And you can see that when
the square is on the wheel,
it is in fact dropping in terms
of the true class probability.
And then finally
the Afghan hound.
What's interesting about that
third example is the probability
is dropping when the
square is on the dog,
but it's also increasing
when the square is
on the face of the
human on the left, which
means that if you actually
occlude the face of the human,
the model thinks even more
that the true class is
in fact an Afghan hound.
You're just removing additional
unnecessary information for it
to discover the true class.
So this model seems
to be doing well.
It seems to be looking
in the right place.
We call that
occlusion sensitivity.
Pretty simple, another
tool with saliency map
and integrated gradients
in your toolkit.
Let's push it slightly further.
Here we're given, along with
the classification output,
the zoo wants a real time
visualization of the model's
decision process.
And you have one
day to show that.
And we're talking about
convolutions again.
What do you do?
So the important part is to
know the methods that we've
seen so far are post methods
where you analyze the output
or you show something.
Here we're looking
at ideally a module
that we could plug in our
network that would constantly
give us the decision making
process of the network,
or at least where
it's looking at.
How would you do this?
This is our network, by the way.
We're taking an input.
We're adding zero padding,
and we have a series
of conv ReLU max pool blocks.
And then at the end, we flatten.
We have a triple fully
connected layer, a softmax,
and we get our probability
output for classification.
So first question,
where do you think
is the weakness of
this network when
it comes to interpreting
where the model is looking
at on a picture?
A part of this
architecture is very mixed,
interpreting the
network way harder.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
Why?
Because of you look at all
the pixels at once, I guess,
over the last month, there
have been three of them.
So it's three layers of
abstraction from the last layer
all the way to what you get.
Yeah, totally right.
They're fully connected layers.
You're looking at all the
pixels at the same time.
You're mixing everything, and
you're doing it three times.
So by the end of
those three layers,
the information has been
mixed together, essentially.
You do not find the
localized information
that you had pre that with the
maxpool and the conv layers.
So how could you change that
layer in order to avoid that?
How would you
modify your network
if you wanted to retain maybe
the performance of the model
but not lose that
localized information?
I guess, could you do one layer.
I think it's huge.
I don't it know.
But it might be--
I don't actually know how
many times larger than.
Yeah, good idea.
Instead of doing
three, can we do one?
Can we still have a layer that
makes the interpretation easy.
Actually, there's another
trick which we're going to see,
but it's similar to
what you described.
Let's say we
convert this network
into something where the
flattening of the pixels
and the fully connected
layers are converted
into a single global
average pooling layer
and a fully connected layer.
So here we reduce from 3 to
1, the fully connected layers.
We still need our fully
connected layers and our softmax
because it's a
classification task,
and we want a good
decision engine at the end.
But we converted.
We added a global
average pooling.
So let me explain
why this is better.
So the last conv
block essentially
is giving us a volume.
For the sake of simplicity,
let's say that volume
is a 4 by 4 with six channels.
And I color-coded
them for simplicity.
So each of these
channels is a feature map
that is resulting from
a filter being scanned
through the previous input.
Everybody's clear on that?
So global average
pooling is going
to take each of these
channels, feature maps,
and is going to average
them in a single number.
So if you take the orange
matrix and you average it,
it gives you 104.7.
You do the same thing with the
green one, the blue one, all six
of them, and you
get a volume or call
it a vector of size 6, 1, 1, 6.
So why is that interesting?
Because we actually did not
lose the localized information.
We did not mix things up.
We just assigned a single
number to a feature map
that we retained, so the
localized information is still
there on the previous volume.
And now we can treat
that as a vector that
goes through a decision engine
or a fully connected layer that
ultimately goes
through our softmax
and gives us the probabilities.
So this architecture
is easier to trace back
to localized information
in the input space
because you can actually
look at, let's say,
one of the score of dog.
And you can look at the weights
of each of these edges that
tell you how much has the
feature map from the volume
before contributed
to that score.
So in other words, if
I had to summarize,
let's say the feature
map looks like this.
So this feature map is
very high, has somehow
activated heavily in some
portion of the input image.
The others similarly have
activated two other things.
You're taking the weights from
your fully connected layer.
By the way, you have
to retrain that layer.
You have to just train that
layer, that last one, and then
you sum all of them,
and it gives you
what we call a class
activation map for the class
that you're visualizing.
So you're overlaying those
last six feature maps,
and you're weighing them with
the weights of the last fully
connected layer.
You're not losing information.
You're not mixing three
fully connected layers
that are impossible to trace
back to the input space.
OK.
So if you now give
it an input image,
and you overlay the
class activation
map for the score of dog, which
you can do for other classes,
you can do the same thing
for the class of cat,
look at the different
weights, the feature maps,
and maybe for the class
of cat, the weights
will certainly be different.
So the contribution of each
feature map will be different.
Yeah.
And this is what you get.
This is called class
activation map.
And it's from folks
over at Berkeley.
And so here's a video
that describes it.
It runs really quickly.
You can think of it as a slight
modification to a vision network
that can allow you to unpack
what's happening inside
and what's the decision process.
There's also an improvement to
the CAM or Class Activation Map
algorithm called Grad-CAM,
which enhances that method.
Any questions on
class activation maps?
So we're getting to know
convolutions a little better.
Yeah.
I have a question.
In the video, it seems
like it has hypermobility
on unrelated things
all the time,
like [INAUDIBLE] of the models.
Yeah.
So you were saying
in the video, it
seems like the model
sometimes is looking
at the meaningless things.
Yeah.
I mean, it's not
surprising, frankly.
This is the previous
generation of models.
And on top of that,
you're looking on a video.
The model is a
classification network.
So it might look
sometimes at things
that are not even labeled.
And so it has to
find the closest one.
It might not make sense at all.
That's why you build
that type of model
to visualize and
understand the network
is actually not
working that well.
But maybe on the main objects
that you actually want
for your task, let's say the zoo
wants to do very well with cats
and dogs, you can verify that
when a cat is moving, even
at fast speed, the model
is quickly looking at it.
Super.
Let's do a couple more
methods because it's
going to build our intuition
for frontier models.
So now the zoo trusts you.
It trusts that the model
correctly locates animals,
but they get of scared and they
wonder if the model understands
what a dog is.
Does it understand
actually what a dog is,
or is it just like pattern
matching random things?
How could you take this
ConvNet and query what
the model thinks the dog is?
How would you do that?
How could you ask the
model, what's your best
representation of a dog?
You are trying to
reverse-engineer or get
an image that maximizes
the probability of dog.
OK.
Yeah.
You did say two things.
So get an image, so a
forged image that maximizes
the probability of dog.
Yeah, let's do that actually.
And then on your second point
about reverse engineering,
we're going to look at
the method there as well.
But, yeah, I agree you could.
So how would you
concretely do that?
What would you maximize?
The softmax
OK.
Actually, what we
said earlier, but I
think you came right after that
is we would not take the softmax
output because the
softmax output is
dependent on other classes.
You divide by the sum of the
exponentials of other classes.
And so you could actually
maximize the softmax output
by not maximizing
the class you want
but by minimizing the
other classes, which is
different than what you want.
So here's what we'll do.
We'll define a
loss function where
we take the pre-softmax
score of dog,
so the thing right
before the softmax, which
is only dependent on
that specific class.
And we might also regularize it
to make sure it looks natural.
The reason we want the
regularization term
is because pixels need to be
between 0 and 255, roughly.
And so you don't want
to run an optimization
problem where pixels
can have values
that go all over the place.
It's just not going to
look good to the human eye.
And so we're going to do that.
We're going to run a
gradient ascent algorithm.
So similar to what we've seen
in some of the previous classes
where we're going to update
the pixels of an input
image, a completely
random input image
until we can maximize the
loss function we defined.
So we forward propagated
the random image,
we compute the objective, we
back propagate all the way
back to the pixels, and
then we update the pixels
to maximize that objective.
And we do that many times
until we end up with something
that might look like this.
So let's say we take the
score of a Dalmatian.
Here researchers, and this
is work from Jason Yosinski,
shows that you can
start seeing the model.
If you ask the model
what is a Dalmatian,
it will tell you it's
something with black dots
on a white background, roughly.
So actually it might
not understand fully
what the dog is, but that's
what it thinks it is.
So we just unpacked it a
little bit and query that.
Another interesting one is
if you look at the goose,
so here, the top left
label goose for the model
is many of them.
What does that mean?
It means probably the model
has seen a bunch of geese
all the time together and
has rarely seen a single one.
And maybe the labeled data
was labeling that as goose
when it was geese.
And so the model actually
doesn't understand
that it's a single one.
It thinks that all of
them are the label.
Does that make sense?
OK.
Super.
So that's called class
model visualization.
You can actually-- oh,
sorry, I wasn't showing
what I was talking about.
No, I was showing.
The way to improve
those visualization
is just to change some of
the regularization methods.
So the researchers have
shown that you can actually
add more color by regularizing
better so it looks better
to the human eye.
And then it becomes
easier to query
the model for a
variety of classes just
to make sure that it
understood those classes.
And so same with flamingos,
actually, the label flamingo
to the model feels
like many flamingos,
just something you can observe.
Any questions on class
model visualization?
Nothing's super new, just
another tool in your kit.
It turns out you can apply
the same type of method
as class model visualization.
But instead of doing
it at the class level,
you do it in an
intermediary activation.
So you could actually
do the same exercise,
sort of what you
were saying earlier
with the masking
of the later layer
and just looking
inside the network.
You could pick an
activation in the network,
create an objective function
with a regularization
and say, hey, show
me the input picture
that maximizes this activation.
And that should tell you what
is the input that maximizes
activation the most.
So that's class
model visualization
which can also be applied
with gradient ascent
anywhere inside the
network at any neuron.
And that already gives
you some of a method
to look at the neuron
level and say, hey,
what's the input that
maximizes the fake input
that theoretically
you could generate
that maximizes that activation.
The next method is actually
the most commonly used today
because it's so
simple and intuitive.
It's a data set search.
So what you could actually
do is to pick a filter.
You just pick one filter, you
pick its feature map among--
I guess, you pick
one feature map
at some point in the network,
such as at after this max
pooling layer.
And so let's say you have 256
filters in that convolution
layer.
So you have 256 feature
maps of size 5 by 5.
And you find across
all your data,
your validation set
the top five image
that maximize this feature map.
So you just track the
activations in that feature map.
You find the highest activation
across all your data,
and you find the
top five images.
And you can do that.
Again, you would say, this seems
that the filter that produced
that feature map has
learned to detect shirts,
because if you find the top
five images that activated
that feature map the most,
that filter the most,
it's all images of shirts.
If you were to find something
like this, you would say.
It seems that the filter
has learned to detect edges.
And you could do that
across every feature map
to interpret your filters.
Simple data set
search that can allow
you to interpret if a filter
is reacting to something
meaningful.
So if you look at
these pictures that I
printed at the bottom of the
slide, they're all cropped.
So why are they cropped?
They don't look like images from
the data set that the image is
probably bigger than that.
The body.
The what?
Like [INAUDIBLE] on
the bottom, [INAUDIBLE]
So we took the input image.
We send it through
the conv ReLU blocks.
And then we pick a feature
map in the fifth block,
let's say, what is this
feature map looking at?
Is it looking at the
whole image or no?
Sorry.
So we pick a feature map.
And in that feature map,
we find the activation
that's the highest.
So let's say the activation
is the row number
5, column number 3, if
you pick that activation
does it have access to the
entire input image or not?
Not necessarily.
But it is more focused
on what is actually--
it's closer to what it's
actually predicting.
So you're closer to actually
getting to the right answer.
So that's why you're basically
seeing where the shape
itself is.
Not necessarily.
Yeah.
So you don't necessarily have
access to the entire image.
The best way to visualize
it is that the first layer.
Let's say on the first layer,
you take the input image,
you take a filter, and
you run it through.
Well, that activation in the
feature map of the first layer
is only going to see
what the filter sees.
When you go deeper
in the network,
do you see more or less
on average of the image?
A single activation,
does it have access
to more or less
parts of the image?
You're saying more?
Yeah, it's more.
Let's look at it.
So here's a picture 64
by 64 by 3, let's say.
We have a conv
network, five layers.
And after five layers, the
last conv has 13 filters
and leads to a 13 by 13-- sorry.
It has 256 filters.
That leads to a 13
by 13 feature maps.
If I look at this
feature map, let's
say that's the most activated,
I trace back to the input space.
It will have access to this
part of the image, let's say.
Now if there was
another conv ReLU block,
and I was looking
at a feature map,
it would have even more
abstraction of multiple portions
of these squares.
So it would actually
see slightly more
from the input image.
Does that make sense?
So that's how you
would think about it.
And it makes sense
because at the end of it,
the last output has
access to the entire image
because all these things are
adding up to the prediction.
So the deeper the activation,
the more it sees from the image.
And that's why the
images were cropped.
They were just cropped
based on tracing back
what that activation was looking
at in the input image, which
you can do very simply
computationally.
So now we're going to
look at our last method
for convs, which has to do
with reverse engineering conv.
And then we'll move to
the frontier models.
So remember this slide from
when we introduced Generative
Adversarial networks, GANs.
I didn't talk too much about
the generator architecture.
I just said it was
a neural network.
But I did mention
that something's
weird about that network, which
is that the input is way smaller
than its output.
The input is a vector z.
The output is an image
of more dimensions.
It is very common that such
a network needs to upsample
and thus would
use deconvolution.
Sometimes in the
literature, you're
going to see dimensions
of deconvolutions
as an upsampling network
where the input is
smaller than the output.
Sometimes those are called
transposed convolutions,
but we're going
to talk about why.
Another example where you
might run into upsampling
is when you have an
encoder/decoder type networks
such as for segmentation.
So let's say you're given an
image of a cellular set of cells
like this, and then you
want to label segments
the pixels that
belong to a cell just
to find the different cells.
Typically, you would use a set
of convolutions that reduces
the volume in height and width.
And then you'll get information
encoded in a dense format
that you will then upsample
because your output should
be of the size of the input
minus the number of channels.
But at least every pixel
should have its own class.
And so typically that would
be a set of convolutions
followed by deconvolutions.
So you downsample, you upsample.
Why am I talking
about deconvolutions?
Because we're going to try to
reverse-engineer conv networks
by adding a
deconvolutional module that
will take a specific activation
and will reverse-engineer
the trace to verify what was the
reason this activation was high.
This idea is key
not only for convs
but for any network you'll
think about in the future
when you work on it if you want
to actually reverse-engineer
the reason a specific
neuron has been active.
So let's take the example
of a 1D convolution.
This is the most
basic example just
for the sake of
understanding the math.
And I give you an
input x, which has
some padding with
two zeros at the top,
two zeros at the bottom, and
then x1 through x8 values.
And I send that input
to a 1D convolution,
which has one single filter of
size 4 with a stride of two.
What's the size of my output y?
Remember the formula.
What?
Five.
Correct.
Yes.
I assume you did this.
So you took an x, you applied
the formula and you floored it.
You didn't forget to add 1.
And then you ended up with 5.
Yeah.
Correct.
Super.
So we have our output of 5.
And let's say we define our
filter size for w1, w2, w3, w4.
It's actually easy to see
that the conv1d can be written
as a system of
equations where y1
equals w1 times 0 plus w2 times
0, because of the padding,
plus w3 times x1
plus w4 times x2.
You're just overlaying the
filter on top of the first four
indices of the inputs, and
you're doing a dot product.
Same thing with the
second one, third one,
all the way to the fifth one.
And that's your
system of equations
that describes this conv1d.
Now, because it's a
system of equations,
you could actually write it
as a matrix multiplication.
So you could say the conv1d is
literally just a weight matrix
that we multiply by the input.
So the inputs and the output
sizes we know, 5, 1 and 12, 1.
So the weight matrix
is necessarily
a 5 by 12 weight matrix.
So we just rewrote the conv1d
as a single weight matrix
that you multiply by the
input, you get the output.
If you were to draw this matrix,
this is what it would look like.
So it would be a
matrix with values
all along the diagonal
and the rest are zeros.
So that's our conclusion.
Conv1d can be rewritten as a
matrix vector multiplication.
Everybody follows?
So if you can write it as
a matrix multiplication,
remember we're talking
about reverse engineering,
then I could say
deconv is possible.
It's possible to
reverse-engineer that.
And in fact, I'm going to make
a very big assumption that
is not always true.
Sometimes it's true, but
for practical reasons,
we're in deep learning.
It's an engineering field.
We're going to assume
that W is invertible.
And so you can find
a matrix H that
is equal to the
inverse of W such
that x equals Hy so that
you're able to reverse-engineer
the signal.
I'm going to make a second
assumption in the sizes I
printed, which is even
bigger, is that W is not
only invertible,
it's also orthogonal,
meaning that its inverse
is its transpose.
It happens that
it's sometimes true.
And in fact, if you think
about an edge detector.
So let's say our filter
is minus 1, 0, 0, 0, 1.
It's an edge detector.
So I have one too many zeros.
But it's an edge detector.
And it's actually
invertible, and its inverse
is its transpose.
And so that simplifies
our reverse engineering
because we have a conv1d.
And we know that we can
write it as a matrix vector
multiplication.
And we can transpose that
matrix to reverse it.
And maybe it's not
always true, but it's
true enough for it to
work in deep learning.
Pretty much.
You're going to do
that so many times.
That's why in the literature,
oftentimes deconvolutions are
called transpose convolutions.
I give you the 1D example.
The 2D example is similar.
It's just more complicated.
There's more math, things
mix up, but same idea.
Now, there is a trick
that makes it simpler
to code the deconvolution.
And to see that trick, I just
drew x equals W transpose y.
So you have your x, which
is a vector of size 12,
although there's two padding
at the top or at the bottom.
And then I transpose the W
matrix that I was showing you.
And then I multiply that
by my vector y of size 5.
This is actually a transpose
convolution with stride 2 is
equivalent to something
slightly different,
which is a sub pixel
convolution of stride 1/2.
It's a mathematical trick.
You can do it at
home, but you would
see that these two
operations are equivalent,
meaning you can actually
flip the filter.
So you see in the left
side of the screen,
the filters are flipped.
So if you look at the
first row of my matrix,
it's not w1 through w4.
It's w4 through w1.
So I flipped the filter,
and I scanned it all the way
through the diagonal.
I also used another trick,
which is my y vector.
I inserted zeros rows
in between the values.
It's called sub-pixel.
So I inserted zeros, and
I also added some padding.
So a couple of tricks but no
need to remember it by heart.
If there's anything
you can remember,
it's that implementing
a deconvolution
in the sub-pixel
version I was describing
is similar to a convolution.
But what you do is you create a
sub-pixel version of the input
by adding zeros in between
the values and padding it.
You flip the filters, and
you divide the stride by 2.
And that's what a
deconvolution is.
So if you have a
convolutional neural network
and you want to reverse-engineer
it, you take the filters.
You flip them.
You create a sub-pixel
version of the input.
You divide the stride by
2, and you run the process.
You will have reversed
that convolution.
The reason we're doing
that is because we're just
rewriting the convolution
as another convolution.
But the hyperparameters
are different.
But it's easy to code.
You're just reusing the
same code pretty much.
Anyway, let's get
back to our example.
Here, we have an image of a dog.
We run it through ConvNet.
And we pick at some point in
that ConvNet a feature map.
We pick one feature map only
among the 256 possible feature
maps right here.
And we're going to look at the
max activation of that feature
map.
So we find the max.
Let's say it's this one.
So row 2, column 3
is the maximum number
of that feature map.
What does it mean?
It means the filter that
led to that feature map
when it looked at its input, it
was maximal in that location.
It maximally activated
in that location.
We zero out every other
entries of this matrix.
And then we reverse the network.
So we max-pooled; we unpooled.
We ReLU; we do the reverse.
We do a deconv
instead of the conv,
which is a transpose
convolution sub-pixel version,
flip the filter,
divide the stride by 2.
And we do that how many times?
Three times because
we had three blocks.
And then we should be able to
reconstruct what this activation
was maximally activated for.
And we get a cropped
version as we learned,
the cropped part of the image
that this activation was
looking at, and exactly the
pixels that maximized its value.
Does that make sense?
It's pretty complex, but it's
important to know these methods
because you might run into
something similar in the future
or be asked to interpret certain
feature maps, certain activation
maps, et cetera.
So some additional details that
we'll cover is what is unpooled
and why do we do
some ReLU in there.
So very simply, let's say I
take the maxpooling layer.
I maxpool this filter
size 2 by 2 stride of 2.
If you wanted to unpool
this, how would you do it?
Our pooling layers,
maxpooling layers invertible?
No?
Why?
Yeah.
There's no way of knowing
where the layer came from.
Yeah, exactly.
It's not invertible, because
if you pick the 6 here
on the top left, you
can tell that the 6 was
in one of these four, but
you don't where it was.
So you can't invert.
And it's very important
to where it was.
So it's not invertible,
but you could actually
use a trick to
make it invertible,
which is passing what
we call switches.
So during the
forward propagation,
you look at all your maxpooling.
And you remember with the binary
matrix, so very lightweight
matrix, where the
pooling happened,
where the maxpooling happened.
And then when you're
doing the unpooling,
you remember those switches,
so you keep them in memory,
and you pass them back.
And that should tell you
where the value came from.
So that's what we
mean by unpooling.
So I go back to my previous map.
The only thing I need to change
to be able to reverse-engineer
my network is to pass the
switches and the filters,
by the way, because
the deconv is just
the flipped version of the
filter with sub-pixel and stride
divided by 2.
And so I do that.
So you can see you can literally
invert your network here
and trace back from one
activation to the input space.
And then for ReLU
is a little odd.
I'm not going to spend too
much time on it because it's
more empirical than nothing.
But ReLU forward is
essentially zeroing out
every value that is negative
during the forward pass.
Technically, a ReLU
backward is impossible
unless you have
also the switches.
If you have the switches, you
could actually, pass linearly
back whatever was kept because
it's the identity function.
But actually that would
kill your positive signal
coming back.
So instead, you just reuse ReLU.
Basically, you use
ReLU because you
want to start from
the activation that
is the highest on
your feature map
and to keep passing the positive
signal back to the input space.
Don't worry too much about it.
It's just that ReLU
is just passed as ReLU
during the reconstruction
process, not as a proper ReLU
backward.
OK.
So here we go.
We send our dog
through the network.
We look at a specific
maxpool output.
We take the feature map.
We find the activation that is
the highest in that feature map.
We zero out all the rest.
We reverse-engineer our network.
We find the cropped
part of this dog
with the pixels that led to
that specific feature map.
We are interpreting the filter
that led that feature map,
and you can do that
anywhere across the network.
But of course, if
you're earlier,
the crop is going
to be even smaller.
If you're later,
generally bigger.
So you learned
deconvs/transpose convs.
Now, let's look at some
practical visualizations
from Matthew Zeiler
and Rob Fergus.
These are great researchers in
the space of visualizations.
They've been making
so much progress.
So they train the network.
They looked at results on a
validation set of 50,000 images.
So what you're seeing is the
first layer and specifically
the patches.
What the patches are, they're
the top 9 strongest activation
per filter.
So for each filter
in the first layer,
they look at the top 9
strongest activation.
And they remember the data
points that was leading to that.
So that's the data set search
method that we saw together.
What are the 9 images that
led to that maximum feature
map activating the most?
Print them.
Those are the patches
for each filter.
If you do that, you can already
interpret some of the filters
by seeing that,
oh, this one reacts
to edges that are
diagonal, or this one
reacts to edges that are
straight, for example.
On the bottom-right, we
actually print the filters raw.
And of course, because
it's the first layer,
it is interpretable.
So if in fact you
have an edge detector,
you should see when you
print that matrix that it
looks like an edge detector.
That doesn't work for
layers beyond one.
So now let's go a little deeper.
Now, we're going layer 2.
And we're looking
at the deconvs.
So what are they doing?
They're essentially looking
at the top 1 strongest
activation per feature
in the second layer.
So the second layer
has 256 feature maps.
They're presented here.
You pick one feature map.
You look across all these
50,000 validation images.
You find the
maximum feature map.
You take the specific
portion of that feature
map, the specific entry
that's maximally activated.
You zero out the rest.
You do your deconv.
You pass the switches,
blah, blah, blah,
and you get the cropped part
of the image that represents
why it was activated.
And this is printed
all over here.
And you can see you can
start interpreting that
by doing the top 1, or
you can do the top 9.
And if you actually
do the top 9,
you would start seeing that
in fact a certain filter have
very clear purposes.
Some filters detect circles.
Some filters detect odd shapes.
If you keep doing
that in layer 3,
you would start seeing
with the deconv method
that the filters are capturing
more complex information.
Remember, in the first
lecture, we did together.
I said that the deeper
you go in the network,
the more the
information adds up,
and you get more
complex features later.
This is a proof of
that, pretty much.
Now if you go to layer 3,
and you can do all of it.
You can do the top
9 patches where
if the nine patches
look very similar,
you can probably safely
say that this filter was
responsible for this
type of shape or color
or salient feature.
And then you can do the
deconv as well, essentially.
Let's watch together
a very short video
of Jason Yosinski that shows a
little bit of everything we've
learned together.
In school buses
and zebras, you can
tell the difference between
Maltese terriers and Yorkshire
terriers.
We now what it takes to train
these neural networks well,
but we don't know so much
about how they're actually
computing their final answers.
We developed this interactive,
deep visualization toolbox
to shine light into
these black boxes,
showing what happens
inside of neural nets.
In the top left corner,
we show the input
to the network, which
can be a still image
or video from a webcam.
These black squares
in the middle
show the activations on a
single layer of a network,
in this case, the popular deep
neural network called AlexNet,
running in cafe.
By interacting with
the network, we
can see what some of
the neurons are doing.
For example, on this first
layer, a unit in the center
responds strongly to
light to dark edges.
Its neighbor, one
neuron over, responds
to edges in the opposite
direction, dark to light.
Using optimization,
we can synthetically
produce images that light
up each neuron in this layer
to see what each
neuron is looking for.
We can scroll
through every layer--
We've seen that method
class activation.
Including convolution, pooling,
and normalization layers.
We can switch back and
forth between showing
the actual activations and
showing images synthesized
to produce high activation.
This is a class model
visualization method.
By the time you get to the
fifth convolutional layer,
the features being computed
represent abstract concepts.
For example, this neuron
seems to respond to faces.
We can further
investigate this neuron
by showing a few different
types of information.
First, we can artificially
create optimized images
using new regularization
techniques that
are described in our paper.
That's the class
model visualization.
Respond to a face and shoulders.
We can also plot
the images from--
That's the data set search.
As well pixels from those images
most responsible for the high
activations.
And that's the deconv--
Deconvolution technique.
This feature responds
to multiple faces
in different locations.
And by looking at
the deconv, we can
see that it would respond more
strongly if we had even darker
eyes and rosier lips.
We can also confirm
that it cares
about the head and shoulders
that ignores the arms and torso.
We can even see that it fires
to some extent for cat faces.
Using backprop or
deconv, we can see
that this unit
depends most strongly
on a couple units in the
previous layer conv4,
and on about a dozen
or so in conv3.
So because of deconv, you can
trace back the entire layers
before where--
The top 9 images.
OK, I'm going to leave it to
you, but you get the idea.
These researchers
built a toolkit
that essentially reproduces
some of the methods we've
seen together, although we've
seen more methods than what's
in the toolkit.
And so your kit is now able
to answer many questions
about convolution, such,
hey, what part of the input
is responsible for the output?
We now that we can use occlusion
sensitivity or class activation
maps.
What is the role of a
neuron filter layer?
We have many methods that
can allow us to do that.
Can we check what
the network focuses
on given the input image?
We have methods to do that.
And how does the neural
network see our world?
We have the gradient
ascent class
model visualization method that
allow us to maximize an input
image with respect-- sorry--
find the input image that
maximizes a certain activation.
Super.
So that was the first part.
And then we're going to
move toward frontier ideas.
Any questions on CNNs?
Do you feel like you
have a better idea
of how to look inside a CNN?
Good.
So let me start by comparing
CNNs to more modern frontier
networks.
The core distinction is going to
be that CNNs deal with localized
information.
They visualize edges, textures,
and shapes when in modern,
call it, LLMs, we visualize
relationships and meanings
between concepts
or between tokens.
And this is because transformers
are based on attention.
And that started with the
"Attention Is All You Need"
paper, which essentially
explained why attention on its
own is highly performant and can
allow us to model very complex
relationships.
By the way, this is just the
first figure of the "Attention
Is All You Need" paper, which
you should all be able to read
and understand by
now in the class.
And transformers
really represent
language using two very simple
ideas that are visualizable.
We can interpret them
to a certain extent.
The first one is the
attention patterns.
Attention looks at the
relationship between tokens.
So you look at a specific
token, which can be a word,
a sub-word or a syllable--
I'm going to simplify
by saying it's a word--
and its relationship with other
words in the training set.
And that's the attention that
the transformer looking at it.
Each attention head
learns different patterns.
So it can learn things
like linking pronouns
to nouns or tracking structures
or enforcing a certain ordering.
And then I really like
this visualization, which
is from Jesse Vig in 2019.
And this visualization
essentially
shows you there's a
very nice blog post
that he wrote with
a few figures where
you can see he presents
how attention can
be visualized in simple ways.
What is the connection between a
fixed token with the surrounding
tokens, let's say.
So this is essentially
the transformer analog
to the CNN saliency maps that
we looked at, pretty much.
The other things
that transformers
or more modern language
model uses embeddings.
During the pre-training phase,
you're also learning embeddings.
You are ready to read the
BERT paper, in fact, now
with the baggage you
have from the class.
And what's interesting
about embeddings,
and I printed a picture
here from Garg in 2021.
I also encourage you
to see that short blog
posts where he uses a
visualization method
called t-SNE.
It's a dimensionality
reduction method.
We're not going to
present it in the class,
but it's taught actually a
lot in biotech and health.
It's used very extensively
for those of you who work
with the Stanford Hospital.
And it allows you to
visualize embeddings.
And embeddings are
how the language model
perceives our words.
So you would expect
tokens that should
have similar semantic
meanings to be
next to each other
in that space,
or tokens that have nothing
to do with each other
to be far away from
each other in distance.
And that can be a
way to sanity check
that your model
actually is learning
meaningful representations.
So together attention
and embeddings
are what let large language
models track relationship
and meanings.
And you can visualize
your embeddings
with dimensionality
reduction tool.
You can even visualize
attention relationships as well.
Unfortunately, the
modern transformers
are so complicated that
even the cutting edge
research is only
able to interpret
those relationships with two
layer transformers, pretty much.
The best you find out there
is probably Anthropic's work,
so I linked two papers.
The first one is called
the "Mathematical Framework
for Transformer Circuits", which
is essentially explaining how
the different components within
a transformer interact with each
other, and they introduce
the concept of a circuit.
And then the second one is a
follow up to that paper called
"In-Context Learning
With Induction Heads".
Induction heads are
probably the best tool
we have to visualize what's
happening inside a transformer.
It's pretty complex.
You should be able to
understand it by now,
but you'd have to spend quite
some time to go deeper into it.
I just will link them.
We're not going to talk about
it for the sake of time.
Let's get to some fun stuff.
Training and
scaling diagnostics.
So how do frontier labs
check if a model is training?
Well, we've talked about
it in the first case study.
But one very natural way is
to look at the loss curves.
You can look at the training
loss, at and the validation loss
and make sure that they
follow a smooth trajectory.
And if it's not smooth,
there's probably
something that went wrong.
You've probably trained
your own network
where some loss functions
look very funky.
I remember back in the
days, there was even blogs
where people would post
their ugliest loss functions,
and there was a lot on there.
You might find sudden
jumps on the loss.
That means maybe the batch
that has been processed
has been corrupted.
Maybe you're doing
extremely well on it
when you should actually
not do that well.
And it might raise a flag.
You might find bugs in
your code because of that.
You might find gradients
that are exploding,
gradients that are vanishing.
All of that you could visualize
at the loss function level.
Now, note that loss functions
can be run at a global level
or on a specific
subset of your data.
We're going to talk about
it in data diagnostics.
The other things that are
interesting to track, also
sometimes referred to in
the community as a training
telemetry, is to watch and
track your gradient norms,
look at your learning
rate schedule,
or even look at hardware
efficiency metrics
to feel if you've underutilized
compute, which we talked about
again in the first part.
So imagine that if you're
working at a major frontier lab,
you probably have a dashboard
that tracks your different loss
function for different subsets
of the data, your checkpoints,
all of that.
You would have all of that.
Unfortunately, very
few of these are
published because they're IP.
They don't want to
give it out because it
will leak essential information
about their architecture,
about what's going well, what's
not going well, et cetera.
And that's why you find very
few information on these.
The one thing that you do
find some charts on that are
really helpful is scaling laws.
So scaling laws,
which we've talked
about in a previous
lecture, is essentially
trying to understand the
relationship between our model
performance and some other,
call it, hyperparameters
such as the model
capacity, so the size
of the model, the amount of
compute that's being used
or the data set size.
DeepMind has done
amazing work, I
think it was in 2022, a couple
of years ago, with Chinchilla.
This chart is borrowed from
the Chinchilla paper, where
essentially what I want
you to look at here
is they're comparing
the Chinchilla
model, the green
star, to other models,
including GPT-3, which
came up a little before.
And what they're showing is
that the scaling law is actually
slightly different than
what OpenAI thought.
And they analyze GPT-3.
And said GPT-3 is actually
not performing well enough
for the size that it is at.
And it was found that GPT-3 was
not trained for long enough.
They essentially explained
that if you kept training GPT-3
for longer, you would have
had way better performance.
And it was not about
the model size.
In fact, the model
was underutilized.
So they plotted these lines.
So the dotted line
is what probably we
thought in 2021, the scaling
law, the power law would be.
And they showed that it's
actually not exactly that
where essentially the idea is
they plot the full line here,
and they say this is our
analysis of the scaling law.
If your star is
above that line, it's
probably that your model
should be trained longer.
If it's on the line, it's
respecting the scaling laws
that they're finding.
And that's what's interesting
about this Chinchilla paper.
Yeah.
So this is after
OpenAI GPT model paper?
So that's after the
GPT-3 paper, Chinchilla
came in 2022 saying you should
have trained GPT-3 longer.
You would have done better.
And here's Chinchilla,
a model that
has less parameters than
GPT-3, so 70 billion
versus 175 billion.
And that is performing better.
Yes.
To go deeper, I also
pulled a few charts
that show you the power laws
between the loss function.
So on the vertical axis,
you have the test loss
that shows essentially your
performance on the test set.
And then on the horizontal
axis, on the x-axis,
you have compute data
set size and parameters.
So how are those scaling
laws established?
Essentially, they
fix two of them,
and they vary the third one.
And they see if
things are respected.
Let's say you're keeping
the same compute,
the same data set size, but
you're training a model that
is twice as big in
logarithms, what
does it tell you about the
performance, essentially?
Are those scaling
laws respected?
And so what's nice
now is that we have
a precedent for scaling laws.
So if you were actually
training such big models,
you would compare
to the scaling laws
that are available out there.
Remember, another reason
these are important
is because models training
runs are so expensive.
It wasn't shared
publicly, but we
estimate that GPT-5 is probably
in the hundreds of millions.
And so you want to know,
should I train that model
twice longer or not?
Because that's a big
financial decision.
And the scaling laws
allow you to determine,
should I invest in
compute, should I
invest in growing my data
set, so finding more data,
or should I invest
in model capacity,
making my model bigger?
Together these forms a health
dashboard for the model.
So that's training and scaling
diagnostic, loss functions,
et cetera.
Health dashboard,
scaling laws, all of that
are things that
researchers might
use to get a broad sense
of where to invest more
in terms of improving
their model.
The other one is
something we've already
seen to a certain extent,
is how labs evaluate
model capabilities and safety.
And they might do
it with benchmarks.
So capability benchmark
might be evaluating
the model in tasks like
reasoning or coding
or math or multilingual
tasks, et cetera.
It might also be
comparing checkpoints
that help you understand how
your model is improving over
time depending on what you're
feeding it, or depending
on some hyperparameters
that you're tweaking.
And also error clusters.
So just to tell you a little
more about error clusters,
if you actually use benchmarks
across a wide variety of tasks,
you might see that all the model
checkpoint number 5 is actually
doing very poorly at reasoning.
Let's see why is that.
So here are some examples from
a competitive math benchmark
2025 AIME published
by OpenAI on GPT-5.
And actually the bottom
one is from today.
This morning, Mistral announced
their third generation model.
So I thought I'd pull it to show
you how real time these things
are and just published today.
And they're comparing across
reasoning, and math, and et
cetera against benchmarks.
Now the risk is, are these
benchmarks contaminated?
How can a benchmark
be contaminated?
Yeah.
If it was in the training data.
The problem is these models are
trained on so much data online.
You don't know.
Maybe it was trained on a blog
post where someone actually
was presenting a
benchmark and describing
what the benchmark was about.
Maybe it was trained
on GitHub, and there
was a text file in a very
shady part of the GitHub
that was listing some of
the test sets information.
All of those might
contaminate benchmarks.
How would you identify that
benchmark has been contaminated,
test set has been contaminated?
Isn't that kind of what
is normal for [INAUDIBLE].
Everybody should read the
results and benchmarks,
but then the model came
up and people actually
tried it on similar tasks.
It wasn't performing well.
So it's like we're testing
it on similar stuff.
Yeah.
Llama 4 you brought
up, just to repeat,
looked good on benchmark,
looked poor in practice
after the community tested it.
The general consensus, I mean,
my opinion is, I actually
don't look too much
at the benchmarks
when a foundation model
provider publishes them.
Or in other words,
I would look at them
in relative value between models
rather than absolute value.
And you'll wait for the
community to test it,
on agentic workflows
on their tasks,
and then people will get a
taste for if it works or not,
and on what it works.
So it took some
time, for example,
for the community to realize
how good Claude was at coding,
let's say.
It was clear from the
benchmark, but others were also
clearly good.
But over time, people
felt like, oh, wow, it's
actually really good at coding.
You had a question or no?
OK.
Cool.
Oh, yeah, contamination.
So how to detect if a
test set has been exposed?
A few methods.
Some researchers might do a
search within the data set.
So let's say you
have a training set,
and you have a
held out test set.
And you actually
look for n grams.
So you take sequences
of tokens size 7, 8.
And you search
through the train set,
and you find that
they're same n grams
is also found in the test set.
There's a chance some of
it has been contaminated.
You can do it also with
hashes or with embeddings.
Actually, maybe the test set has
been contaminated but not word
for word, maybe semantically.
And so you might do the
same thing with an embedding
and run a search and
say that, oh, wow,
this specific example
from the test set
is found in the training set
semantically very similar stuff.
So you might
actually run analysis
to figure out if
it's contaminated.
And if you find that your
test set has been exposed
or you have a reason to
think it's been exposed,
what do you do?
You would usually
fix the test set.
The test set is smaller.
You would remove
all those examples
that you think are exposed,
and you would replace them
with brand new ones
that are completely held
offline in a folder that
is separate, not available
online, et cetera.
Yeah.
Then there's the problem
of safety evaluations.
I'm not going to spend
too much time on it,
but safety is important to
foundation model providers.
They stress test their model and
their many adversarial attacks,
jailbreaking, social
engineering, misuses.
They also assess harmful content
generation, hallucination,
privacy, leakage, et
cetera, et cetera.
And then they also look
at how the foundation
model behaves in an
agentic workflow,
as I was saying earlier.
So not only evaluating
it one shot,
but evaluating it in a workflow.
Here are some examples
of actually very
nice joint collaboration
between OpenAI and Anthropic
from last year, where
they work together
to assess the safety
of their models,
and they tried to jailbreak
the model to socially engineer.
And they published
some the findings
on password protection
or phrase protection.
I linked it, and
I would encourage
you to quickly look at it.
They wrote prompts to try to
extract a password from a model
and see if the model was good
at not leaking the password,
for example.
So these dashboards essentially
inform the go/no-go decision
for releasing or for determining
what the HF will be based on.
So if you're actually going
to do supervised fine-tuning
or reinforcement learning from
human feedback, it's expensive
and you want to do it on
the stuff that's failing.
So if you identify exactly
which evals are failing,
you will then use
that information
to focus the RLHF on
that specific problem
and save a lot of
money and human time.
Lastly, let me see
if there's anything
else I wanted to mention here.
Let's talk about
the data diagnostic,
and we'll end on that.
So data diagnostics, this
is probably the last area
that frontier models
are very focused on.
So how labs detect data issues.
There are many
things you can do.
But I really like
distribution check.
So I pulled this chart from
a paper called "The Pile"
from 2020 where the pile
is a very large data set,
800 gigabytes, that is
made from diverse texts.
And they kept the data domain.
So they explained using that
figure what the data set
is made of.
So the data set might be made
of information from free law,
or it might be
made of Wikipedia,
Stack Exchange,
GitHub with coding.
And so you have different
domains within that data set.
And in fact, when you
train a model on that,
you can plot the loss function
across the entire data set,
or you can plot
the loss function
across different domains
within that data set, which
give you more
intuition for where
it might be failing or working.
And so you might want to
track domain proportions
in your data set.
And domain proportions also
matter because it is observed
that if certain domains are
underrepresented in the data,
the performance of the
model on that domain
is likely going to drop in
comparison to another domain.
So all things are not equal.
If you actually have so much--
we remember with the speech
recognition example
where I said,
you have too many
zeros and too few ones,
and so the model just
doesn't learn the ones.
This is also a problem
with online learning.
So imagine those frontier
model they're learning live.
Oftentimes, they're just
being fed data constantly.
And maybe the batch
from the last month
had very little coding data.
And so the last portion of
the training, the distribution
of the coding domain,
or the frequency
was lower than other domains.
And so sometimes
you might see a drop
in performance for a specific
domain if you're not careful.
That can be fixed with
sampling like smart sampling.
You remember what we
saw in reinforcement
learning with the experience
replay, where we actually
kept experiences and we put
them in a replay memory,
and then we sampled from that.
Those are the types of
methods, sampling methods that
allow a model provider
to make sure they keep
the frequency of data domain
the same at different portions
of the training.
Token statistics, just to
mention it a little bit,
you want to count the frequency
changes for key tokens which
I was mentioning.
So let's say, a math
token is underrepresented.
That will be a problem.
The derivative symbol
is underrepresented.
That might actually lead
to way worse performance
for that specific
task where you ask
the model to make derivatives.
And so labs oftentimes monitor
token drift or distribution
or the frequency per token.
And they use sampling to fix it.
And finally the
contamination checks, which
we have talked about earlier.
I also give you
concrete examples.
I'm not going to go
through all of them.
But these are examples of token
distribution, reef reports,
tokenizer statistics,
issues that I raise here
or some anomalies on
corrupt data detection.
So if I read one of
the examples for you,
let's pick this one maybe.
Non-English tokens increase from
12% to 19% after new web crawl,
where that might mean that the
domain of that specific language
is increasing
relative to others,
and that might lead to an
increase in performance
or a drop in performance
for a different language.
As simple as that.
OK, to summarize everything,
what are examples of things
that frontier labs monitor?
Global training loss, validation
loss, both global and domain
specific on the
subset of the data,
scaling curve alignment,
comparing your test loss
to your compute to
your, to your data set,
or to your model capacity.
We didn't talk too much about
router, but mixture of experts.
Imagine you have a lot of the
models that are top models right
now or mixtures of
experts, meaning
that in your transformer block
for the multi-layer perceptron,
there's actually multiple
experts that are being trained
in parallel, and
there's a router that
will route that batch of
data to the right experts
to top 1, top 2, top 3, experts.
And it's very common for
the router to fail to
or to always exploit the
same mixture of experts.
You need a mechanism to
detect when this happens.
And so you might have in
your health dashboard some
of a router information, or
whether the mixture of experts
are all used as
much as each other.
Sometimes certain
experts are going
to be so specialized
that they're never
going to be used almost.
And you want to avoid that.
And you might do some
load balancing to avoid.
Gradient norms, learning
rates, checkpoint
to checkpoint, eval
benchmark token distribution,
tokenizer statistic.
We covered all of
that at a high level.
And as I said earlier,
frontier labs rarely
publish those dashboards
because it's IP
and because it can leak certain
deep information about their IP
and how their
models are trained.
And so you usually learn
about these things year after.
You might learn
about these things
on a model that came out three
years ago or four years ago
and they're OK now
with sharing it.
It's pretty common.
So closing remarks,
any questions first?
Yeah.
Do you, for example, Claude
training coding models.
So do they care
more about tokens
that are shown in
code in general,
or are they more worried about
having that diverse tokens?
Yeah.
So you're asking if Anthropic
is training Cloud Code,
do they care mostly
about coding data,
or do they also add other data?
Yeah, it's a tough question.
I don't have the exact answer.
It's been shown that
certain domains might
improve the performance
of other domains.
So I imagine that in coding
if you have math data,
maybe math data actually helps
the performance of coding,
especially for
functional programming,
let's say coding languages
that are more mathematical.
But I could clearly see
that if they were training
Cloud Code on web
crawl and everything,
it would not perform well
because you would have
so much crap data that is
not relevant for what you're
trying to get the model to do.
And so I think there is a
balance between those things.
So it's safe to say you
would want to be in the--
you would want to include
neighboring domains as well?
I think you could
run experiments.
So would you include
neighboring domains
if I were training
Cloud Code and I
had a lot of money to do
that, I would probably--
maybe you would start
with a Python language,
and you get as much, and there's
so much data on Python language,
so you probably have
enough already there.
But then you want a model that
scales to other programming
languages.
Well, probably Python is useful
for C++, C++ is useful for Java,
and then functional programming,
if you're going to ELIXIR,
Scala, things like that, they're
helping each other probably
to a certain extent.
But you will need to have
a presentation of those.
I could see that--
I'm pretty sure, and I
don't work at Anthropic,
so I don't know.
But I'm pretty sure, let's say
a language like Rust increases
in popularity,
which is the case.
And then in the
data distribution,
you start seeing more frequency
of those tokens from Rust.
Does that affect the
performance on other languages?
Probably yes.
That's my guess.
And how do you track it?
This is all what
we talked about.
Yeah.
If you train on publicly
available data, a lot of people
are saying to use
synthetic data.
What do you think of that?
Do you think that would
increase performance?
Yeah.
Question is, let's say we
trained on everything online
and now real data.
What about synthetic data?
Should we use it a lot?
Should we use it strategically?
What's the future of that?
So it depends of are you talking
about general purpose models
or not, specialized models?
In general, it is a good
idea to do data augmentation
to use synthetic data.
Although I would always watch
the token frequency, meaning you
can't because synthetic
data is way cheaper.
And so if you actually
generate some synthetic data
of a certain data domain, and
then it impedes on the rest
and lowers the performance on
the rest because the model just
is always trained on
that synthetic data,
then that's a problem.
In practice, I think also
the returns of synthetic data
might be plateauing
at some point.
The recent news, I guess, and if
you look at the DeepMind paper,
it's probably that we're
lacking high quality data more
than we're lacking synthetic
data for most domains right now.
But who knows if it's
going to be the case.
Some other people would
say what we're actually
lacking is letting these
agents play in RL environments
in the wild and generate their
own synthetic data or real data
but part of a game.
Nobody has quite the answer.
I would just say the
trend has gone from--
Actually you should look
at a paper from Epoch AI.
Maybe you've seen that already.
But Epoch AI has a really nice
research report which says by--
I forgot the exact
numbers, but it's in there.
By 2025, the frontier labs
would have exhausted low quality
data available online in texts.
By 2027, low quality data
in audio, image, and video
would have been exhausted.
By 2030, high quality data
would also have been exhausted.
And at that point it's
like, what's next?
Probably by that
time, data is not
going to be the
bottleneck anymore.
And it's going to be more about
model architecture, potentially.
Are we producing more data than
we're using to train the models?
Are we producing more
data than we're using?
Probably, yes.
But it doesn't mean the
models are not plateauing.
You go and you code in Python.
Your Python code is going to
be already online somewhere,
most likely, or 99% of it.
So the model is actually not
learning that much from it.
It's just more data,
not higher quality data.
And that's why I think
the plateau is there.
Maybe the best
radiologist in the world
is producing a
research paper that
is so unique that it's
high quality by definition
of what the models feel
is high quality today.
But how much of
that can we expect?
Is there a risk that
the model gives training
on data information [INAUDIBLE]
and that data is probably
a bad idea to train on
this thing [INAUDIBLE]
we produce for what.
What would that [INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, it's risky.
Is it risky for the
model to-- the model,
let's say is online
learning, so it's
learning from new data
being produced by everyone.
Is that going to risk the
model performance to drop?
Essentially, that's
what you're asking?
[INAUDIBLE] anyone
at the end of the day
is also [INAUDIBLE] because
most people have used data.
Yeah, yeah.
In that case, yeah.
Yeah, the data produced
is also coming out of AI.
Yeah, for sure, more
today than before.
Coding data today is
increasingly generated.
And so it's just fed back.
So just long story
short, it's not
that interesting for training.
Super.
So closing remarks and
reminder on what's next.
So by the way, I hope you
feel after this lecture
that you have a better
understanding of the techniques
that you can use in order
to look inside a model,
look outside the model, both for
CNNs and for frontier models.
Again, it's just a
two-hour lecture.
We don't have time to go so
deep as much as I would like it
in each of these domains.
It's my last
lecture this quarter
and so thank you
for participating.
I enjoyed spending
time with you all.
I hope you spend time
on your projects.
Projects can be very
delightful in CS230.
Over the years, I've seen people
use their products to get a job,
to start a company,
to make friends.
And so I don't think
you will regret
putting time and effort
into your projects,
even if we don't have
too much time left.
Those are the last milestones
or deliverables for the class.
I hope you enjoyed the class.
We're always looking
for feedback.
And so I'm eager to
hear from you all.
Thank you.