Hi, everyone.
Welcome to another lecture
for CS230 Deep Learning.
Today, we're going to talk about
enhancing large language model
applications.
And I call this
lecture Beyond LLM.
It has a lot of newer content.
And the idea behind
this lecture is
we started to learn
about neurons,
and then we learned
about layers,
and then we learned about
deep neural networks,
and then we learned a little bit
about how to structure projects
in C3.
And now we're going one level
beyond into, what would it
look if you were building
agentic AI systems at work,
in a startup, in a company?
And it's probably one of
the more practical lectures.
Again, the goal is
not to build a product
end to end in the
next hour or so,
but rather to tell
you all the techniques
that AI engineers have cracked,
figured out, are exploring,
so that after the class,
you have the breadth of view
of different
prompting techniques,
different agentic workflows,
multi-agent systems, evals.
And then when you
want to dive deeper,
you have the baggage to
dive deeper and learn faster
about it.
Let's try to make it as
interactive as possible, as
usual.
When we look at the
agenda, the agenda
is going to start with the
core idea behind challenges
and opportunities
for augmenting LLMs.
So we start from a base model.
How do we maximize the
performance of that base model?
Then we'll dive deep into the
first line of optimization,
which is prompting methods, and
we'll see a variety of them.
Then we'll go slightly deeper.
If we were to get our
hands under the hood
and do some fine tuning,
what would it look like?
I'm not a fan of fine tuning,
and I talk a lot about that,
but I'll explain why I try to
avoid fine tuning as much as
possible.
And then we'll do a section 4 on
Retrieval-Augmented Generation,
or RAG, which you've probably
heard of in the news.
Maybe some of you
have played with RAGs.
We're going to
unpack what a RAG is
and how it works and then the
different methods within RAGs.
And then we'll talk about
agentic AI workflows.
I'll define it.
Andrew Ng is one
of the first ones
to have called this trend
agenetic AI workflows.
And so we look at the
definition that Andrew
gives to agentic
workflows, and then we'll
start seeing examples.
The section 6 is very practical.
It's a case study where we will
think about an agentic workflow,
and I'll ask you to measure
if the agent actually works,
and we brainstorm
how we can measure
if an agentic
workflow is working
the way you want it to work.
There's plenty of methods called
evals that solve that problem.
And then we'll look briefly
at multi-agent workflow.
And then we can have a
open-ended discussion
where I share some thoughts
on what's next in AI.
And I'm looking forward
to hearing from you all,
as well, on that one.
So let's get started with the
problem of augmenting LLMs.
So open-ended question for you--
you are all familiar
with pre-trained models
like GPT 3.5 Turbo or GPT 4.0.
What's the limitation of
using just a base model?
What are the typical
issues that might
arise as you're using a
vanilla pre-trained model?
Yes.
It lacks some domain knowledge.
Lacks some domain knowledge.
You're perfectly right.
We had a group of
students a few years ago.
It was not LLM related, but
they were building an autonomous
farming device or vehicle that
had a camera underneath, taking
pictures of crops to
determine if the crop is
sick or not, if it
should be thrown away,
if it should be used or not.
And that data set is not a
data set you find out there.
And the base model or
pre-trained computer vision
model would lack that
knowledge, of course.
What else?
Yes.
[INAUDIBLE] pictures are
very dark [INAUDIBLE]
OK, maybe the-- you're saying--
so just to repeat
for people online,
you're saying the model
might have been trained
on high-quality data,
but the data in the wild
is actually not
that high quality.
And in fact, yes, the
distribution of the real world
might differ, as we've seen with
GANs, from the training set,
and that might create an
issue with pre-trained models.
Although pre-trained
LLMs are getting better
at handling all
sorts of data inputs.
Yes.
Lacks current information.
Lack what?
Current information.
Lacks current information.
The LLM is not up to date.
And in fact, you're right.
Imagine you have to retrain
from scratch your LLM
every couple of months.
One story that I found funny--
it's from probably three years
ago or maybe more five years
ago, where during
his first presidency,
President Trump one
day tweeted, "Covfefe."
You remember that tweet or no?
Just "Covfefe."
And it was probably a typo
or it was in his pocket.
I don't know.
But that word did not exist.
The LLMs, in fact, that
Twitter was running at the time
could not recognize that word.
And so the recommender
system sort of went wild,
because suddenly everybody was
making fun of that tweet using
the word "Covfefe," and the LLM
was so confused on, what does
that mean?
Where should we show it?
To whom should we show it?
And this is an example
of a-- nowadays,
especially on social media,
there's so many new trends,
and it's very hard to retrain
an LLM to match the new trend
and understand the
new words out there.
I mean, you oftentimes hear Gen
Z words like "rizz" or "mid"
or whatever.
I don't know all of them.
But you probably want
to find a way that
can allow the LLM to understand
those trends without retraining
the LLM from scratch.
What else?
It's trained to have a
breadth of knowledge.
And if you wanted to do
something specialized,
that might limit [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah, it might be trained
on a breadth of knowledge,
but it might fail or
not perform adequately
on a narrow task that
is very well defined.
Think about enterprise
applications that--
yeah, enterprise application.
You need high precision,
high fidelity, low latency.
And maybe the model is not
great at that specific thing.
It might do fine, but
just not good enough.
And you might want to
augment it in a certain way.
Yeah.
Maybe it has [INAUDIBLE]
so it makes the model
a lot heavier, a lot slower.
[INAUDIBLE]
So maybe it has a lot of broad
domain knowledge that might not
be needed for your application.
And so you're using a
massive, heavy model
when you actually are only using
2% of the model capability.
You're perfectly right.
You might not need all of it.
So you might find ways to prune,
quantize the model, modify it.
All of these are good points.
I'm going to add a
few more, as well.
LLMs are very
difficult to control.
Your last point is actually
an example of that.
You want to control the LLM to
use a part of its knowledge,
but it's not--
it's, in fact, getting confused.
We've seen that in history.
In 2016, Microsoft created
a notorious Twitter
bot that learned from users, and
it quickly became a racist jerk.
Microsoft ended up removing the
bot 16 hours after launching it.
The community was really
fast at determining
that this was a racist bot.
And you can empathize with
Microsoft in the sense
that it is actually
hard to control an LLM.
They might have done a better
job to qualify before launching,
but it is really hard
to control an LLM.
Even more recently,
this is a tweet
from Sam Altman
last November, where
there was this debate
between Elon Musk and Sam
Altman on whose LLM is
the left wing propaganda
machine or the right
wing propaganda machine,
and they were hating
on each other's LLMs.
But that tells you,
at the end of the day,
that even those two teams, Grok
and OpenAI, which are probably
the best funded team
with a lot of talent,
are not doing a great job
at controlling their LLMs.
And from time to time,
if you hang out on X,
you might see screenshots of
users interacting with LLMs
and the LLM saying something
really controversial
or racist or something that
would not be considered great
by social standards, I guess.
And that tells you that the
model is really hard to control.
The second aspect
of it is something
that you mentioned earlier.
LLMs may underperform
in your task,
and that might include
specific knowledge gaps,
such as medical diagnosis.
If you're doing
medical diagnosis,
you would rather have an LLM
that is specialized for that
and is great at it
and, in fact, something
that we haven't mentioned
as a group, has sources.
So the answer is
sourced specifically.
You have a hard time
believing something
unless you have the actual
source of the research that
backs it up.
Inconsistencies in
style and format--
so imagine you're building
a legal AI agentic workflow.
Legal has a very specific
way to write and read,
where every word counts.
If you're negotiating
a large contract,
every word on that contract
might mean something else
when it comes to the court.
And so it's very
important that you use
an LLM that is very good at it.
The precision matters.
And then task-specific
understanding,
such as doing a classification
on a niche field,
here I pulled an example where--
let's say a biotech product is
trying to use an
LLM to categorize
user reviews into positive,
neutral, or negative.
Maybe for that
company, something
that would be considered a
negative review typically
is actually considered
a neutral review
because the NPS of
that industry tends
to be way lower than other
industries, let's say.
That's a task-specific
understanding,
and the LLM needs to
be aligned to what
the company believes is the
categorization that it wants.
We will see an example of how to
solve that problem in a second.
And then limited
context handling--
a lot of AI applications,
especially in the enterprise,
have required data that
has a lot of context.
Just to give you
a simple example,
knowledge management
is an important space
that enterprises buy a lot
of knowledge management tool.
When you go on your drive and
you have all your documents,
ideally, you could have an LLM
running on top of that drive.
You can ask any question,
and it will read immediately
thousands of documents
and answer, what was
our Q4 performance in sales?
It was x dollars.
It finds it super quickly.
In practice, because LLMs do
not have a large enough context,
you cannot use a standalone
vanilla pre-trained LLM to solve
that problem.
You will have to augment it.
Does that make sense?
The other aspect around context
windows is they are, in fact,
limited.
If you look at the context
windows of the models
from the last five years,
even the best models
today will range in context,
window, or number of tokens
it can take as input, somewhere
in the hundreds of thousands
of tokens max.
Just to give you a sense,
200,000 tokens is roughly two
books.
So that's how much
you can upload
and it can read, pretty much.
And you can imagine
that when you're
dealing with video
understanding or heavier data
files, that is, of
course, an issue.
So you might have to chunk it.
You might have to embed it.
You might have to
find other ways
to get the LLM to
handle larger contexts.
The attention mechanism is
also powerful, but problematic,
because it does not do
a great job at attending
in very large contexts.
There is actually an
interesting problem
called needle in a haystack.
It's an AI problem where--
or call it a benchmark--
where, in order to test if your
LLM is good at putting attention
on a very specific fact
within a large corpus,
researchers might
randomly insert
in about one sentence
that outlines
a certain fact,
such as Arun and Max
are having coffee
at Blue Bottle,
in the middle of the
Bible, let's say,
or some very long text.
And then you ask the LLM,
what were Arun and Max having
at Blue Bottle?
And you see if it remembers
that it was coffee.
It's actually a complex problem,
not because the question
is complex, but because
you're asking the model
to find a fact within
a very large corpus,
and that's complicated.
So, again, this is a
limiting factor for LLMs.
We'll talk about
RAG in a second.
But I want to preview--
there is debates
around whether RAG
is the right long-term
approach for AI systems.
So as a high-level idea, a RAG
is a mechanism, if you will,
that embeds documents that
an LLM can retrieve and then
add as context to its initial
prompt and answer a question.
It has lots of application.
Knowledge management
is an example.
So imagine you have
your drive again.
But every document is
compressed in representation,
and the LLM has
access to that lower
dimensional representation.
The debates that this tweet
from [INAUDIBLE] outlines
is, in theory, if we
have infinite compute,
then RAG is useless.
Because you can just read a
massive corpus immediately
and answer your question.
But even in that case,
latency might be an issue.
Imagine the time
it takes for an AI
to read all your drive every
single time you ask a question.
It doesn't make sense.
So RAG has other advantages
beyond even the accuracy.
On top of that, the
sourcing matters, as well.
So it might-- RAG
allows you to source.
We'll talk about all that later.
But there's always this
debate in the community
whether a certain method
is actually future proof.
Because in practice, as compute
power doubles every year,
let's say, some of the methods
we're learning right now
might not be relevant
three years from now.
We don't know, essentially.
And the analogy that he
makes on context windows
and why RAG approaches might
be relevant even a long time
from now is search.
When you search on
a search engine,
you still find sources
of information.
And in fact, in the
background, there
is very detailed
traversal algorithms
that rank and find the specific
links that might be the best
to present you versus if you
had to read-- imagine you had
to read the entire web every
single time you're doing
a search query, without
being able to narrow
to a certain portion
of the space.
That might, again,
not be reasonable.
OK, when we're thinking
of improving LLMs,
the easiest way we think
of it is two dimensions.
One dimension is we are going
to improve the foundation
model itself.
So, for example, we move
from GPT 3.5 Turbo, to GPT 4,
to GPT 4.0, to GPT 5.
Each of that is supposed
to improve the base model.
GPT 5 is another debate because
it's packaging other models
within itself.
But if you're thinking
about 3.5, 4, and 4.0,
that's really what it is.
The pre-trained model improves.
And so you should
see your performance
improve on your tasks.
But the other dimension is
we can actually engineer--
leverage the LLM in a
way that makes it better.
So you can prompt
simply GPT 4.0.
You can change some prompts
and improve the prompt,
and it will improve
the performance.
It's shown.
You can even put
a RAG around it.
You can put an agentic
workflow around it.
You can even put a
multi-agent system around it.
And that is another dimension
for you to improve performance.
So that's how I want you
to think about it-- which
LLM I'm using, and
then how can I maximize
the performance of that LLM?
This lecture is about
the vertical axis.
Those are the methods
that we will see together.
Sounds good for
the introduction.
So let's move to
prompt engineering.
I'm going to start with
an interesting study just
to motivate why prompt
engineering matters.
There is a study
from HBS, UPenn,
as well as Harvard
Business School, and--
well, there is also
involved Wharton--
that took a subset
of BCG consultants,
individual contributors,
split them into three groups.
One group had no access to AI.
One group had access to--
I think it was GPT 4.
And then one group
had access to the LLM,
but also a training on
how to prompt better.
And then they observed the
performance of these consultants
across a wide variety of tasks.
There's a few things
that they noticed
that I thought was interesting.
One is something they
called the jagged frontier,
meaning that certain tasks
that consultants are doing fall
beyond the jagged frontier,
meaning AI is not good enough.
It's not improving
human performance.
In fact, it's actually
making it worse.
And some tasks are
within the frontier,
meaning that AI is actually
significantly improving
the performance, the speed,
the quality of the consultant.
Many tasks fell within and
many tasks fell without,
and they shared their insights.
But the TLDR is--
there is a frontier within
which AI is absolutely helping
and one where they call out
this behavior, or falling asleep
at the wheel, where people
relied on AI on a task that
was beyond the frontier.
And in fact, it
ended up going worse
because the human was not
reviewing the outputs carefully
enough.
They did note that the
group that was trained
was the best, better than the
group that was not trained
on prompt engineering,
which also motivates why
this lecture matters, so
that you're within that group
afterwards.
One other insights were the
centaurs and the cyborgs.
They noticed that
consultants had the tendency
to work with AI in
one of two ways,
and you might, yourself, be
part of one of these groups.
The centaurs are
mythical creatures
that are half human, half--
I think, half, what, horses?
Yeah?
Horses?
Half horses, half something.
And those were individuals
that would divide and delegate.
They might give a pretty
big task to the AI.
So imagine you're working on a
PowerPoint, which consultants
are known to do.
You might actually write
a very long prompt on how
you want it to do your
PowerPoint and then let it
work for some time
and then come back
and it's done, when others
would act as cyborgs.
Cyborgs are fully blended,
bionic human robots,
human and robot, augmented
with robotic parts.
And those individuals will
not delegate fully a task.
They would actually work
super quickly with the model
back and forth.
I find that a lot of students
are actually more working
like cyborgs than centaurs, but
while maybe in the enterprise,
when you're trying to
automate the workflow,
you're thinking
more like a centaur.
That's just something
good to keep in mind.
Also, a lot of companies
will tell you, oh, we're
hiring prompt
engineers, et cetera.
It's [? a cure. ?]
I don't buy that.
I think it's just a skill
that everybody should have.
You're not going to
make a [? cure ?] out
of prompt engineering,
but you're probably
going to use it as a very
powerful skill in your career.
So let's talk about basic
prompt design principles.
I'm giving you a very
simple prompt here.
Summarize this document,
and then the document
is uploaded alongside it.
And the model has not
much context around
what should be the summary?
How long should be the summary?
What should it talk
about, et cetera?
You can actually improve these
prompts by doing something like
summarize this 10-page
scientific paper on renewable
energy in five bullet points,
focusing on key findings
and implications
for policymakers.
That's already better.
You're sharing the
audience, and it's
going to tailor it
to the audience.
You're saying that you
want five bullet points,
and you want to focus
only on key findings.
That's a better prompt,
you would argue.
How could you even make
this prompt better?
What are other
techniques that you've
heard of or tried yourself that
could make this one shot prompt
better?
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
OK.
Right example.
So say, you mean, here is an
example of a great summary.
Yeah.
You're right.
That's a good idea.
[INAUDIBLE]
Very popular technique.
Act like a renewable energy
expert giving a conference
at Davos, let's say, yeah.
That's great.
Someone-- yeah.
Say you're really good at it.
Yeah.
You are the best in
the world at this.
Explain.
Yeah.
Actually, I mean,
these things work.
It's funny, but it does work
to say act like x, y, z.
It's a very popular
prompt template.
We'll see a few examples.
What else could you do?
Yes.
Of course, you'd like to
critique your own model.
Critique your own project.
So you're using reflection.
So you might actually
do one output
and then ask it to critique
it and then give it back.
Yeah.
We see that.
That's a great one.
That's the one that
probably works best
within those typically,
but we see some examples.
What else?
Yeah.
Break the task down into steps.
OK.
You know how that is called?
No.
OK.
Chain of thoughts.
So this is actually
a popular method
that's been shown in
research that it improves.
You could actually give
a clear instruction
and also encourage the
model to think step
by step approach, the
task step by step,
and do not skip any step.
And then you give it some
steps, such as step one,
identify the three most
important findings.
Step two, explain
how key each finding
impact renewable energy policy.
Step three, write the
five-bullet summary
with each point addressing
a finding, et cetera.
So chain of thoughts, I linked
the paper from 2023 that
popularized chain of thoughts.
Chain of thoughts
is very popular
right now, especially
in AI startups
that are trying to
control their LLMs.
OK.
To go back to your examples
about act like XYZ, what
I like to do, Andrew Ng
also talks about that,
is to look at other
people's prompts.
And in fact, in online, you have
a lot of prompt repositories
for free on GitHub.
In fact, I linked the awesome
prompt template repo on GitHub,
where you have so many
examples of great prompts
that engineers have built. They
said it works great for us,
and they published it online.
And a lot of them
start with act as.
Act as a Linux terminal.
Act as an English translator.
Act like a position
interviewer, et cetera.
The advantage of
a prompt template
is that you can actually
put it in your code
and scale it for
many user requests.
So let me give you an
example from Workera.
Workera evaluates skill.
Some of you have taken
the assessments already.
And tries to personalize
it to the user.
And in fact, if you actually
read in an HR system
in an enterprise,
in the HR system,
you might have a Jane is
a product manager level 3,
and she is in the US, and her
preferred language is English.
And actually, that
metadata can be
inserted in a prompt templates
that will personalize
personalized for Jane.
And similarly for Joe, whose is
preferred language is Spanish,
it will tailor it to Joe.
And that's called
a prompt template.
[INAUDIBLE]
So the question is do
the foundation models
use a prompt
templates, or do you
have to integrate it yourself?
So the foundation
models probably
use a system prompt
that you don't see.
Like when actually,
you type on ChatGPT,
it is possible, it's not public,
that OpenAI behind the scenes
has like act like a very
helpful assistant for this user.
And by the way, here is
your memories about the user
that we kept in a database.
You can actually
check your memories.
And then your prompt goes under,
and then the generation starts.
So probably, they're
using something like that.
But it doesn't mean you
can't add one yourself.
So in fact, if you think about a
prompt template for the Workera
example I was showing,
maybe it starts
when you call OpenAI by act
like a helpful assistant.
And then underneath, it's like
act like a great AI mentor that
helps people in their career.
And OpenAI is,
from template, also
has follow the instruction
from the creator
or something like that.
It's possible.
Questions about
prompt templates.
Again, I would encourage you to
go and read examples of prompts.
Some of them are
quite thoughtful.
Let's talk about zero shot
versus few shot prompting.
It came up earlier.
Here's an example.
Again, going back to the
categorization of product
reviews, let's say that
we're working on a task
where the prompt is classify
the tone of the sentence
as positive,
negative, or neutral.
And then you paste the review,
which is the product is fine,
but I was expecting more.
If I were to survey the room,
I would bet that some of you
would say it's negative.
Some of you would
say it's neutral.
Because you actually
have a first part
that is relatively positive.
It's fine.
And then the second part,
I was expecting more,
which is relatively negative.
So where do you land?
This can be a
subjective question.
And maybe in one industry, this
would be considered amazing.
And another one, it would
be considered really bad
because people are used to
really flourishing reviews.
And so the way you can actually
align the model to your task
is by converting that
zero shot prompt.
Zero shot refers to
the fact that it's not
being given any example.
Into a few short
prompts, where the model
is given in the prompt, a set
of examples to align it to what
you want it to do.
So the example
here is again, you
paste the same prompt as
before with the user review.
And then you add,
here are examples
of tone classifications.
These exceeded my
expectation completely.
Positive.
It's OK, but I wish
it had more features.
Negative.
The service was adequate.
Neither good nor bad.
Neutral.
Now classify the
tone of this sentence
after you've heard
about these things,
and the model then
says negative.
And the reason it says
negative, of course,
is likely because of the second
example, which was it's OK,
but I wish it had more features,
which we told the model that
was negative.
Because the model saw
that it's aligned now
with your expectations.
A few short prompts
are very popular.
And in fact, for
AI startups that
are slightly more
sophisticated, you
might see them keep
a prompt up to date.
Whenever a user says
something and they
might have a human
label it and then
add it as a few shots
in their relevant
prompts in their code base.
You can think of that as
almost building a data set.
But instead of actually
building a separate data set
like we've seen with
supervised fine tuning
and then fine tuning
the model on it,
you're just putting it
directly in the prompt.
It turns out it's
probably faster
to do that if you want
to experiment quickly
because you don't touch
the model parameters.
You just update your prompts.
And if it's text
examples, you can actually
concatenate so many
examples in a single prompt.
At some point, it
will be too long,
and you will not have the
necessary context window.
But it's a pretty
strong approach
that is quick to align an LLM.
OK?
Yes.
[INAUDIBLE]
So the question was is there
any research on how long
the prompt can be before
the model essentially loses
itself or doesn't follow
instructions anymore?
There is.
The problem is that research
is outdated every few months
because models get better.
And so I don't know where
the state of the art is.
You can probably find
it online on benchmarks
on like we see that--
I give you an example.
On the Workera product, you
have a voice conversation
for some of you
that have tried it,
where you're asked to
explain what is the prompt.
And then you explain,
and then there's
a scoring algorithm in behind.
We know that after eight
turns, the model loses itself.
After eight turns,
because you always
paste the previous
user response,
it just starts going wild.
And so the techniques
we use in the background
is we actually create
chapters of the conversation.
Maybe one chapter is
the first eight prompt.
And then you actually start
over from another prompt.
You can summarize the first
part of the conversation,
insert the summary,
and then keep going.
Those are engineering hacks that
engineers might have figured out
in the background.
Because eight turns makes a
prompt quite long actually.
Let's move on to chaining.
Chaining is the most popular
technique out of everything
we've seen so far in
prompt engineering.
It's not chain of thought.
So chain of thought we've
seen is think step by step,
step 1, step 2, step 3.
Do not skip any step.
This is different.
This is chaining complex
prompt to improve performance,
and this is what it looks like.
You take a single step prompt,
such as read this customer
review and write a
professional response that
acknowledges their concern,
explains the issue,
offers a resolution,
and then you
paste the customer review,
which is I ordered a laptop.
It arrived three days late.
The packaging was damaged.
Very disappointing.
I needed that urgently for work.
And then the output
is an email that
is immediately given
to you by the LLM
after it reads the prompt.
So this might work, but it
might be hard to control.
Because think about it.
There's multiple steps
that you have listed,
and everything is embedded
in the same prompt.
And if you wanted to debug step
by step and know which step is
weaker, you couldn't.
You would have everything
mixed together.
So one advantage of chaining is
you would separate the prompts,
so that you can debug
them separately.
And it will also lead
to an easier manner
to improve your workflow.
Let's say a first prompt
is extract the key issues.
Identify the key
concerns mentioned
in this customer review.
Pace the customer review.
Second prompt.
Using these issues, so
you paste back the issues,
draft an outline for a
professional response that
acknowledges concerns,
explains possible reasons,
and offer a resolution.
So this is not--
Prompt number 3, write
the full response.
So using the outline, write
the professional response.
And then you get
your final output.
So in theory, you can tell
me, oh, the second approach
is better than the
first one at first.
But what you can notice
is that we can actually
test those three prompts
separately from each other
and determine if we will get the
most gains out of engineering
the first prompt, optimizing
it, or the second one,
or the third one.
We now have three prompts that
are independent from each other.
And maybe if the
outline was better,
the performance of the email,
how much the open rate will be
or the user satisfaction
on the response
will actually get higher.
And so chaining improves
performance but performance,
but most importantly, helps
you control your workflow
and debug it more seamlessly.
Yes.
So if we that the three prompts
independently work really well,
if we combine them
into one prompt,
and we highlight a step
by step thinking process,
does on average, we get
a [INAUDIBLE] by itself,
or do we still have
to do that breakdown?
So let me try to rephrase.
You say, let's say we look
at the first prompt which
has all three tasks
built in that prompt.
What exactly do you mean?
You mean like if we
evaluate the output
and we measure some user
insight, satisfaction,
et cetera?
Why don't we just modify that
prompt and essentially see how
it improves user satisfaction?
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
I see.
So why do we need
the three steps?
I mean, think about it.
The intermediate output
is what you want to see.
Like if I'm debugging
the first approach,
the way I would do it is I
would capture user insights.
Like here's the email.
How good was the response?
Thumbs up, thumbs down.
Was your issue resolved?
Those would tell me
how good is my prompt.
And I can engineer that
prompt, optimize it,
and I would probably
drive some gains.
But I will not be able
easily to trace back
to what the problem was.
While in the second
approach, not only I
can use the end to end
metrics to improve my process.
I can also use the
intermediate steps.
For example, if I look at prompt
2 and I look at the outline
and I see the outline is
actually, meh, it's not great,
then I think I can get a lot
of gains out of the outline.
Or the outline is
actually really good,
but the last prompt doesn't do
a good job at translating it
into an email.
So the outline is exactly
what I want the LLM to do,
but the translation in
a customer facing email
is not good.
In fact, it doesn't follow
our vocabulary internally.
Then I knew the
third prompt is where
I would get the most gains.
So that's what it
allows me to do,
have intermediate
steps to review.
Are there any
latency [INAUDIBLE]
We'll talk about it.
Are there any latency concerns?
Yes.
In certain applications, you
don't want to use a chain
or you don't want to use a long
chain because it adds latency.
We'll talk about that later.
Good point.
So practically, this is
what chaining complex
prompts look like.
You have your first prompt
with your first task.
It outputs.
The output is pasted
in the second prompt
with the second
task being defined.
The output is then pasted
into the third prompt
with the third task
being defined and so on.
That's what it looks
like in practice.
Super.
We'll talk more later
about testing your prompts,
but there are
methods now to do it,
and we'll see later in this
lecture with our case study
how we can test our prompts.
But here is an example
of how you might do it.
You might have a
summarization workflow prompts
that is the baseline.
It's a single prompt.
You might have a
refined summarization
which is a modified
prompt of this,
or a workflow with a chain.
And then you have your test
case, which is the input
that you want to
summarize, let's say.
And then you have
the generated output.
And you can have humans
go and rate these outputs.
And you would notice that the
baseline is better or worse
than the refined prompt.
Of course, this manual
approach takes time,
but it's a good way to start.
And usually, the advice is
get hands on at the beginning
because you would quickly
notice some issues,
and it will give you better
intuition on what tweaks
can lead to better performance.
However, if you wanted
to scale that system
across many products, many
parts of your code base,
you might want to find a
way to do that automatically
without asking humans to
review and grade summaries.
One approach is
to use platforms,
like at Workera, our team uses a
platform called Prompt Food that
allows you to actually
automate part of this testing.
In a nutshell,
what it does is it
can allow you to run the same
prompt with five different LLMs
immediately, put
everything in a table.
That makes it super easy for
a human to grade, let's say.
Or alternatively, it might
allow you to define LLM judges.
LLM judges can come
in different flavors.
For example, I can
have an LLM judge that
does a pairwise comparison.
So what the LLM is asked to
do is here are two summaries.
Just tell me which one is
better than the other one.
That's what the LLM does.
And that can be used
as a proxy for how good
the summarization baseline
versus the refined version is.
Another way to do
an LLM judge is
if you do it for a
single answer grading,
so here's a summary
graded from 1 to 5.
And then you can go
even deeper and do
a reference-guided
pairwise comparison.
Or you add also a rubric.
You say a 5 is when a summary
is below 100 characters.
I'm just making up.
Below 100 characters.
Mentions at least
three key points
that are distinct and starts
with a first sentence that
displays the overview and
then goes into the detail.
That's a great summary,
number 5 out of a 5.
0 is the LLM failed to summarize
and actually was very verbose,
let's say.
And so you put a
Rubrik behind it,
and you have an LLM as
just finding the rubric.
Of course, you can now
pair different techniques.
You can do a few
shots for the rubric.
You can actually give examples
of a 5 out of 5s, 4 out of 4s,
3 out of 3s because now,
you multiple techniques.
Does that make sense?
Yeah.
OK.
So that was the second
section on prompt engineering
or the first line
of optimization.
Now, let's say you've
exhausted all your chances
for prompt
engineering, and you're
thinking about actually touching
the model, modifying its weights
or fine tuning it
in other words.
I was telling you, I'm
not a fan of fine tuning.
There's a few reasons why.
One, it requires substantial
labeled data typically
to fine tune.
Although now, there
are approaches
that are getting better
at fine tuning that
look more few shot prompting
actually than fine tuning.
It's sort of merging.
Although one
modifies the weight,
the other doesn't
modify the weights.
Fine tuned models may also
overfit to specific data.
We're going to see a
funny example actually.
Losing their general
purpose utility.
So you might fine tune a model.
And actually, when someone
asks a pretty generic question,
it doesn't do well anymore.
It might do well on your task.
So it might be relevant or not.
And then it's time
and cost-intensive.
That's my main problem.
And at Workera, we
steer away from fine
tuning as much as possible.
Because by the time you're
done fine tuning your model,
the next model is
out, and it's actually
beating your fine tuned
version of the previous model.
So I would steer away from
fine tuning as much as you can.
The advantage of the prompt
engineering methods we've seen
is you can put the next best
pre-trained model directly
in your code.
It will update
everything immediately.
Fine tuning doesn't
work like that.
There are advantages though
where it still makes sense.
If the task requires repeated
high precision outputs
such as legal,
scientific explanation
and if the general
purpose LLM struggles
with domain-specific language.
So let's look at a
quick example together,
which is an example
from Ros Lazerowitz.
I think it was a couple of
years ago, September 23,
where Ros tried to
do Slack fine tuning.
So he looked at a lot of Slack
messages within his company.
And he was like, I'm
going to fine tune
a model that speaks like us or
operates like us because this
is how we work.
This is the data that represents
how people work at the company.
And so he actually went ahead
and fine tuned the model,
gave it a prompt,
like, hey, write--
he was delegating to the model.
A 500-word blog post
on prompt engineering.
And the model responded, I shall
work on that in the morning.
And then he tries to push the
model a little further and say,
it's morning now.
And the model said,
I'm writing right now.
It's 6:30 AM here.
Write it now.
OK, I shall write it now.
I actually don't what
you would like me to say
about prompt engineering.
I can only describe the process.
The only thing that comes
to mind for a headline
is how do we build prompt?
It's kind of a funny example for
fine tuning because it's true
that it went wrong.
Like he was supposed
to think like I want
the model to speak
like us at work.
And it ended up
acting like people
and not actually
following instructions.
So one example why I would
steer away from fine tuning.
Super.
Let's talk about RAGs.
RAGs is important.
It's important to out there
and at least having the basics.
It's a very common interview
question, by the way.
If you go interview
for a job, they
might ask you to
explain in a nutshell
to a five-year-old
what is a RAG.
And hopefully after that,
you'll be able to do it.
So we've seen some of the
challenges with standalone LLMs.
Those challenges include the
context window being small,
the fact that it's hard
to remember details
within a large context window,
knowledge gaps, cutoff dates,
you mentioned earlier.
The model might be
trained up to a date,
and then it cannot follow
the trends or be up to date.
Hallucinations.
There are some fields.
Think about medical
diagnosis, where
hallucinations are very costly.
You can't afford
a hallucination.
Even in education, imagine
deploying a model for the US
youth education,
and it hallucinates,
and it teaches millions
of people something
completely wrong.
It's a problem.
And then lack of sources.
A lot of fields love sources.
Research fields love sources.
Education love sources.
Legal loves sources as well.
And so the pre-trained LLM
doesn't do a good job to source.
And in fact, if you have tried
to find sources on a plain LLM,
it actually hallucinates a lot.
It makes up research papers.
It just lists like
completely fake stuff.
So how do we solve
that with a RAG?
RAG integrates with external
knowledge sources, databases,
documents, APIs.
It ensures that answers are
more accurate, up to date,
and grounded because you can
actually update your document.
Your drive is always up to date.
I mean, ideally, you're always
pushing new documents to it.
And when you query, what is
our Q4 performance in sales?
Hopefully there is the last
board deck in the drive,
and it can read the
last board deck.
And more developer control.
We'll see why RAGs allow
for targeted customization
without actually requiring
the retraining of the model.
In fact, you don't touch
the model with RAGs.
It's really a technique that
is put on top of the model.
So to see an example
of a RAG, this
is a question answering
application where
we're in the medical field,
and a user is asking a query,
what are the side
effects of drug X?
This is an important question.
You can't hallucinate.
You need to source.
You need to be up to date.
Maybe there is a new
update to that drug that
is now in the database,
and you need to read that.
So a RAG is a great example of
what you would want to use here.
The way it works is
you have your knowledge
base of a bunch of documents.
What you do is you
use an embedding
to embed those
documents into lower
dimensional representations.
So for example, if the
document is a PDF, a long PDF,
you might read the
PDF, understand it,
and then embed it.
We've seen plenty of
embedding approaches
together, triplet loss,
et cetera, you remember?
So imagine one of
them here for LLMs
is embedding those documents
into lower representation.
If the representation
is too small,
you will lose information.
If it's too big, you
will add latency.
It's a tradeoff.
You will store typically
those representations
into a database called
a vector database.
There's a lot of vector
database providers out there.
I think I've listed a
couple that are very common.
No, I haven't listed, but
I can share afterwards.
A vector database is
essentially storing those vector
in a very efficient manner,
allowing the fast retrieval
with a certain distance metric.
So what you do is you
also embed, usually
with the same algorithm,
the user prompts.
And you run a retrieval
process, which is essentially
saying, based on the
embedding from the user
query and the vector database,
find the relevant documents
based on the distance
between those embeddings.
Once you've found the relevant
documents, you pull them,
and then you add them to the
user query with a system prompt
or a prompt template on top.
So the prompt template
can be answer user query
based on list of documents.
If answer not in the
documents, say I don't know.
That's your prompt templates
where the user query is pasted,
the documents are
pasted, and then
your output should be what
you want because it's not
grounded in the documents.
You can also add to
this prompt template.
Tell me the exact
page, chapter, line
of the document that was
relevant, and in fact,
link it as well, just
to be more precise.
Any question on RAGs?
This is a simple, vanilla RAG.
Yes.
Do document embeddings still
retain information [INAUDIBLE]
Question is do the
document embeddings still
retain the information of the
location of the information
within that document,
especially in big documents?
Great question.
We'll get to it in a second.
Because you're right
that the vanilla RAG
might not do a good job
with very large documents.
So let's say, when you
open a medication box
and you have this gigantic white
paper with all the information,
and it's very long, maybe a
vanilla RAG would not cut it.
So what people have
figured out is a bunch
of techniques to improve RAGs.
And in fact, chunking is a great
technique that is very popular.
So you might actually store
in the vector database
the embedding of
the full document.
And on top of
that, you will also
store a chapter level vector.
And when you retrieve, you
will retrieve the document.
You retrieve the chapter.
And that allows you to be more
precise with the sourcing.
It's one example.
Another technique
that's popular is HyDE.
Hypothetical
document embeddings,
where a group of researchers
published a paper
showing that when you
get your user query,
one of the main problem
is the user query
actually does not look
like your documents.
For example, the
user query might
be what are the side effects
of drug X, when actually,
in the document in
the vector database,
the vectors represents
very long documents.
So how do you guarantee
that the vector
embedding is going to be close
to the document embedding?
What they do is they use
the user query to generate
a fake hallucinated document.
They embed that
document, and then they
compare it to the vector
in the vector database.
That makes sense?
So for example,
the user says what
is the side effect of drug X?
There's a prompt that this is
given to another prompt that
says, based on this user query,
generates a five-page report
answering the user query.
It generates potentially
a completely fake answer.
You embed that, and it will
be closer to the document
that you're looking for likely.
It's one example
of a RAG approach.
Again, the purpose
of this lecture
is not to go through all
these three and explain
you every single method that
has been discovered for RAGs.
But I just wanted to show
you how much research
has been done between
2020 and 2025 in RAGs
and how many branches
of research you now have
that you can learn from.
The survey paper is LinkedIn
the slides, by the way,
and I'll share them
after the lecture.
Super.
So we've made some progress.
Hopefully now, you
feel if you were
to start an LLM application, you
know how to do better prompts.
You know how to do chains.
You know how to do fine tuning.
You also how to do retrieval.
And you have the
baggage of techniques
that you can go and read
and find the code base,
pull the code, vibe code it.
But you have the breadth now.
The next set of topics
we're going to see
is around the question
of how could we
extend the capabilities of LLMs
from performing single tasks,
and hence, with
external knowledge,
to handling multi-step,
autonomous workflows?
And this is where we get
into proper agentic AI.
So let's talk about
agentic AI workflows
towards autonomous and
specialized systems.
Then we'll talk about evals.
Then we'll see
multi-agent systems.
And we'll end with a little
thoughts on what's next in AI.
So Andrew Ng actually coined
the term agentic AI workflows.
And his reason was that a lot
of companies use, say agents.
Agents, agents everywhere,
agents everywhere.
If you go and work
at these companies,
you would notice that they mean
very different things by agents.
Some people actually
have a prompt,
and they call it an agent.
Other people, they have a very
complex multi-agent system,
they call it an agent.
And so calling everything an
agent doesn't do it justice.
So Andrew says let's call
it agentic workflows.
Because in practice, it's a
bunch of prompts with tools,
with additional
resources, API calls
that ultimately are
put in a workflow,
and you can call that
workflow agentic.
So it's all about the multi-step
process to complete a task.
Also, calling it
agentic workflow
allows us to not
mix it up with what
I called agent, in
the last lecture,
with reinforcement learning.
Because in RL, agent has a
very specific definition,
interacts with an environment,
passes from one state
to the other, has a
reward and an observation.
You remember that chart, right?
So here's an example of
how we move from a one step
prompt to a multi-step
agentic workflow.
Let's say a user
queries a product.
What is your refund
policy on a chatbot?
And the response,
using a RAG, says
refunds are available
within 30 days of purchase,
and maybe the RAG can even look
link to the policy documents.
That's what we learned so far.
Instead, an agentic workflow
can function like this.
The user says, can I get
a refund for my order?
And the response via
the agentic workflow
is the agent retrieves the
refund policy using a RAG.
The agent then follows up
with the users and says,
can you provide
your order number?
Then the agent queries an API
to check the order details.
And finally, it comes
back to the user
and confirms your order
qualifies for a refund.
The amount will be processed
in three to five business days.
This is much more thoughtful
than the first version,
which is sort of vanilla.
So that's what
we're going to talk
about in the next
couple of slides,
is how do we get from the
first one to the second one?
There are plenty of specialized
agency workflows online.
You've heard, and if
you hang out in SF,
you probably see a bunch
of billboards, AI software
engineer, AI skills
mentor you've
interacted with in the
class through Workera.
AI SDR, AI lawyers, AI
specialized cloud engineer.
It would be a stretch to
say that everything works,
but there's work being
done towards that.
I'm not personally
a fan of putting
a face behind those things.
I think it's gimmicky.
And I think in a few
years from now, actually,
very few products will have
a human face behind it,
but it might be a marketing
tactic from some startups.
It's more scary than it
is engaging, frankly.
OK.
I want to talk about
the paradigm shift.
That's especially useful.
Let's say you're a
software engineer
or you're planning to
be a software engineer.
Because software
engineering as a discipline
is sort of shifting.
Or at least the
best engineers I've
worked with are able to move
from a deterministic mindset
to a fuzzy mindset and
balance between the two
whenever they need to
get something done.
So here's the paradigm shift
between traditional software
and agentic AI software.
The first one is the
way you handle data.
Traditional software deals
with structured data.
You have JSONs.
You have databases.
They're pasted in a
very structured manner
in a data engineering pipeline.
And then there used
to be displayed
on a certain interface.
The user might feel a form that
is then retrieved and pasted
in the database.
All of that historically
has been structured data.
Now, more and more companies are
handling free form text, images,
and all of that requires dynamic
interpretation to transform
an input into an output.
The software itself used
to be deterministic.
Now you have a lot of
software that is fuzzy.
And fuzzy software
creates so many issues.
I mean, imagine if you
let your user ask anything
on your website.
The chances that it
breaks is tremendous.
The chances that you're
attacked is tremendous.
The chances-- it's really,
really complicated.
It's more complicated than
people make it seem on Twitter.
Fuzzy engineering is truly hard.
You might get hate as a company
because one user did something
that you authorized them to
do that ended up breaking
the database and ended up--
we've seen that
with many companies
in the last couple of years.
So it takes a very specialized
engineering mindset
to do fuzzy
engineering, but also
know when you need
to be deterministic.
The other thing I'd call is
with agentic AI software,
you want to think about your
software as your manager.
So you're familiar with the
monolith or microservices
approaches in software, where
you structure your software
in different boxes that
can talk to each other,
and it allows teams to
debug one section at a time.
Now the equivalent with agentic
AI is you think as a manager.
So you think, OK, if I
was to delegate my product
to be done by a group of humans,
what would be those roles?
Would I have a graphic designer
that then puts together a chart
and then sends it to a marketing
manager that converts it
into a nice blog post, that
then gives it to the performance
marketing expert, that then
publishes the work, the blog
post, and then
optimizes and A/B tests?
Then to a data scientist
that analyzes the data
and then puts
hypotheses and validates
them or invalidates them.
That's how you would typically
think if you're building
an authentic AI software.
When actually, the equivalent
of that in traditional software
might be completely different.
It might be We have
a data engineer box
right here that handles
all our data engineering.
And then here, we
have the UI/UX stuff.
Everything UI/UX
related goes here.
And companies might structure
it in very different ways.
And here is the business logic
that we want to care about.
And there's five engineers
working on the business logic,
let's say.
OK.
Testing and debugging
is also very different.
And we'll talk about
it in the next section.
The other thing
that I feel matters
is with AI in engineering,
the cost of experimentation
is going down drastically.
And so people, I feel,
should be more comfortable
throwing away code.
It's like in traditional
software engineering,
you probably don't
throw away code a ton.
You build a code, and it's
solid, and it's bulletproof,
and then you update
it over time.
We've seen AI companies be
more comfortable throwing away
codes, which has advantages in
terms of the speed at which you
move but also
disadvantages in terms
of the quality of your
software that can break more.
So anyway, just wanted to do
an update on the paradigm shift
from deterministic
to fuzzy engineering.
Oh, and actually, I can give
you an example from Workera
that we learned probably
over the last 12
months is like if
you've used Workera,
you might have seen that the
interface has asks you sometimes
multiple choice questions.
And sometimes, it asks
you multiple select.
And sometimes, it asks you drag
and drop, ordering, matching,
whatever.
Those are examples of
deterministic item types,
meaning you answer the
question on a multiple choice.
There is one correct answer.
It's fully deterministic.
On the other hand, you sometimes
have a voice questions,
where you go to a
role play or you
have voice plus
coding questions,
where your code is being read
by the interface or whatever.
Those are fuzzy, meaning
the scoring algorithm
might actually make
mistakes, and those mistakes
might be costly.
And so companies
have to figure out
a human in the
loop system, which
you might have seen with the
appeal feature at the end.
So at the end of the assessment,
you have an appeal feature where
it allows you to say, I
want to appeal the agent
because I want to challenge
what the agent said on my answer
because I thought I was better
than what the agent thought.
And then you bring the
human in the loop that
then can fix the agent, can
tell the agent, actually,
you were too harsh on the
answer of this person.
And that's an example of
a fuzzy engineered system
that then adds a human in the
loop to make it more aligned.
And so if you're
building a company,
I would encourage you to
think about what can I
get done with determinism?
And let's get that done.
And then the fuzzy
stuff, I want to do fuzzy
because it allows
more interaction.
It allows more back
and forth, but I need
to put guardrails around it.
And how am I going to
design those guardrails?
Pretty much.
OK?
Here's another example
from enterprise workflows,
which are likely to
change due to agentic AI.
This is a paper from McKinsey,
I believe from last year,
where they looked at a financial
institution, and they said,
we observed that they often
spend one to four weeks
to create a credit risk memo.
And here's the process.
A relationship manager
gathers data from 15
and more than 15
sources on the borrower,
loan type, other factors.
Then the relationship manager
and the credit analyst
collaboratively analyze that
data from these sources.
Then the credit analyst
typically spends 20 hours
or more writing a memo
and then goes back
to the relationship manager.
They give feedback, and then
they go through this loop
again and again.
And it takes a long time
to get a credit memo out.
And then run a research study,
where they changed the process.
They said gen AI agents could
actually cut time by 20% to 60%
on credit risk memos.
And the process has changed
to the relationship manager,
directly work with the
Gen AI agent system,
provides relevant materials
that needs to produce the memo.
The agent subsidizes
the project into tasks
that are assigned to
specialist agents,
gathers and analyzes the
data from multiple sources,
drafts a memo.
Then the relationship manager
and the credit analyst
sit down together,
review the memo,
give feedback to the agent.
And within 20% to 60%
less time are done.
And so this is an example where
you're actually not changing
the human stakeholders.
You're just changing
the process and adding
Gen AI to reduce the time it
takes to get a credit memo out.
It turns out that, imagine
you're an enterprise,
and you have 100,000 employees,
and there's a lot of enterprises
with 100,000
employees out there.
You are currently
under crisis in terms
of redesigning your workflows.
It turns out that
if you actually
pull the job descriptions
from the HR system
and you interpret
them, you also pull
the business process
workflows that you
have encoded in your drive.
You actually can find
gains in multiple places.
And in the next
few years, you're
probably going to
see workflows being
more optimized to add Gen AI.
Even if that happens, the
hardest part is changing people.
What we know, this is
great in theory, but now,
let's try to fit that second
workflow for 10,000 credits,
risk analysts, and
relationship managers.
My guess is it will take years.
It will take 10, 20 years to
get to this being actually done
at scale within an organization.
Because change is so hard.
It's so hard to rewire business,
workflows, job descriptions,
incentivize people to do
different, and be different,
and train them.
And so this is what the
world is going towards,
but it's going to take
a long time I think.
OK.
Then I want to talk about
how the agent actually works
and what are the core
components of an agent.
Imagine a travel
booking agent. that's
an easy example you've
all thought about.
I still haven't been able to get
an agent to book a trip for me,
or I was scared because
it was going to book
a very expensive or long trip.
But in theory, you can
have a travel booking
agent that has prompts.
So the prompts we've
seen, we know the methods
to optimize those prompts.
That travel agent also has
a context management system,
which is essentially the memory
of what it knows about the user.
That context
management system might
include a core memory or working
memory and an archival memory,
OK?
What the difference
is within memory
is not every memory needs
to be fast to access.
Think about it.
You're onboarded on a product,
and the first question is hi,
what's your name?
And I say, my name is Keon.
That's probably going to
sit in the working memory
because the agents, every
time he's going to talk to me,
he's going to want
to use my name.
But then maybe the
second question
is what's your birthday?
And I give it my birthday.
Does it need my
birthday every day?
Probably not.
So it's probably going to
park it on the long term
memory or the archival memory.
And those memories
are slower to access.
They're farther down the stack.
And that structure
allows the agent
to determine what's
the working memory,
and what's the long term memory?
And that makes it easier for the
agent to retrieve super fast.
Because think about it.
When you interact
with ChatGPT, you
feel that it's very
personal at times.
You feel like it
understands you.
Imagine every time you call it,
it has to read the memories.
And that can be costly.
It's a very burdensome
cost because it happens
every time you talk to it.
So you want to be highly
optimized with the working
memory.
If it takes three
seconds to look
in the memory, every time you're
going to talk to your LLM,
it's going to take three
seconds, which you don't want.
Anyway.
And then you have the tools.
The tools can include
APIs like a flight search
API, hotel booking API, car
rental API, weather API,
and then the payment
processing API.
And typically, you would
want to tell your agent
how that API works.
It turns out that agents
or LLMs, I should say,
are very good at reading
API documentation.
So you give it the
API documentation,
and it reads the
JSON, and it reads,
what does a GET
request look like.
And this is the format
that I need to push.
And then it pushes it in
that format, let's say.
And then it retrieves something.
Does that make sense,
those different components?
Anthropic also talks
about resources.
Resources is data that is
sitting somewhere that you
might let your agent read.
For example, if you're building
your startups, you have a CRM.
A CRM has data in it, and you
want to do lookups in that data.
You will probably
give a lookup tool,
and you will give
access to the resource,
and it will do lookups
whenever you want super fast.
This type of
architecture can be built
with different
degrees of autonomy,
from the least autonomous
to the most autonomous.
And I'll give you
a few examples.
Less autonomous would be
you've hard coded the steps.
So let's say I tell the travel
agent first identify the intent.
Then look up in the
database the history
of this customer with us
and their preferences.
Then go to the flight
API, blah, blah, blah.
Then go to the--
I would hard code the steps.
OK.
That's the least autonomous.
The semi-autonomous is I
might hard code the tools,
but we're not going to
hard code the steps.
So I'm going to tell the agent,
you act like a travel agent.
And your task is to help
the person book a travel.
And these are the tools that
you have accessible to yourself.
And so I'm not hard
coding the steps.
I'm just hard coding the
tools that you have access
to for yourself.
The more autonomous is the
agent decides the steps
and can create the tools.
So that's where you might
give actually access
to a code editor, to the agent.
And the agent might actually be
able to ping any API in the web,
perform some web search.
It might even be able
to create some code
to display data to the user.
It might even be able to
perform some calculations.
Like oh, I'm going to
calculate the fastest route
to get from San
Francisco to New York,
and which one might be
the most appropriate
for what the user
is looking for.
And then I want to calculate
the distance between the airport
and that hotel
versus that hotel.
And I'm going to
write code to do that.
So it's actually
fully autonomous
from that perspective.
So yeah.
Remember those keywords.
Memory, prompts,
tools, et cetera.
Now, I presented the
flight API, but it does not
have to be an API.
You probably have heard the term
MCP or model context protocol
that was coined by Anthropic.
I pasted the seminal article on
MCP at the bottom of this slide.
But let me explain in a nutshell
why those things would differ.
In the API case,
you would actually
teach your LLM to ping an API.
So you would say this is
how you ping this API,
and this is the data that
it will send you back.
And you would have to do
that in a one off manner.
So you would have
to build or give
the API documentation
of your flight API.
You're booking hotel
API, your car rental API.
And then you would give
tools for your model
to communicate with those APIs.
It doesn't scale
very well versus MCP.
MCP, it's really about putting
a system in the middle that
would make it simpler for
your LLM to communicate
with that endpoint.
So for instance, you might have
an MCP server, an MC client,
where you're trying
to communicate
with that travel database
or the flight API or MCP.
And your agent might actually
just communicate with it
and say, hey, what do you need
in order to give me more flight
information?
And that agent will respond
by I would like you to tell me
where is the origin flight,
where is the destination
and what you're looking
for at a high level.
This is my requirement.
OK.
Let me get back to you
with in my requirement.
Oh.
You forgot to tell me
your budget, whatever.
Oh.
Let me give you my
budget, et cetera.
And it's agent to
agent communication,
which allows more scalability.
You don't need to
hard code everything.
Companies have displayed
their MCPs out there,
and your agent can
communicate with them
and figure out how to
get the data it needs.
Does that make sense?
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE] rewriting
any [INAUDIBLE]
I think it is, ultimately.
The question is, isn't
it a shifting issue?
Because anyway, if an
API has to be updated,
the MCP has to be updated,
is what you say, right?
Yes, that's correct.
But at least it allows the
agent to go back and forth
and figure out what
the requirements are.
But at the end of the day,
ideally, if you're a startup,
you have some documentation.
And automatically, you have
an agent or an LLM workflow
that reads that documentation
and updates the code
accordingly.
But I agree.
It's not something that
is fully autonomous.
Yeah.
i I've seen some
security issues.
Why is that possible.
Which security specifically?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
So are there security
issues with MCPs?
So think about it this way.
MCPs, depending on the data
that you get access to,
might have different
requirements, lower stake
or higher stake.
I'm not an expert
at the full range.
But it wouldn't surprise me
that when you expose an MCP to--
I think you would a lot of
MCC have authentication.
So you might
actually need a code
to actually talk to it, just
like you would with an API,
or a key.
Yeah, but that's
a good question.
I'm not an expert at the
security of these systems,
but we can look into it.
Any other questions
on what we've
seen with the agentic workflows,
APIs, tools, MCPs, memory?
All of that is under progress.
So even memory is not a
solved problem by any means.
It's pretty hard actually.
Yes.
You don't need an
[INAUDIBLE] The MCP just
makes it easier to access
the API, but technically,
[INAUDIBLE]
Exactly, exactly.
Is MCP about efficiency
or accessing more data?
It's about efficiency.
Let's say you have a coding
agent, and it has an MCP client,
and there's multiple MCP servers
that are exposed out there.
That agent can communicate
very efficiently with them
and find what it needs.
And it's a more
efficient process
than actually displaying APIs
and the APIs on that side
and how to ping them and
what the protocol is.
But it's not about
the data that is
being exposed because
ultimately, you control
the data that is being exposed.
You probably, depending
on how the MCP is built,
my guess is you probably
expose yourself to other risks
because your MCP server can
see any input pretty much
from another LLM.
And so it has to be robust.
But yeah.
Super.
So let's look at an
example of a step
by step workflow for
the travel agent.
So let's say the user says, I
want to plan a trip to Paris
from December 15 to
20th with flights,
hotels near the Eiffel Tower,
and then an itinerary of must
visit places.
That's the task to
the travel agent.
Step two, the agent
plans the steps.
So it says, I'm going
to find flights.
Use the flight search API to
get options for December 15.
Search hotels, generate
recommendations for places
to visit, validate
preferences, budget, et cetera.
Book the trip with the
payment processing API.
That's just the
planning, by the way.
Step three, execute the
plan, use your tools,
combine the results,
and then proactive
user interaction and booking.
It might make a first
proposal to the user
and ask the user to
validate or invalidate
and then may repeat that
planning and execution process.
And then finally, it might
actually update the memory.
It might say, oh, I just
learned through this interaction
that the user only
likes direct flights.
Next time, I'll only
give direct flights.
Or I noticed users are fine with
three star hotels or four star
hotels.
And in fact, they don't want
to go above budget or something
like that.
So that hopefully makes sense
by now on how you might do that.
My question for you is how
would you know if this works.
And if you had such a system
running in production, how
would you improve it?
Yeah.
Lets users rate
their experience.
So that's an example.
So let users rate their
experience at the end.
That would be an end
to end test, right?
You're looking at the user
experience through the steps
and say how good was it
from 1 to 5, let's say.
Yeah.
It's a good way.
And then if you learn
that a user says 1,
how do you improve the workflow?
[INAUDIBLE]
OK.
So you would go down a tree
and say, OK, you said 1.
What was your issue?
And then the user says the
prices were too high, let's say.
And then you would go back and
fix that specific tool or prompt
or, yeah, OK.
Any other ideas?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, good.
So that's a good insight.
Separate the LLM related stuff
from the non-LLM related stuff,
the deterministic stuff.
The deterministic
stuff, you might
be able to fix it more
objectively essentially.
Yeah.
What else?
So give me an example
of an objective issue
that you can notice and
how you would fix it
versus a subjective issue.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
So let's say you say
there's the same flight,
but one is cheaper than
the other, let's say.
It's objectively worse.
And so you can capture
that almost automatically.
Yeah.
So you could
actually build evals
that are objective, that are
tracked across your users.
And you might actually
run an analysis after
and see that for
the objective stuff,
we notice that our LLM AI agent
workflow is bad with pricing.
It just doesn't read price
as well because it always
gives a more expensive option.
Yeah.
You're perfectly right.
How about the subjective stuff?
Do you choose a direct
or indirect flight
if the indirect is a
little bit cheaper?
Yeah.
Good one.
Do you choose a direct
flight or an indirect flight
if the indirect is cheaper but
the direct is more comfortable?
Yeah.
That's a good one actually.
So how would you capture
that information.
Let's say this is used
by thousands of users.
Could you feed
something in [INAUDIBLE]
Could you feed something in?
Yeah, I mean, you could--
could feed something in
about the user preferences?
Well, you could
build a data set that
has some of that information.
So you build 10 prompts, where
the user is asking specifically
for a direct--
saying that I prefer
direct flights because I
care about my time, let's say.
And then you look at the
output and you actually
give a good example
of a good output,
and you probably
are able to capture
the performance of your agentic
workflow on this specific eval.
Does it prioritize?
Does it understand
price conscious--
is it price conscious,
essentially,
and comfort conscious?
Yeah.
What about the tone?
Let's say the LLM right
now is not very friendly.
How would you notice that,
and how would you fix it?
Yeah.
Have the test user
run the prompt
and see if there's
something wrong with that.
OK.
Have a test user run the
prompt and see if there's
something wrong with that.
Tell me about the last step.
How would you notice
that something is wrong?
So a couple of tests
[INAUDIBLE] evaluates
the response and [INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
I agree with your approach.
Have LLM judges that
evaluate the response
against a certain rubric of
what politeness looks like.
So here in this case,
you could actually
start with error analysis.
So you start, you
have 1,000 users.
And you can pull up
20 user interactions
and read through it.
And you might notice,
at first sight,
the LLM seems to be very rude.
It's just super, super
short in its answers,
and it's not very helpful.
You notice that with your
error analysis manually.
Then you go to the next stage.
You actually put
evals behind it.
You say, I'm going to
create a set of LLM judges
that are going to look
at the user interaction
and are going to rate
how polite it is.
And I'm going to
give it a rubric.
Then what I'm going to do
is I'm going to flip my LLM.
Instead of using GPT-4,
I'm going to use Grok.
And instead of using
Grok, I'm using Llama.
And then I'm going to run
those three LLMs side by side,
give it to my LLM judges, and
then get my subjective score
at the end to say, oh, x model
was more polite on average.
Yeah.
Perfectly right.
That's an example of an
eval that is very specific
and allows you to
choose between LLMs.
You could actually do the
same eval not across LLMs,
but fixed the LLM,
change the prompt.
You actually, instead of
saying act like a travel agent,
you say act like a
helpful travel agent.
And then you see the influence
of that word on your eval
with the LLM as judges.
Does that make sense?
OK.
Super.
So let's move forward and
do a case study with evals.
And then we're almost
done for today.
Let's say your product manager
asks you to build an AI
agent for customer support, OK?
Where do you start?
And here is an example
of the user prompt.
I need to change my shipping
address for order, blah, blah,
blah.
I move to a new address.
So what do you start if I'm
giving you that project?
Yes.
We search online for existing
models and [INAUDIBLE]
So do some research.
See benchmarks and
how different models
perform at customer support.
And then pick a model.
That's what you mean.
Yeah.
It's true you could do that.
What else could you do?
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
OK.
Yeah, I like that.
Try to decompose the different
tasks that it will need
and try to guess which ones will
be more of a struggle, which
ones should be fuzzy, which
ones should be deterministic.
Yeah, you're right.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
Similar to what you said.
That's what I would
recommend as well.
You say I would sit down
with a customer support
agent for a day or two, and
I would decompose the tasks
that are going through.
I will ask them, where
do they struggle?
How much time it takes?
Yes.
That's usually where you want to
start with task decomposition.
So let's say we've done that
work, and we have this list.
I'm simplifying.
But the customer support
agent, human, typically
would extract key
info, then look up
in the database to retrieve
the customer record.
Then check the policy.
Are we allowed to
update the address,
or is it a fixed data point?
And then draft a response
email and sends the email.
So we've decomposed that task.
Once you've
decomposed that task,
how do you design
your agentic workflow?
Yes.
[INAUDIBLE]
Exactly.
So to repeat,
you're going to look
at the decomposition of tasks,
get an instinct of what's fuzzy,
what's deterministic,
and then determine
which line is going to be an LLM
one shot, which one will require
maybe a RAG, which one will
require a tool, which one will
require memory, which one--
So you will start
designing that map.
Completely right.
That's also what
I would recommend.
You might actually draft it and
say, OK, I take the user prompt.
And the first step of
my task decomposition
was extract information that
seems to be a vanilla LLM.
You can guess that the
vanilla LLM would probably
be good enough at
extracting the user wants
to change their address,
and this is the order number
and this is the new address.
You probably don't need
too much technology
there other than the LLM.
The next step, it feels like
you need a tool because you're
actually going to have to
look up in the database
and also update the address.
So that might be a
tool, and you might
have to build a custom
tool for the LLM
to say, let me connect
you to that database
or let me give you access to
that resource with an MCP.
After that probably need an
LLM again to draft the email,
but you would probably
paste confirmation.
You would paste the
confirmation that your address
has been updated from x to y.
And then the LLM
will draft an answer.
And of course,
just to not forget,
you might need a tool
to send the email.
You might actually need
to post something to
for the email to go out.
And then you'll get the output.
Does that make sense So
exactly what you described.
Now moving to the next step.
Once we have-- we
compose our tasks.
Then we have designed an
agentic workflow around it.
It took us five minutes.
In practice, it
would take you more
if you're building
your startup on that.
You want to make sure your
task decomposition is accurate,
your thing is accurate
here, and then
you can have a lot of
work done on every tool
and optimize it and
latency and cost.
But let's say, now we
want to know if it works.
And I'm going to assume
that you have LLM traces.
LLM traces are very important.
Actually, if you're
interviewing with an AI startup.
I would recommend you in the
interview process to ask them,
do you have LLM traces?
Because if they don't
have LLM traces,
it is pretty hard to debug an
LLM system because you don't
have visibility on the chain of
complex prompts that were called
and where the bug is.
And so it's a basic
part of an AI startup
stack to have an LLM traces.
So let's assume you have traces.
How would you know
if your system works?
I'm going to summarize some
of the things I heard earlier.
You gave us an example
of an end to end metric.
You look at the user
satisfaction at the end.
You can also do a
component-based approach
where you actually will look at
the tool, the database updates,
and you will manually do
an error analysis and see,
oh, the tool actually always
forgets to update the email.
It just fails at writing.
And I'm going to fix that.
This is deterministic
pretty much.
Or when it tries
to send the email
and ping the system that is
supposed to send the email,
it doesn't send it
in the right format.
And so it bugs at that point.
Again, you could fix that.
Draft of the email.
The LLM doesn't do a great job.
It's not very polite
at drafting the email.
So you could look at
component by component,
and it's actually easier
to debug than to look at it
end to end.
You would probably
do a mix of both.
Another way to look at
it is what is objective
versus what is subjective?
So for example, an
objective example
would be a DLRM extracted
the wrong order ID.
The user said my order
ID is X, and the LLM,
when it actually looked
up in the database,
it used the wrong order ID.
This is objectively wrong.
You can actually
write a Python code
that checks that, checks just
the alignment between what
the user mentioned and what was
actually pasted in the database
or for the lookup.
You also have subjective
stuff, which we talked about,
where you probably want to
do either human rating or LLM
as judges.
It's very relevant
for subjective evals.
And finally, you
will find yourself
having quantitative evals
and more qualitative evals.
So quantitative would be
percentage of successful address
updates.
The latency.
You could actually track
the latency component-based
and see which one
is the slowest.
Let's say sending the
email is five seconds.
It's too long, let's say.
You would notice component
based or the full workflow.
And then you will decide, where
am I optimizing my latency,
and how am I going to do that?
And then finally, qualitative.
You might actually do
some error analysis
and look at where are
the hallucinations?
Where are the tone mismatches?
Are the user confused, and
by what they're confused?
That would be more qualitative.
And typically, it would take
more white glove approaches
to do that.
So here's what it
could look like.
I gave you some examples.
But you would build
evals to determine
objectively, subjectively,
component-based, end
to end based, and then
quantitatively and
qualitatively, where's
your LLM failing
and where it's doing well.
Does that give you a
sense of the type of stuff
you could do to fix or
improve that agentic workflow?
Super.
Well, that was our
case study on evals.
We're not going to
delve deeper into it.
But hopefully, it gave you
a sense of the type of stuff
you can do with LLM
judges, with objective,
subjective, component-based,
end to end, et cetera.
Last section on
multi-agent workflows.
So you might ask, hey, why do we
need multi-agent workflow when
the workflow already
has multiple steps,
already calls the LLM multiple
times, already gives them tools.
Why do we need multiple agents?
And so many people are talking
about multi-agent system online.
It's not even a
new thing, frankly.
Multi-agent systems have
been around for a long time.
The main advantage of
a multi-agent system
is going to be parallelism.
It's like is there
something that I
wish I would run in parallel,
sort of independently,
but maybe there are some
things in the middle?
But that's where you want
to put a multi-agent system.
It's when it's parallel.
The other advantage
that some companies
have with multi-agent systems
is an agent can be reused.
So let's say in a company,
you have an agent that's
been built for design.
That agent can be used
in the marketing team,
and it can be used
in the product team.
And so now you're
optimizing an agent,
which has multiple stakeholders
that can communicate with it
and benefit from
its performance.
Actually I'm going
to ask you a question
and take a few, maybe a
minute to think about it.
Let's say you were
building smart home
automation for your
apartment or your home.
What agents would
you want to build?
Yeah.
Write it down.
And then I'm going to
ask you in a minute
to share some of the
agents that you will build.
Also, think about
how you would put
a hierarchy between
these agents,
or how you would
organize them, or who
should communicate with who.
OK?
OK.
Take a minute for that.
Be creative also because I'm
going to ask all of your agents,
and maybe you have an agent
that nobody has thought of.
OK.
Let's get started.
Who wants to give
me a set of agents
that you would want for
your home, smart home.
Yes.
The first is like a set
of agents [INAUDIBLE]
OK.
So let me repeat.
You have four agents,
I think, roughly.
One that tracks biometric,
like where are you in the home?
Where are you moving?
How you're moving,
things like that.
That sort of knows
your location.
The second one determines
the temperature of the rooms
and has the ability
to change it.
The third one tracks
energy efficiency
and might give feedback on
energy and energy usage.
And might be, I
don't know, maybe
it has the control over
the temperature as well.
I don't know actually.
Or the gas or the water, might
cut your water at some point.
And then you have an
orchestrator agent.
What is exactly the
orchestrator doing?
It passes instructions
[INAUDIBLE]
OK.
Passes instructions.
So is that the agent
that communicates mainly
with the user?
So if I'm coming
back home and I'm
saying I want the
oven to be preheated,
I communicate with
the orchestrator,
and then it would
funnel to another agent.
OK.
Sounds good.
Yeah.
So that's an example
of, I want to say,
a hierarchical agentic
multi-agent system.
What else?
Any other ideas?
What would you add to that?
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
Oh, I like that.
That's a really good one.
So let me summarize.
You have a security agent that
determines if you can enter
or not.
And when you enter, it
understands who you are.
And then it gives
you certain sets
of permissions that might
be different depending
of if you're a parent or a kid.
Or you might have access to
certain cars and not others.
Or your kid cannot open the
fridge, or I don't know.
Something like that.
Yeah.
OK, I like that.
That's a good one.
And it does feel like it's a
complex enough workflow where
you want a specific
workflow tied to that.
I agree.
What else?
Yes.
[INAUDIBLE] So you can
get more complicated.
So high energy savings
with whether or not you
or someone else can be blind
to those in the house or also
when you tap into the grid.
Yeah So another thought I
have as well is much harder
to track in the grocery store.
But understanding
what's in your fridge.
OK
Well, that's really
good actually.
So you mentioned two of them.
One is maybe an agent that has
access to external APIs that
can understand the weather
out there, the wind, the sun,
and then has control over
certain devices at home.
Temperature, blinds, things
like that, and also understands
your preferences for it.
That does feel like it's a good
use case because you could give
that to the orchestrator,
but it might lose itself
because it's doing too much.
And also, these problems
are tied together,
like temperature outdoor
with the weather API
might influence the
temperature inside,
how you want it, et cetera.
And then the second
one, which I also like,
is you might have an agent
that looks at your fridge
and what's inside.
And it might
actually have access
to the camera in the
fridge, for example,
and know your
preferences and also has
access to the
e-commerce API to order
Amazon groceries ahead of time.
I agree.
And maybe the orchestrator
will be the communication line
with the user, but it might
communicate with that agent
in order to get it done.
Yeah.
I like those.
So those are all
really good examples.
Here is the list I had up there.
So climate control, lighting
security, energy management,
entertainment,
notification agent,
alerts about the system updates,
energy saving, and orchestrator.
So all of them you
mentioned actually.
And then we didn't talk about
the different interaction
patterns, but you do have
different ways to organize
a multi-agent system.
Flat, hierarchical.
It sounds like this
would be hierarchical.
I agree.
And the reason is
UI/UX, is I would rather
have to only talk
to the orchestrator,
rather than have to go to
a specialized application
to do something.
Like it feels like
the orchestrator
could be responsible for that.
And so I agree, I would probably
go for a hierarchical setup
here.
But maybe you might also
add some connections
between other agents,
like in the flat system
where it's all to all.
For example, with climate
control and energy,
if you want to
connect those two,
you might actually allow them
to speak with each other.
When you allow agents to
speak with each other,
it is basically an MCB
protocol, by the way.
So you treat the agent like
a tool, exactly like a tool.
Here is how you interact
with this agent.
Here is what it can tell you.
Here is what it needs
from you, essentially.
OK super.
And then without going
into the details,
there are advantages to
multi-agent workflows
versus single agents,
such as debugging.
It's easier to debug
a specialized agent
into debug an entire system.
Parallelization as well.
It's easier to have
things run in parallel,
and you can earn time.
There are some
advantages to doing that,
and I'll leave you with this
slide if you want to go deeper.
Super.
So we've learned so many
techniques to optimize LLMs,
from prompts to chains to
fine tuning, retrieval,
and to multi-agent
system as well.
And then just to end on a couple
of trends I want you to watch.
I think next week is
Thanksgiving, is that it?
It's Thanksgiving break.
No, the week after.
OK.
Well ahead of the
Thanksgiving break.
So if you're traveling, you
can think about these things.
What's next is in AI, I wanted
to call out a couple of trends.
So Ilya Sutskever, one of
the OGs of LLMs and OpenAI
co-founder, raised that question
about are we plateauing or not.
The question are we going to
see in the coming years LLM sort
of not improve as fast as
we've seen in the past?
It's been the feeling
in the community
probably that the
last version of GPT
did not bring the
level of performance
that people were expecting,
although it did make
it so much easier to use for
consumers because you don't need
to interact with
different models.
It's all under the same hood.
So it seems that
it's progressing,
but the plateau is unclear.
The way I would think about it
is the LLM scaling laws tell us
that if we continue to
improve compute and energy,
then LLMs should
continue to improve.
But at some point,
it's going to plateau.
So what's going to take
us to the next step?
It's probably
architecture search.
Still a lot of LLMs,
even if we don't
understand what's under
the hood or probably
transformer-based today.
But we know that the human brain
does not operate the same way.
There's just certain
things that we
do that are much more
efficient, much faster.
We don't need as much data.
So theoretically,
we have so much
to learn in terms of
architecture search
that we haven't figured out.
It's not a surprise that
you see those labs hire
so many engineers.
Because it is possible
that in the next few years,
you're going to have
thousands of engineers trying
to figure out the different
engineering hacks and tactics
and architectural
searches that are
going to lead to better models.
And one of them suddenly will
find the next transformer,
and it will reduce by 10x the
need for compute and the need
for energy.
It's sort of if you read Isaac
Asimov's Foundation series.
Individuals can have an amazing
impact on the future because
of their decisions.
Whoever discovered transformers
had a tremendous impact
on the direction of AI.
I think we're going to see
more of that in the coming
years, where some group of
researchers that is iterating
fast might discover certain
things that would suddenly
unlock that plateau and
take us to the next step,
and it's going to continue
to improve like that.
And so it doesn't surprise me
that there's so many companies
hiring engineers right
now to figure out
those hacks and
those techniques.
The other set of gains
that we might see
is from multi-modality.
So the way to think about it is
we've had LLMs first text-based,
and then we've added imaging.
And today, models are
very good at images.
They're very good at text.
It turns out that being good at
images and being good at text
makes the whole model better.
So the fact that you're good
at understanding a cat image
makes you better at
text as well for a cat.
Now you add another modality
like audio or video.
The whole system gets better.
So you're better at
writing about a cat
if you know what
a cat sounds like,
if you can look at a
cat on an image as well.
Does that make sense?
So we see gains that are
translated from one modality
to another, and that might lead
in the pinnacle of robotics
where all these
modalities come together.
And suddenly, the
robot is better at
running away from a cat
because it understands
what a cat is, how
it sounds like,
what it looks like, et cetera.
That makes sense?
The other one is the multiple
methods working in harmony.
In the Tuesday lectures, we've
seen supervised learning,
unsupervised learning,
self-supervised learning,
reinforcement learning, prompt
engineering, RAGs, et cetera.
If you look at how
babies learn, it
is probably a mix of those
different approaches.
Like a baby might have some
meta learning, meaning it
has some survival
instinct that is
encoded in the DNA most likely.
And that's like the baby's
pre-training, if you will.
On top of that, the mom or
the dad is pointing at stuff
and saying bad, good, bad, good.
Supervised learning.
On top of that, the baby
is falling on the ground
and getting hurt.
And that's a reward signal
for reinforcement learning.
On top of that, the baby
is observing other people
doing stuff or
other babies doing
stuff, unsupervised learning.
You see what I mean?
We're probably a mix
of all these methods,
and I think that's where
the trend is going, is
where those methods that
you've seen in CS230
come together in order to build
an AI system that learns fast,
is low latency, is
cheap, energy-efficient,
and makes the most out
of all of these methods.
Finally, and this is
especially true at Stanford,
you have research going on that
you would consider human-centric
and some research that
is non-human centric.
By human-centric, I should
say human approaches
that are modeled after the
brain and approaches that
are not modeled after humans.
Because it turns out that the
human body is very limiting.
And so if you actually
only do research
on what the human
brain looks like,
you're probably missing out on
compute and energy and stuff
like that that you
can optimize even
beyond neuronal
connections in the brain,
but you still can learn a
lot from the human brain.
And that's why there are
professors that are running labs
right now that
try to understand,
how does back propagation
work for humans?
And in fact, it's probably that
we don't have back propagation.
We don't use back propagation,
we only do forward propagation,
let's say.
So this type of stuff
is interesting research
that I would encourage you
to read if you're curious
about the direction of AI.
And then finally, one thing
that's going to be pretty clear,
I call it all the time,
but it's the velocity
at which things are moving.
You're noticing,
part of the reason
we're giving you
a breadth in CS230
is because these methods
are changing so fast.
So I don't want to bother
going and teaching you
the number 17
methods on RAG that
optimizes the RAG
because in two years,
you're not going to need it.
So I would rather
you think about what
is the breadth of things
you want to understand.
And when you need it, you
are sprinting and learning
the exact thing you need faster
because the half life of skill
is so low.
You want to come out of the
class with a good breadth
and then have the ability
to go deep whenever
you need after the class.
And so that's sort of how that
class is designed as well.
Yeah.
That's it for today.
So thank you.
Thank you for participating.