So what I'd like to do
today is chat with you
about the full cycle of
a deep learning project.
And as I promised in
the first lecture,
rather than me talking at you
for an hour and 20 minutes
or whatever, we'd love for this
to be much more interactive.
And so what I'm going to do is
illustrate this with an example,
but also ask you a
bunch of questions
along the way about what
you would do if you are
the one working on the project.
I'm going to use as an
illustrative example.
So plan for this to
be quite interactive
and please interrupt any
time and ask questions.
Since I think that's why I
want to do this in person
here at Stanford.
So one of the reasons
why developing machine
learning or deep
learning or other types
of AI projects, including AI
projects using large language
models or agentic AI workflows
or whatever is that AI projects
are different than traditional
software engineering projects.
So one of the biggest
differences between AI projects
of the many different flavors--
supervised learning,
OM based, generative
AI based is that in
traditional software projects,
you write code, and
you control your code.
Write whatever code you want.
Compile it.
Your code does what
you tell it to.
But AI projects involve
both code as well as data
that you train
your algorithm on.
And you almost never know what
strange and wonderful things
there are in your data.
For example, if you're
working on a face recognition
application-- that's a running
example I'm going to use today--
then as you're just getting
started on the project,
it's really difficult
to in advance
what you find in the data.
Is the lighting
of the face good?
Do you struggle with people
with very long hair or people
with short hair?
Do people making weird
facial expressions
make your system struggle?
Do people wearing glasses
make your systems struggle?
So data is so rich
that a lot of time,
you can't predict in
advance what your AI
system is going to
do, not because you
don't control the code.
You can write whatever
neural network
or whatever code you want.
But you don't
what's in the data.
And this is why, unlike
traditional software
engineering, machine
learning development
is a much more iterative
process where you just
have to build something,
see how it works, and then
through a process,
discover, almost discover
what is in the
data, and therefore
what you should be doing
to change your code to make
your overall system perform.
And this is also true
not just for-- this
is true not just for deep
learning based systems.
This is also true for modern
large language models.
There's been a lot of hype buzz
about how LLMs, Large Language
Models, are hard to control.
I think there's a lot of
excessive hype about that kind
of fear mongering.
There's a little bit of that.
But one of the
reasons why none of us
know in advance what
LLMs do is because it
was trained on a lot
of data, more data
than any human could
possibly look at.
And we just don't
know with precision
what is in all that data
that the arm was trained on.
And so because we
know the data, we
can't really look at
all the massive tens
of trillions of tokens
of data was trained on.
It's hard to know exactly
how large language model will
perform, which is why building
agentic AI applications
or building large language
models based applications
is also very empirical
or very experimental.
Meaning you just have
to build something,
then see where it goes well,
see where it goes poorly,
and then use that
to fix problems.
And that's how you
drive progress.
That makes sense?
So, because you control your
code, but you don't really know.
It's hard to control the data.
And this is true,
both for the data
you have stored
in your hard disk,
you can have terabytes of
data stored in my hard disk.
I don't really know
what's in my hard disk.
And the thing you really don't
control is what data the world
will give you in the future.
So when you deploy a
system in the world,
say, face recognition,
which we should talk about.
Will people wear a
thick, heavy scarf
that covers part of their
face when it's winter?
We just don't know.
There are all these things in
data that will surprise you.
And you don't even
control your past data
that's already a hard disk.
You certainly can't
control your future data.
So it turns out that a lot
of machine learning classes
talk about building models.
And you learn a lot
from the online videos
about how to build powerful
deep learning models.
But it turns out that building
the overall machine learning
system or a deep learning
system has a lot more work
than just training models.
But if you look a lot
of causes, there's
actually a very strong
focus on modeling
because I think that's what
academia has focused on.
We can train models,
evaluate models,
publish papers on models.
And so you find
that a lot of causes
focus on training a good
deep learning model.
And that is
absolutely important.
But because we know
how to evaluate models,
different research groups can
benchmark different models.
There's a lot of academic
research work on that.
That's reflected
a lot of causes.
But this is just a
small part of what
you need to do if you want to
build an effective deep learning
system.
And what I want
to do today is go
outside the small box
of models to give you
a broader view of what it feels
like to develop a deep learning
or AI or machine
learning system.
And this is what it often--
this is what building
a deep learning system
would be like, which is,
first, specify the problem,
figure out what we're
actually working on.
The running example
I want to use today
will be to build a face
recognition system, or face rec
system for security, for
deciding when to unlock a door.
And [INAUDIBLE] [? talked ?]
about some face recognition,
which I abbreviate
face rec architectures,
last week as well.
But specific application
I want to talk about
is something I've worked on.
Actually, I built one of the
commercial systems that--
For this, if this is a
door and this is-- well,
you or a friend or maybe someone
that you don't want to let
in, approaching, if you
have a little camera--
sorry, bad drawing--
take a picture
of whoever's
approaching the door
and decide whether or
not to unlock the door.
So face recognition
to decide who
is authorized to enter
a restricted location,
like a corporate office building
or your house or whatever.
And actually, one common use
case that one of my teams built
was a key card, swipe key cards.
So sometimes, key
cards get stolen.
And so one of the systems we
deploy fairly large office
complexes was if you
swipe a key card,
we also just take a
picture that is then soon
discarded to make sure
that the key card is
held by the person whose face
is shown on the key card.
So it makes it harder
if someone to steal
a key card to gain unauthorized
access to an office complex.
So I'm going to use this as the
motivating example for today.
And after specifying a problem,
typical process is then--
sometimes, the open
source model can download.
But let's say for today that
the open source model is not
good enough.
You want to train
your own model.
The typical process, we
get data, design the model,
train the model.
And then we will iterate
through these steps
a bunch of times until
the model looks like it's
performing well enough.
And then after that, we have
to deploy it and monitor
and maintain the model.
So I'm actually going to
talk a bunch about multiple
of these steps today because
I want you to come away
with a feel for
when you're working
on a real machine
learning application,
what the important
steps you will face on.
And so as I alluded,
machine learning development
is very iterative process.
So for these three steps, we
often drive a rapid development
loop where we--
oops, sorry-- design the model,
train it, analyze the results,
and then may be designed to
update the model or the data
or something and
iterate around this loop
many times before
you are satisfied.
And just one more detail.
It turns out that
for face recognition,
the very common
architecture, which
you learn in detail about
later in the online videos,
is a neural network
called a Siamese network.
And what that does is
a neural network that
takes as input two pictures.
And two pictures get
fed to a neural network
or a deep learning algorithm.
And it's a job of a deep
learning algorithm to tell us,
are these two pictures the same
person or different persons?
Because if you're trying
to set up this system, say,
for your house, and maybe
you have a few family members
or roommates you want to let in.
Then it'd be quite
annoying if you
have to retrain a neural
network for every single home.
So the most common way
to do face recognition
is of a neural network
that inputs two pictures.
And the job of the neural
network is to tell me,
are these two pictures
the same person?
And then the way you set
up the system is to input
a few registration pictures.
So take a picture of yourself.
Take a picture of your roommate.
Take a picture any family
members you want to have access.
So then, when someone
comes, it can quickly
check if the person
that just showed up
is one of the people
that's authorized.
And then let them in.
And then the corporate
key card swipe example
is someone swipes a
card and my card says,
this is Andrew's card.
Then I'll quickly pull up
my registration picture
to double check
if I am, if I seem
to be the same person as the
Andrew that was registered.
So this is a typical neural
network architecture.
So, I have a question for you.
One thing I'd like
to do today is
walk you through a
number of scenarios
and invite you to think
about what decision you would
make if you are the CTO
of a startup building
these technologies.
So my question for you is, if
you're the CTO of a startup,
building the next face
recognition system,
and if your lawyers
have said you
aren't allowed to download
data from the internet.
So let's not download
data for this application.
How would you go about getting
data to train this system?
So what you need is
a bunch of pictures
of people to train a
neural network to say,
are they the same person or not.
So maybe take a few
minutes to think about it,
and then I'll see if
people raise hands and give
some answers.
And one specific
question I have as well
is, how long would you take
to collect data before you
start training a model?
So I think, well,
we need to get data.
We design the model,
I guess, and then
you need to train model.
So what does the
timeline look for you?
We'll specify the problem.
We design the model.
How many hours or days or weeks
would you is spent to get data
and how before you start
running your gradient descent?
I see a hand up.
Sure, go ahead.
Are we [INAUDIBLE]
everyone around the world,
or are we specifically like Bay
Area or America [INAUDIBLE],
or it's like this
[? wide range ?] [INAUDIBLE]?
Let me leave it a
bit more open-ended.
Say you just graduated
from Stanford.
And you're CTO of a three-person
startup building this thing
that, eventually, hopefully,
you sell all around the world.
But your goals are
just get started
with the three of you working
out of Palo Alto, California.
And do it as your real
self, with the resources
that you have.
Anyone want to
venture an answer?
How would you get data to
train a neural network?
Go for it.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, cool, video
streaming service.
By video streaming
service, you're
thinking like Netflix and Hulu?
Are you thinking
security videos?
Like Zoom.
I see.
Cool.
Like a video.
People [INAUDIBLE] video.
I see.
Cool, cool, cool.
Video streaming service.
How long do you think
it'll take to do that?
A couple of months.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, cool.
Cool.
Thank you.
Creative idea.
Any other ideas?
How would you go
about getting data?
Go ahead.
[INAUDIBLE] [? work ?] with
a three-person startup.
I've had a larger company.
I would put a camera
[INAUDIBLE] the camera [? up ?]
[? also the ?] [? start ?] and
just ask the employees if they
would like to participate in
the collection and take pictures
of [INAUDIBLE].
[? So ?] the [? employees ?]
that are after them.
We might not be generalizable,
but [INAUDIBLE].
Cool, awesome.
Stick a camera there.
Let people opt in to
get their picture taken.
Cool.
I think I saw a hand up.
Go for it.
[INAUDIBLE]
Sorry.
I see.
Cool.
How would you get users?
[INAUDIBLE]
I see.
Cool.
Yeah, by your own people
mean like, grab some friends
and ask them.
They'll give you
their LinkedIn photo,
give you some pictures
from your camera roll.
Yeah, cool.
I like that.
That's fast.
Any other ideas?
Go ahead.
[INAUDIBLE]
I see.
Interesting.
Yeah, ask Stanford
to send an email.
Cool.
I love Stanford.
Stanford is a
wonderful institution.
Awesome.
That's going to take
a while, I think.
[LAUGHTER]
Creative idea.
I like the creative ideas.
So let me share with you
one guiding principle
for how I would encourage you
to approach this problem of data
collection.
I appreciate all the
creative ideas, actually.
One of the frameworks I often
use to decide how I collect data
is speed.
Because I find that--
actually, especially
in building a startup.
In my opinion, one
of the strongest
predictors for whether a
startup will succeed, and also,
whether a small, innovative
project in a large corporation--
you can be a giant corporation.
But if a team of three, work
on a small, innovative project,
a big company, I find that
one of the biggest predictors
for the chance of
success is just
the speed of execution,
the sheer speed of getting
stuff done.
And so when I'm
sitting with a team
and brainstorming
different tactics,
I will gravitate toward
the tactics that let
me get a data set very quickly.
And quickly usually
means one or two days,
even if it ends up with a
inferior, smaller, lower quality
data sets or whatever.
Because I don't really know what
problems I'll see in my data.
And the quicker I can get
the data set, create a model,
see where it goes
wrong, the quicker I
can then discover what's
wrong with my data and fix it.
True story.
Chatting with a CEO that told
me-- he actually had spent
I think it was
over $100 million.
Definitely more than
tens of million dollars.
Spent a lot of money buying
a company for its data.
And then he actually said, hey,
Andrew, I spend all this money
to get all this data.
Can you help me figure
out how to monetize this,
how to make money off of this?
And I look and goes, boy,
I wish I hadn't done that.
And what I find is
that the value of data
is just so difficult
to know in advance.
What's important and what's
not important about data?
So for a lot of these
tactics, for example,
I think student IDs
is an interesting one.
But our student ID photos
are weird in some way.
Or are they too expressionless
or people smiling too much
in student IDs.
I actually have no idea.
Actually, my Stanford ID, I look
really weird in my Stanford ID.
And I actually the idea
of seeking a camera
and just letting people come up
and opt in and take a picture
if you can do it quickly.
And I think in a big company
or even in a small startup--
it's important to respect user
privacy or individual privacy.
But if you can stick a camera
in some place that doesn't--
what's the word--
invade people's privacy
that don't want to be any part
of this, but let people opt in,
take the pictures of permission.
If you can do that in days,
I find that to be valuable.
One of the things I found--
quite a few of my projects
found that Stanford students,
our community here is pretty
cosmopolitan with people
from all around the world.
We're not fully representative
of the world's distribution
of people, but we
actually do have people
from all around the world.
A lot of Stanford people
are actually very nice.
So one thing I've
done multiple times is
when I need to collect data,
we'll go to places on campus
with high foot traffic.
Turns out cafeterias have
very high foot traffic.
And we just ask people,
hey, work on the project.
Can I get a sample
of your voice?
Can I take a picture of you?
And with the informed
consent, tell people,
is it OK if I do this?
I've been delighted at
how collaborative Stanford
students are.
And I find that one thing I've
often done is gone to my teams
and said, we have two
days to collect data.
It's 11:52 AM now.
Let's figure out
what we can do by--
what day is it--
Tuesday.
Let's go ahead and do
by Thursday, 11:52 AM.
So that gives us a 48
hours and let's brainstorm.
How can we collect data?
And it's fine if the
data isn't all there.
Find that the data low quality.
But that velocity lets us
more quickly train the model,
figure out what's wrong with
the data, and then jigger
or we tweak how we collect data.
So I find that there's
some teams that
will ask, how can we collect
the data we need and how long?
And then ask, how
long will that take?
That usually leads to
much slower execution.
I, instead, tend
to go to my teams
and say, we have
two days or one day
or maybe a week, some
short time span like that,
and say, what's
the most creative,
respectful, responsible,
but creative way you
can use to collect data
in a short time span?
And one of the ways to
think about that, too,
is a training a model takes--
let's say it takes two days.
Maybe I should
take more one day.
If you can train a model
in a couple of days,
then I would not
spend like two months
to find data to train a model.
Because then, this
becomes a huge bottleneck.
Because you can train the
model relatively quickly,
let's take a commensurate
amount of time to design a model
or design the data
as train a model.
And depending on how long
it takes to train a model,
sometimes, training a model
needs to run overnight.
I actually see teams sometimes
take one day iteration
loops around this.
The fast moving
teams I work with,
we often go around
this loop once
per day for the smaller models.
If we're training a large
AI foundation model,
sometimes, training a model
takes weeks or even months,
then the process
can be different.
If your model run is
going to be two months,
then, yeah, maybe it makes sense
to spend a couple of months
to get the data really right.
But for face recognition,
you could train that
overnight, or actually, in a
couple of hours quite easily.
So it makes sense not to
spend massive amounts of time
before you go into
train the model.
Does that make sense?
And the word empirical
means experimental.
Sorry, I've used the
word a few times today.
And I think we say that
machine learning is
very empirical process.
Meaning, it's very
experimental process.
You have to do it,
see what happens,
then decide what to do next.
I know that sometimes, others
have criticized our field
like we never what we're doing.
We just try stuff
and see what works.
And there's a little
bit of truth to that.
I think understanding neural
networks, hyperparameters,
architecture that
is really valuable.
So we don't just
try stuff at random.
But because we don't
what's in the data,
we do try a lot of things,
and then drive a disciplined
process, understand what works
and what doesn't, and then use
that to navigate forward.
Does that make sense?
And then I'll just say, there's
one exception to the advice I'm
giving here, which is, if
you're working on the project
that you have worked
on many times before--
so, I've built a bunch of
facial recognition systems,
so I have a sense from
previous experience
and from reading research papers
that certain things, I know
are just not going to
work if I have 100 images.
So there's some face recognition
systems that I know probably
need at least 50,000 images
before it will have any hope
of working.
So because of that
prior experience,
having gone through that loop a
lot, I now have a basis to say,
OK, I do need 50,000 images,
then I might invest upfront
and put more effort upfront
to get those 50,000 images.
But I think for
most applications
you work on for the
first time, if you don't
have an academic literature
to justify certain larger data
investments, or if you don't
have the prior experience
yourself, then I would
focus on the speed
of iterating around this loop.
Make sense?
And to relate this to
large language models based
applications as well, a
lot of us, a lot of you
are probably-- well, you may
be building applications that
prompting OMs and
calling an API,
like OpenAI or Anthropic
or Gemini or Meta Llama
or whatever API to get
things back from [? home. ?]
One of the reasons that, too,
is a very experimental and very
iterative empirical
process is because when
you write an LLM
prompt, you don't really
know in advance
how well it's going
to do because it was trained
on data that none of us
have really looked at.
And that, too, is why,
instead of theorizing
for a long time about
what prompt to use in LLM,
just try it out.
And then it's by doing that,
you will then see the problems.
And then your focus can
be on fixing the problems.
Makes sense?
And in fact, there's a lot of
discussion on responsible AI,
how do you make your
AI systems are safe,
or they don't have
unforeseen circumstances.
And because a lot
of the theorizing--
you can only theorize so much.
I find that if you want to build
safe, responsible AI systems,
one of the best ways to do that
is to just build it, and then
experiment with it in
a sandbox environment.
Just don't let it
out in the world
until you've tested
it rigorously.
But just go build
something, and then test
it, probe it in the
safety of your own laptop.
Don't let it enter
innocent users
and have some weird impact
on innocent third parties.
But it's only by building
it and probing it
that you can figure out
where can it go wrong,
where it will say
inappropriate things, where
it would respond inappropriately
to certain user queries?
And then that tells you where
the problems are, and then
work on addressing.
Yeah, question?
How do you use
[? generalizing ?] results
to [INAUDIBLE]?
Sorry.
Say that again.
So when you come up and
you analyze it as a model
and you come to a conclusion
that your model is not good,
how do you use that to figure
out what's wrong in the data?
Great question.
So when you analyze something's
wrong with your model,
how do you use that to
take the next step forward?
That's a big topic that
we'll talk at length multiple
times in some of the videos and
also in some future lessons.
But maybe long story short,
one of the things you could do
is change your neural
network architecture.
You may realize that
maybe the sign means
that it wasn't working or
read the literature change
architecture.
The other thing you can
often do is change your data.
So data-centric AI
is the discipline
of systematically entering your
data to build a successful AI
system.
And it turns out that if
you build a face recognition
system, let's say, I like
your hat, Stanford hat.
That's cool.
But let's say,
hypothetically, that you
find that the system has
really struggles recognizing
people that are wearing hats.
Then you may say, I
need to get more data
with people wearing hats.
And so it's often that
looking at what goes wrong,
we should call error analysis.
That then gives you
the insight to say, oh,
it works well on these types of
data or these types of users,
but it struggles with these
types of users in the data.
So can I fix my data
or get more data just
on the subset of cases
it struggles with?
And that's a very common motion.
That's very common
process for then driving
the performance of your system.
And this is also why
blindly going out
to grab more data
willingly, that's often
not a good strategy.
Because there's just too
much data you could get.
Do I want more data with
people with long hair
or short hair or people
with facial hair?
Sorry, too much hair.
Too many hair examples.
Or do I want people
wearing a scarf,
covering part of
the face, or people
that wear glasses, or
that don't wear glasses,
or people that are
slightly turned away?
There's just so
many different types
of data you could invest
effort to get more of that
until you build a system,
see where it goes well,
see where it goes poorly, is
really difficult to decide where
to get more data and just
get more data of everything
under the sun.
That's very slow and expensive.
And I think part of the
hype about the value of data
has led people to have sometimes
overly simplistic view of data.
Yes, of course,
I want more data.
But just grabbing more
data of all types of data
is a very inefficient,
very expensive way
to improve my system.
And even if you look at the way
that frontier models are trained
right now is not a game of just
grabbing more data of anything
under the sun.
It is identifying
the subcategories
where it's valuable to invest
to get high quality data, which
is why, if you look at--
It turns out in AI, there
are two clear buckets
of value in LLMs.
There's the general
answering people's questions.
I think OpenAI [INAUDIBLE]
is doing really well there.
Gemini, Anthropic have momentum.
But there's a [? chance in ?]
general questions.
And then one of the
verticals is really
valuable, is AI for
coding assistant.
So I think Claude has
been ahead for a while.
But OpenAI, Gemini 2.5
Pro, some of the models
are making really good
progress in coding as well.
And if you look at the work that
the frontier teams are doing
to improve coding, building
iterative agentic workflows
is part of it.
But also finding clever ways to
come up with coding related data
is also a part of it.
And if you want your OM
to do better in coding,
you don't grab data willy-nilly
with low quality random internet
chat, social media,
or whatever data.
But instead, having high
quality coding related data
is how you can have
a focused effort
to improve your OM's
ability to code.
So a lot of these
things are actually--
Yeah, I feel more
data is better.
That is absolutely true.
But it's also overly simplistic.
Data is not monolithic.
There are subcategories of data.
And having a view on
what piece of data
to really invest in
getting a lot more of,
that's really important to being
efficient in how you improve
your system's performance.
That makes sense?
Well, we'll talk more
about error analysis later.
Any other questions?
Cool.
Yeah, go for it.
What about the
technology of data?
For example, in the future, if
you want to collect [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah, so as you collect
data, the quality
of data matters a lot, too.
And I think data quality
is tricky, I think.
When building an application
for the first time,
I would still focus on speed and
collecting some data quickly.
But as you then analyze
where a system is going well
and where it's doing
poorly, you often
find that the quality
of data really matters.
So trying to decide, should I
talk about this now or later?
So let's see what's
a good example.
Let's talk about [INAUDIBLE].
There's a lot of low
quality random chat
on the internet that's not
that useful for training LLMs.
But I think it's
actually now well known
that if you can legally access
very high quality written,
authored articles or books
that are highly edited, very
insightful, that's very high
quality data for training norms.
And I'll give an example later
as well for face recognition.
It turns out that
blurry images would
be a lower quality than
sharp, in-focus images,
assuming that's
representative of how you want
to recognize people's faces.
So that really matters as well.
Anything else?
Cool Yeah, go for it.
Question about the
data and how close
do you need to be to ask
what we want them to do.
For example, in face
recognition where
we're trying to compare
two pictures [INAUDIBLE]
to train a model, just to
compare object, just [INAUDIBLE]
people's faces.
It's much faster,
but we're moving away
from the ideal task we
want [INAUDIBLE] to do.
So what is the balance here?
Yeah, so just repeat for mic.
How important is it that
the data you collect
is similar to the distribution
of things you want to work on?
I think it's important,
but not as important
as most people might think.
So it turns out one of the
reasons neural networks have
been so effective is because
when you build a very
large neural network, you
can throw all sorts of data
into it, including data that is
not perfectly tuned to your test
set distribution.
And it often
doesn't hurt so long
as your network is big enough.
So you raise the example.
What if we have it identified
two identical objects?
If it's generic objects like
water bottles and markers,
maybe that's too far afield.
But if we were to
use, let's say,
simulated cartoonish
characters that
look really different
than real humans,
my guess is it probably
won't hurt at all
and may even help a little bit.
And so throwing
in a lot of data,
you can train a large neural
network with a lot of capacity
to absorb even some
slightly relevant data.
It usually doesn't hurt and
might even help a little bit.
But how much it helps is
another empirical question
that will be problem
dependent, and we often just
have to try it out.
But in the past, people
used to have an obsession
that the data you
train on has come
from exactly the same
distribution as the distribution
you test on.
That used to be how
machine learning was
done 10, 15 years ago.
That's really not
true today anymore.
I think we're very comfortable.
And I think when neural
networks were much smaller, when
you could train
very small models,
there was a sense
that you didn't
want to distract the neural
network with irrelevant data
because a computer was
expensive, with few parameters.
And if you distract
on irrelevant stuff,
maybe it gets less
good at the core tasks
you really care about.
But if you can train a bigger
than neural network, which
is getting easier and
easier these days,
then it's become much more OK to
toss in some data that hopefully
isn't incorrect data.
I think incorrect data
would be a problem.
But just irrelevant
examples hurts
much less because big neural
networks is like a human brain.
The fact that I learned
to play the piano
probably doesn't
make me worse at AI.
Because hopefully, my
brain is big enough
to learn to play the piano
and learn some stuff about AI.
And I think as neural
networks get big enough,
they can learn some
other irrelevant things
and also do well at the core
task that you really care about.
But this was less true if
my brain was really small.
I don't think any are
fans of Sherlock Holmes.
But I think Sherlock
Holmes had an attic theory
that your brain has
only so much capacity
so you've got to forget some
stuff to learn new stuff.
But when you train very
large neural networks,
that's much less true.
Cool.
Thank you all the questions.
So what I want to do is just
keep going through this flow.
So we talked about get data,
design model, train the model.
We'll talk a lot more
about error analysis later
this quarter of
how to figure out
where your algorithm
is still subpar
and where to focus
efforts to improve it.
But what I want to do is give
you a sense of a deployment.
So, when you have
trained a model
is often a bunch of
software engineering work
to then maybe take
your model, host it
in the cloud or local server,
and have it run inference.
So a very common architecture
for deploying machine
learning model will be that
you have a neural network
as a piece of software.
You deploy it maybe on
a cloud hosted service
so that your software can
accept a picture or a set of two
pictures, and it
will reply back.
Do I unlock the door or not?
Or is this the
same person or not?
So that's much of
software engineering
work that needs to be done.
But in practical
deployment settings--
I'll actually tell you.
It turns out that if you're
building a practical face
recognition system, you probably
find that if you are trying
to unlock a door to a corporate
campus is too expensive or too
slow to stream video 24/7 to
cloud to classify every frame
at 30 frames a second to see if
there's a person that you should
unlock the door for.
So in practical face recognition
systems, what we end up doing--
so actually, let's take
the example of someone
walk up to the door to your
home, to your door at home.
And you want to see if
there's someone there that you
should unlock the door for.
So a lot of systems
will actually
have an image from the camera,
and then try to build a system--
So what we have
so far is a system
that takes as input an image
and maybe a reference image.
Neural network says, do
I unlock the door or not?
But it turns out that
if streaming video is
too expensive, classifying
every frame is too expensive,
we'll often end up with
a system like this.
Well, VAD stands for
Visual Activity Detection.
And what this does is
a usually low cost,
low power, inexpensive
compute job
to run to just very quickly
maybe try to figure out,
is there a human face there?
Because it turns out, actually,
if you're building something
unlock your front door
to you and your friends,
if you look out my
front door and my house,
it's pretty boring.
There's a wall.
We see a little over
the street, but nothing
moves most of the time.
So almost all of the
time, it's very obvious
that there's no one outside my
front door trying to be let in
and be very wasteful to stream
all that video to the internet
for classification.
So visual activity detection
is usually a low cost,
low power system to just
very quickly decide,
should I do the work of
sending this to the larger face
recognition system
neural network that
may be hosted on
the cloud to have
it do the much more
computationally expensive work
to decide, 0 or 1, do I
unlock the door or not?
So this type of
optimization, in order
to make the system
computationally
feasible to deploy
is fairly common.
And I'm going to give
you two options for how
to implement VAD.
And I'm going to ask
you to reflect on them,
and then tell me which one
you would pick to get started.
So option one is a non-machine
learning based method,
which is--
see if the number
of pixels changed--
is greater than some
threshold epsilon.
So if the camera is
stationary, maybe
looking at a wall,
most of the time,
the pixels barely change
because it's just a wall.
And so you can write
a little bit of code
using some image library
like PIL, Python Imaging
Library, or some simple write a
few lines of code to just say,
has the number of
pixels whose RGB
values that change more than
some threshold has more than 10%
of the pixels changed
compared to what it looked
like a second ago, in order to
see if there's anything in front
of your camera to even
decide to pass this to a more
high powered neural network.
Option two would be to train
a small neural network.
So face recognition is
a pretty complex task.
You have to look at
multiple cues in the face.
Look at the eyes,
look at the mouth.
So that takes a relatively
large neural network.
But just taking a
quick glance to see,
is there even a human
in front of my door?
That's a much simpler task.
So option two would be training
a very small, very low power,
very lightweight neural network
to just very quickly tell you,
do you think there's
a human there?
And then use this
trained model to decide,
is it worth passing on to a much
more powerful neural network
running in the cloud
with a lot more resources
to make the final determination?
So if you are the CTO of a
three-person startup building
this, how would you start?
We'll give everyone a few
seconds to reflect on this,
get people's thoughts.
Go for it.
[INAUDIBLE] in the street
where people walk by.
[INAUDIBLE] you might get
a lot of false positives.
So it depends on what
type of phone you have.
And you can also
go with an option
that you can make it sound
simpler classification,
not necessarily a
[INAUDIBLE] or it [INAUDIBLE]
is there a person
there [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah, right.
Cool Yeah, cool.
Just repeating
[INAUDIBLE] my mic.
So problem dependent
depends on whether you're
on the street where a lot
of people walking past maybe
consider other algorithms.
They're even cheaper
than small neural net.
Cool.
[INAUDIBLE] that.
[INAUDIBLE] just a
training model because this
is not the main
[INAUDIBLE] for that.
We could probably just be
talking about [INAUDIBLE]
while we collect more data.
And then [INAUDIBLE] with this.
Yeah, cool.
Great.
So use option one
in the short term.
And then maybe replace
that with option two
when we have more data.
Yeah, cool.
That's very same approach.
I was thinking, why don't
you use two options?
Because the [INAUDIBLE]
is very simple.
Only if that is clear
is then we [INAUDIBLE]
say [INAUDIBLE] or not.
And after that, moving to one.
Sorry, so use both options
or put both in the pipeline.
That's interesting, I see.
[INAUDIBLE]
So option one, let option
one see if anything change.
If something is changed, then
pass this [? neural ?] network.
That's cool.
That could work.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, cool.
Yeah, that could work.
So like a cascade
of multiple steps.
Yeah.
Which would [INAUDIBLE]
because that would affect--
[? because ?] it's
cheap to [INAUDIBLE].
Because then, you
don't have to worry
about someone coming to the
door and nothing happening.
If it's more expensive
than I would probably
invest [INAUDIBLE] options.
I see, cool.
[INAUDIBLE] make sure we're
not wasting [INAUDIBLE].
I see, cool.
Yeah, so how expensive is it
to run this neural network
in the cloud?
So actually, so I would usually
want to design both of these
to run at the edge,
meaning, on the device.
[INAUDIBLE]
This one.
Yeah.
So it turns out that streaming
video is fairly expensive.
So I think, yeah, I feel like--
boy, I don't have numbers
at tip of my fingertips.
But I think running this
24/7 is not feasible.
So we definitely need
something to filter it down.
But sending few
images every minute
is probably not a problem.
Makes sense?
Go ahead.
[INAUDIBLE]
Sorry?
Sample certain
frames of the video
in order to get all of them.
Yes, I guess so.
Yeah, although I think if you
have a video of my front door,
you need a way to sample
other than random, I guess.
Because a lot of
times, nothing happens
unless you take one frame
per minute, I guess,
which would be OK.
But then, we don't want someone
waiting there for a full minute
before we finally get around
to sampling and sending it.
So, yeah.
Go ahead.
This is a question.
Could we use the same
images to train [INAUDIBLE]
a neural network [INAUDIBLE]?
Or with that be biased?
Yeah, can we use the same
images for training this network
to train the option two network?
Maybe.
It's actually one
of the things, I
would say, where to try it
before we know if it works.
Might be doable.
Depends a lot on what
data we collected to train
the [INAUDIBLE] neural network.
Cool.
Let's take a [INAUDIBLE].
Go ahead.
[INAUDIBLE]
Cool, yeah.
How about use option one,
keep a really low threshold.
So we send very few images.
Is that what you mean?
Yeah, I think that would
that be reasonable to try.
Well, so long as we don't
miss too many people.
But, yeah.
Let's take one last comment.
I'll share your
perspective on [INAUDIBLE].
[INAUDIBLE]
Yes.
so one of the
weaknesses of option one
is if there's a tree
swaying in the background
or if you see a road and
there's a car that drives by
or if there's a busy street, the
car is driving by all the time,
or the neighbor's
cat comes and visits.
Those will trigger this.
So those are downsides.
So let me show you a perspective
of how I would approach this,
and what we actually did.
So if you are the CTO of a
startup implementing this,
to me, it again
comes down to speed.
And so what I would ask
is, how long does it
take to implement option
one and how long does it
take to implement option two?
And I think everyone made
good points about the pros
and cons of these two options.
And if you are actually doing
this, the approach I would take
is, just ask, what
can I do really
quickly so I can then deploy
it and see whether it works.
And then I'll fix it
if it doesn't work.
Because I think
these insights like,
would trees swaying in
the background affect it?
It turns out it actually
does probably, but maybe
not if the wind isn't
that strong or if--
But it's very difficult to know
answers to questions like these
because you don't really
know until you stick
on a bunch of cameras in front
of doors and see the data,
then you can get more confident
in how well option one works,
how often does a neighbor's
cat actually come by?
And if there's a car that drives
past other cars usually so far
away, that it doesn't matter
because the number of pixels
per car is small.
So all of these are very
empirical questions.
It's really difficult to answer.
And the fastest
way to get answers
is to just implement
something quick and dirty.
And then run it, see what
goes wrong, and then fix it.
So what happens on--
And to tell you,
what the experience
of a lot of face
recognition teams
is, because option one
is so quick to implement,
this is like five lines
of Python or something.
And get an answer right for you.
Just get on to write five
lines of Python for you.
So you can implement this in
20 minutes, maybe even less.
Whereas this, I think will
take you at least many hours,
maybe longer to implement.
So my instinct would
be to start with this.
And it turns out, having built
many face recognition systems,
I'll tell you this actually
doesn't work well enough for all
the problems people raise.
And so we wind up going to this.
But implementing this
also gives you insights
into where it's going wrong.
And I'll give you one
example of one insight
that we and many other face
recognition teams have,
which is, it turns out that
when you're approaching
a camera that's trying
to recognize your face,
there are some
frames that are going
to be really clear and in
focus, and a lot of frames
that are really blurry.
If you just look at a
video of someone walking
toward the camera,
just when I'm stepping,
sometimes, the velocity
of my face is higher,
and sometimes it's lower.
That's just what it is.
And so sometimes,
my face is in focus.
Sometimes, it's more blurry.
And it turns out that
if you can select out
the high resolution frames and
feed that to face recognition,
you get much higher
quality results.
So this is the kind
of stuff that I
assume most people would
not know about until you
worked on a system like this.
But it turns out that
when I was working on
a system like that, having
a system to not just do
VAD, but also capture the video
and then deliberately select
not just one, but maybe five
frames that are high resolution
and in focus of the
person, that actually
gave a significant boost to the
accuracy of our face recognition
system.
And I mentioned this as an
example of the discovery
that you will have only when you
implement one of these systems,
maybe even implement
this system.
But you implement
the system, you see,
boy, we're trying to
recognize a lot of pictures
from blurry faces.
Maybe you could need to
do something about that.
And this is driving
that empirical process
that may then lead you to
train a neural network, both
to see if there's a
face, but also to see
if the picture of the face
is in focus to select out
that frame for
downstream processing.
Does that make sense?
And this is why you find that
for some meaningful fraction
of questions that
I asked in class.
The thing that's
the speediest to do
is often the right answer
because that obsession
with speed really lets
you go in and figure out
what's in your data and improve
your system more efficiently.
So, yeah.
So what happens in practice?
Start with this.
Discover how it doesn't work
because it doesn't actually
work.
I'll tell you that.
And then figure out.
But use those
learnings to do this.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, so is there a sense of
what is a good classification
accuracy problems like these?
It's actually really difficult.
One of the common benchmarks--
you learn more about this in
the third module on the online
videos as well--
is building machine
learning systems
is easier if we have a
reference level of performance,
like an aspirational target
accuracy, which is often
human-level performance.
And so it turns out that
the way you diagnose
bias and variance,
which I'll talk
should talk about
later in this course,
it's easier if you know what's
an achievable level of accuracy.
And very often, we'll
use what a human expert
could do as achievable
level of accuracy.
And then in the case of
face recognition, definitely
under controlled environments,
we're better than humans.
So, definitely.
Actually, the AI
systems we built,
they're way better than I am
at recognizing human faces.
And I think AI systems are
better than, I will say,
probably the vast
majority of humans,
maybe all humans at this point,
at really distinguishing of two
pictures are the same.
And then it gets
really difficult.
Then it actually gets
more difficult [INAUDIBLE]
even better than humans.
But, yeah.
But until you're as good as
humans on a certain task,
using a human level performance
is often a good benchmark.
And then if you are
doing something that even
humans can't do well--
like it turns out, you're
recommending online books
or movies or whatever.
Humans are actually
not that good at that.
I think most of us would
have a hard time recommending
good movies, even to
our closest friends.
AI actually probably does it
even better than many of us
do as humans.
Then those things is harder
to establish a baseline.
Cool.
Now, one final aspect
I want to touch on
is after deploying a model
to monitor and to maintain
the model, one thing
that often happens
is, you train a
machine learning model.
Works great.
Does well on your training set.
Does well on your test set.
Works great.
And then you deploy it.
And then annoyingly, the
world changes, and your system
no longer works.
So we sometimes call this
data drift or concept drift,
where the distribution
of data, the world
gives you is different than what
you had in your training set
or concept drift, which is
the input output mapping.
Your x and y changes in the
world compared to your training
set.
But to ground this, if you are
training a face recognition
system now in--
when it's not too cold
here in California,
you get faces of a
certain distribution.
But as we approach
winter, if it starts
to rain more, people are
wearing scarves, rain jackets,
people look different.
Or maybe we approach the summer.
More people are
wearing sunglasses.
Then the data
distribution changes.
Or if you train a system based
on data here in California,
but we then decide to deploy
it in a different country
where people dress
differently or where
their appearance is different.
The world keeps on
giving us different data.
And so one of the
jobs of I think us
as machine learning engineers
is to put in place systems that
monitor this type of concept
drift or data drift, and fix
problems as they arise.
When you're out building
machine learning systems,
I have seen a segment
of AI engineers
that think their job is
to do well on a test set.
And so I've been in a bunch
of these conversations
where the machine learning
person would say, look,
I did well on the test set.
My job is done.
But then a product
owner or business owner
will say, no, your
system doesn't work.
Look at all the ways
it does not work.
And then if the machine
learning person says,
well, that's not my problem.
I do well on the test set.
I think that's not
a constructive way
to move it forward.
So I encourage you to
think of yourselves.
If you're building a
machine learning system,
I think of my job as building
something that works.
And that can be different
than building something
that works on a test set.
So if ever you're working on
a product, and someone says,
I know you did well
on the test set,
but your system doesn't work.
I would encourage
you not to respond.
But my job is to
do one to test it.
I encourage you to think about
why doing one on the test set
doesn't translate to doing
well on the application
that people actually care about,
and then lean in and go and fix
that.
And one of the common problems
for why doing well on a test set
doesn't translate to
doing well in real life
is if the data distribution
changes, in which case,
you may need to update the
distribution of data you're
training on in order
to capture whatever
has changed in the world.
And just a few other examples.
I feel like the world gives
us new data all the time.
So if you're building
a web search engine,
sometimes, a new
politician is elected
or there's a new movement
or some new video
goes viral or Taylor Swift
releases a new album, whatever.
And then people are suddenly
searching for a brand--
I thought I'd get
a laugh from that.
No?
No Swifties here.
All right.
[CHUCKLES]
But then suddenly,
a lot of people
are searching for
a brand new thing.
And so the distribution
of data you get
is different because
the world has changed.
Or I've done a lot
of work in factories.
There's actually a
reasonable chance
that a cell phone you
have in your pocket
may have been inspected by
software that my teams wrote.
But sometimes, the
materials change.
Or there's a new machine
installed in the manufacturing
line.
And this machine makes
a new type of scratch
on the cell phone.
So data changes in
inspection lines as well.
Or one thing that
actually surprised me,
when I work on self-driving
cars, one of the things
I was working with, we trained
a lot on data in California.
And then when we took the cars
to Texas, you and I as people,
we can drive just fine in
California or in Texas.
But it turns out that traffic
lights look really different
in Texas, in California.
So traffic lights,
horizontal, vertical.
I think part of it is that
there are very high winds
in some parts of Texas.
So a lot of traffic lights tend
to be strung up differently,
to be robust to high winds.
And so traffic lights actually
look pretty different in Texas.
So the models we train
in California, they
don't work in Texas
because we get new data.
Refresh the data.
So a lot of that is a process
of monitoring and maintaining
the model, even when something
in the world changes.
And before going on to
monitoring the model performance
and maintaining it, one
interesting difference
in performance
between this and this
is option one is
very simple model.
It basically has
one parameter, which
is epsilon, the fraction
of pixels that change.
And so this, because
it's so simple,
is actually very robust to
changes in distribution.
For example, say it's a hot
summer and a lot of people
are wearing sunglasses.
Well, the fraction of
pixels that change,
even when people are
wearing sunglasses,
doesn't change that much.
Maybe if it's
Halloween and people
are wearing crazy
large costumes,
maybe that would change.
But this is actually a
very robust algorithm
because it's so simple.
In contrast, if
you trained on data
with no one wearing
sunglasses because the sun's
not that hot these days.
Then with everyone starts
to wear sunglasses,
this is actually less robust.
So one of the
advantages, very simple
non-machine
learning-based systems
is they may be less
susceptible to data drift.
Because maybe I tuned
this parameter epsilon
to limit the data set.
But even when the data changes,
this tuning can be quite robust.
But if I train a neural
network with, say, thousands
or tens of thousands
of parameters,
then I'm more likely to overfit
to people without sunglasses.
So when people start
wearing sunglasses,
you're more likely to
have to update this model.
And if you are building a--
sorry.
Cool.
Boy.
If you're building a
system, it turns out
to be incredibly helpful if
you can get user permission
to stream a little bit of
data back to your cloud
hosted service.
So that respecting user privacy,
being careful of opt in,
transparent privacy practices--
I think privacy is
really important.
So do be transparent.
Do the right thing for users.
And if you're able to do that
and get a little bit of data
back to your cloud
to plot dashboards--
and maybe one practice
that I've seen
is when building a high
stakes application,
one good practice would be
to gather your team together
and get a diverse
set of opinions
on all the things
you could change,
or all the things
that could go wrong.
And I've built quite a few
machine learning systems.
And I've found that when
we sit down and brainstorm
all the things that could
go wrong, including the data
distribution changes, I don't
think I have ever seen something
go wrong in real
life that we did not
identify as a possible problem.
I might be wrong.
But at least right
now, when we sat down,
we really brainstorm all
the things to go wrong.
I think I have yet
to see something
go wrong that was not
on the list of stuff
that we brainstormed.
And so if you
brainstorm-- and this
is true for safety critical
applications as well.
It turns out creative
teams, you can actually
think of all sorts of things
that could change the data
or things that could go wrong.
And that then lets you try
to design a set of dashboards
or metrics to put in place
to monitor whether or not
any of these things that
you think might go wrong
actually do go wrong.
So we may put in place
dashboards [? light-- ?]
it turns out re-authentication
is a common thing.
How often does the user
need to authenticate twice
before they let through?
That's actually a sign
of user frustration.
So let's build a
dashboard to do that.
How often does a user
have to try twice?
Because it probably
means something
went wrong the first time.
How often do you accept
versus reject the user?
And what is the
latency of the system?
And I find that just as it's
difficult to know in advance
what's in your
data, it's actually
difficult to know in
advance what dashboard
will be the most useful.
And so the best practice
I tend to recommend
is brainstorm a lot of
things that go wrong,
brainstorm a lot of metrics,
and then just create
very rich dashboards
where this is time,
latency, re-authentication.
Time, the number of
zeros versus ones.
And then draw plots over time to
see how these rates trend over
time.
And if you're able to have a
lot of dashboards and sample
and just look at
some of the data
for where you suspect it
may be making a mistake,
that often is then
a good way for you
to have a higher
chance of spotting
when there might be a problem.
And in the times that
built large dashboards
with 20, 30 metrics, I found
that it's surprisingly difficult
to know in advance
which dashboards
will turn out to be useful.
I think in exploratory data
analysis, in data science,
again, because we often
don't know what's in the data
or what the data will
give us in the future,
we just frankly
plot a lot of stuff,
and then go and figure out
from there what is interesting.
So the cost of plotting
something in a Jupyter Notebook
is fairly low.
So let's just plot a lot of
stuff, have a lot of dashboards.
And if you end up with, 30,
50, 100 dashboards tracking
these metrics over
time, then hopefully,
in a few days or
a few weeks, you
figure out that a lot of
them are really boring.
So we figure out that, well,
latency is just not a thing
because the cloud-hosted
deployment is just
very constant.
So well, let's get rid
of that because that's
just a very boring plot.
I'm just not worried about that.
And so often, plot
a lot of things
and then prune back to then
have a smaller number of metrics
and we track and monitor
for the long term.
And then eventually,
when you get
a sense of just being the
normal range for some metric,
you can then also put in
place upper and lower alarms.
So that if it ever goes above
or below certain bounds,
they'll trigger an alarm,
like go pay someone
to take a look to figure out
if something's gone wrong.
That makes sense?
And so unfortunately, just
because you train a model a lot
of time in a real world
production setting,
it doesn't mean you're done.
Because you deploy
it, and then the world
will give you surprising data.
And having a plan to
monitor what happens
as well as to
maintain the model,
meaning get new data,
update the system
to fix problems as
they arise, that
is often an important part of
the practicalities of deploying
a machine learning
system as well.