So what I want to do today
is continue our discussion
on AI project strategy.
So if you're building a deep
learning system for some tasks.
And today, for the
first part of today,
I'm going to use a
speech recognition
voice-activated device example.
And then for the
second half, we're
going to use a kind of AI
deep researcher example.
But what I want
to do is walk you
through a couple concrete
examples of projects
you might work on, and let
you understand what it feels
like to be in the thick
of building an AI system,
making day to day decisions
on what to do next.
I think as you've heard me
say before, understanding
the algorithms is important.
So in this class,
you learn a lot
from the online videos about
the deep learning algorithms,
how to build pipelines.
But even beyond understanding
how the algorithms work,
what really drives performance
is a team's ability
to have an efficient
development process.
How do you tune hyperparameters?
How do you collect data?
When you try something
and it doesn't
work the first time, which
it often doesn't, what
do you do next?
Your skill in making those
decisions is what often makes
a massive, literally 10X
difference in productivity.
And as I was reflecting,
I was preparing
for what to say to you today.
I was reflecting on quite a
few projects where that 10X
difference in productivity is
really not an exaggeration.
Maybe more than 10X.
But I've literally
seen many teams
in many well-known
companies with good brands
spend a year
working on a project
that I will see a more skilled
team execute in a month.
So these differences
in skill are real.
And one of the challenges
for people learning this
is if you work for
some company, maybe
you work on a different
project every year or two.
So it takes you two years
or a year of your life
to gain experience
on one more project.
And then after, I
don't know, 10 years,
you've finally seen 10 projects
and are pretty experienced.
But what I want to do
is, in today's class,
walk you through a few
concrete examples of projects
that are similar to one kind
of simplified versions of stuff
that I've seen myself
to try to accelerate
your hands on experience
looking at these projects
and thinking through if you
are the one in the hot seat,
building a system, and
it works or doesn't work,
or there's a
problem or whatever,
making those decisions
for what you would do.
So try to get you through that
today with a couple of examples,
rather than you having to spend
years, and years of your life
to finally see a small
number of examples of how
these projects can be driven.
So the first, the two motivating
examples I want to use today
is building a
voice-activated device.
In my house, I have
an Amazon Echo, where
I have a lot of them, actually.
And I think it's a
delightful experience.
But those devices like that,
Amazon Echo or Google Home,
or the Apple Siri
and HomePod, they
require quite a bit of setup.
They require some setup.
They connect to Wi-Fi.
Figure a way to
connect to your phone.
Actually, for a long time, even
though I built smart speakers,
for a long time in my house,
I had one light bulb connected
to my home Wi-Fi internet.
Because it's just so much of
a hassle to set things up.
I think now I have two light
bulbs connected in my house.
I guess, I should
connect more stuff.
So for this example,
I want to talk about
if you are part of a startup,
building a new product that
makes it much easier to
get these voice control
devices without the user needing
to do this whole Wi-Fi setup
process.
So I'm not very good at drawing.
But if you could go to some
store and buy a desk lamp
and the desk lamp
already has a name,
I'll just call
this lamp, Robert.
And you could just take it,
plug it into electricity,
plunk it on your desk, and
then say, Robert, turn on.
And then it turns on.
Say, Robert, turn off.
It turns off without needing to
be connected to the internet.
So this is a cloud
access and all that.
Then that would give users
a easier set of experience.
There's a project that
my friends and I actually
discussed a few years ago
that we thought would actually
be a decent startup idea.
We decided not to do it
because there are too
many other ideas that were
even more excited about.
But we felt that actually
like a reasonable startup
idea to build a
little IC circuit,
little integrated
circuit, to sell to say,
lamp manufacturers and
other device manufacturers
to make it really easy
if say, some company
sells lamps to build
little things so they
can very quickly make their
devices voice-enabled.
And if you have a
few pre-built names,
maybe give the users a choice.
You can call your lamp Robert,
or Lana, or I don't know,
or Johnny or I don't
know, Alice or whatever.
Have a little switch, then
users could just buy a lamp,
put it down, and
then immediately
have it be voice
control without needing
to worry about how do you get
this onto my Wi-Fi network.
And if my internet is
down, then my whole house
stays dark as well.
Bizarre things like that.
And I actually
did once have an--
I was building a lot
of voice assistants.
I actually set up
my office to have
a lot of voice control devices.
So had different names
and different lamps.
Standing desk, it
has name as well.
So I'd say-- I forget
what my desk name was.
Jonathan, go higher or whatever.
And then my standing desk
would go up and down.
It's actually pretty cool.
So what I want you-- so just for
today's illustration, probably
we should give the
different devices,
different names because
you can't have every device
in your house called Robert.
Otherwise, you say, Robert, turn
on, the whole house illuminates.
And then Robert, turn off.
Whole house is
plunged into darkness.
So we found out you do
need different devices
to have different names.
But just for today,
I'm going to use,
as illustration, the task
of training a neural network
or building a system that
detects when someone says,
Robert, turn on.
And you need Robert, turn
on, Robert, turn off.
If you have a choice that needs
to be Lana, turn on, Lana,
turn off, a variety of
handful of options of names.
But just for
simplicity, I'm going
to worry only about detecting
the phrase Robert, turn on.
And what do we do for this?
You can rinse and repeat
to get the turn off command
and a handful of
other names to make it
user selectable, what name do
you want to give this thing.
OK.
So this is something
that I'll need to run
on device, small IC circuits.
And I'm going to
ask you a question.
When you've
graduated from CS230,
or maybe when you
graduate from Stanford,
if you are the CTO of a startup
responsible for building this,
what would you do?
So called out.
So imagine you just
graduated from CS230
or graduated from Stanford, and
you are the CTO of a startup,
and you want to build this lamp
that can turn on when anyone
says, Robert, turn on.
How would you
approach this problem?
And I know this is an
incredibly open ended question.
And it turns out life is
incredibly open-ended.
You graduate from CS230, you
have to decide what to do.
So if this is what you're
doing, raise your hand
or call out if you want
to build this product.
What's the first thing you do?
How would you think about it?
Go for it.
[INAUDIBLE] speech-to-text
model [INAUDIBLE]
the actual word of
the lamp [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah.
Cool.
Right.
So get some open source
speech-to-text model
or something, and then
see if you can run.
Yeah, that'd be a good start.
Anything else?
Yeah, go ahead.
[INAUDIBLE] three models.
[INAUDIBLE] just going
on to the second one.
[INAUDIBLE] the third one
would try to [INAUDIBLE].
Three models, one that
detects Robert and one that--
The first one,
detects the sound.
I see.
The second one, detects
the word Robert.
The third one
tries to understand
the sentence [INAUDIBLE].
I see.
Cool.
OK.
So the three models
to detect Robert,
understand, read sentence,
or detected the sound.
Cool.
Go for it.
Sorry.
Say it again.
[INAUDIBLE] Robert.
Then let's say you want
to explain [INAUDIBLE]
then you have repeat the
same process for [INAUDIBLE].
So instead, what you could do
is take a model that takes--
given [INAUDIBLE]
and see, trying
to identify one or two policies.
OK.
Obviously, it's like
a Siamese network.
We actually teach
a Siamese network
in this class, where some
people inputs two audio files
and decide the same word.
So you can more easily
generalize to new words
than Robert.
Cool.
That's actually interesting.
Yeah, go for it.
I don't know how to
[INAUDIBLE] but I
think that maybe people are
going to install some plugin.
And have a [INAUDIBLE]
so I think it's silly.
[INAUDIBLE] like
turn it off, turn on.
Sorry.
You mean just connect
up your device to Siri?
Yes.
[INAUDIBLE] neural
network on my iPhone.
And the iPhone will
send the [INAUDIBLE]
the signal to
[INAUDIBLE] turn on.
I see.
OK, cool.
Yeah.
That sounds interesting.
It sounds like a different
product than this
if we need to connect to your
cell phone and all that, though.
Yeah.
Cool.
All right.
So let me just--
lots of interesting ideas.
Let me just make
some observations.
So I find that when
building software products,
there's actually
lots of good ideas
or lots of reasonable
things you could try.
But as you heard me
mention a few weeks ago,
I think one of the
strongest predictors
for the odds of your building
something compelling is speed.
So I find that of
all of these ideas,
I think some are better than
others, but it doesn't--
but whether the idea is, a bit
better, a little bit worse,
it is important,
but it's actually
secondary to how quickly you
can just get something built.
So if you're actually the
CTO of a startup like this,
I would encourage you to
look and say, all right,
what can we build today, or what
can we build maybe in a week,
and try out any of these
architecture choices
and build it and
see what happens.
Because even if what you build
is a little bit less good,
you can find out
all in two days,
you can course
correct very quickly.
I've actually built a
lot of smart speakers.
So I have maybe first
hand experience of this.
And I'll just share
some things that I
happen to know that there's
no reason you wouldn't know.
But it turns out that--
let's see, at least today,
general purpose, speech
recognition is still a
little bit heavyweight.
It takes quite a lot
of processing power.
It's a bit expensive to
run on an edge device
if you want to make
this just a few dollars.
But it turns out that if you
look at the smart speakers,
there's usually--
if you want to train
a neural network just
to detect one phrase, be it a
phrase like OK, Google, or hey,
Siri or Alexa or whatever, and
the smart speaker trigger words,
that can be done with a
fairly small neural network.
Although to your
point, if we want
to do different neural
networks, different words,
we would need to swap out
different neural networks
and rinse and repeat that.
But if you have only a small
handful of names, phrases
1 to 10, I think they'll be OK.
And then one other
piece of advice
I would give if you're
embarking on this,
is the first thing I
would do, actually,
if I was working on this for
the first time is actually
a literature search.
And it turns out that--
I think we're fortunate
that the AI world has
a ton of open source software
and a ton of open research
papers.
Some are surprisingly,
despite smart speakers having
been around for a
long time, they're
still, to this day, isn't
a single architecture
that everyone's agreed on,
on the best way to do this.
If you look at the literature,
there's still actually
a diversity of opinions on how
to do this type of wake word
or trigger word.
We use those terms.
So when you say something
like, OK, Google or hey, Siri
or Alexa.
That's sometimes
called a wake word
because it wakes up the device
or that triggers the device
circuit activity.
So somewhat surprisingly,
even though we
have smart speakers
for a long time
now, for a lot
more than a decade,
there's still isn't a single
agreed on unified architecture
that the community
has agreed on,
on what's the best
algorithm to do this.
But I feel like if
you are embarking
on this the first
time, the number one
boost in your speed
of learning, it could
be implementing something.
But I would say doing
a literature search
and try open source
software would
be the even faster accelerator.
And I want to give you a few
tips for that real quick.
So today, if this is--
there are a lot of research
articles and blog posts
and GitHub repos on many topics,
certainly wake word detection.
And what I find is that if this
is research paper one, research
paper two, research paper three,
research paper four, I find it
people will spend a lot of
time reading research paper
one until you're done.
This is 0% complete.
This is 100% complete.
And then spend a lot of time
reading research paper two,
spend a lot of time reading
research paper three,
and I just recommend
you not do that.
Instead, when I'm doing a
literature search, what it often
feels like is do
a few web searches
for a handful of resources,
skim all of them, 0% complete,
100% complete.
Based on your
initial reading, you
may decide to go
back to paper three
and spend more time to really
read and understand that,
but that'll help you find
additional references.
You can skim.
And maybe you find a paper
seven that's really seminal.
Spend a lot of effort.
But this is what doing a very
broad survey of the literature
will feel like, where you
really put in the time
to finish only a very
small number of resources,
but spend a lot more time
skipping around and giving
a cursory level, understanding
of a broader set of papers,
which can also point you to
the more useful resources
to focus attention on.
And just one of the things I've
seen among Stanford students,
there's one other thing that I
find people tend to underuse,
which is trying to
talk to experts.
So if you are actually
a CTO of a startup,
trying to build this
for the first time,
I feel like, yeah, we all
want to do our own work
and not bother other
people, which is good.
But I just encourage you
to consider if after you've
done your own work, if
reach out to an expert,
can really accelerate
your learning.
So something I've often done
is I will do my own work.
I don't want to
call random experts
to try to bother them before
I've at least done my work.
But if you've-- sometimes,
I'm reading a paper,
I'm really struggling
to understand it.
And I find that instead of me
struggling for another like four
hours, if I send the authors a
respectful email, and say, hey,
I read your paper.
Try to understand this.
I'm still confused.
Can you help me out?
Can you explain this to me?
A lot of the time, including
when I was less well known.
But I think a lot
of people, if they
see that you're doing your
work and not just reaching out
to them before you've even
done anything, a lot of-- not
everyone, but a lot
of research authors
would actually be
quite understanding
and try to help you out.
And so I find that
for a lot of projects
I did, finding that one expert--
sometimes a Stanford
professor, actually, we
have a lot of speech faculty in
the Stanford faculty as well.
But when I had problems with
my speech recognition system,
sometimes I call Dan
Jurafsky, whatever.
And then a half hour
conversation or even a 10 minute
conversation really accelerates
what I've been able to do.
So I just encourage you to--
it takes you like 10
minutes to send an email,
and maybe there's a 50%
chance you chance to respond.
I don't know.
Not 100% chance.
But sometimes that tends
to be really high ROI.
And then what I
think you find is
that if you do a
literature search,
you will likely
discover that most
of the robust enterprise-grade
smart speaker systems, all
have a specialized system
trained to detect the wake word
or trigger word.
And again, there's a
variety of architectures.
You probably come up with
some good neural network
architectures for this.
And it turns out that there
is no data set on the internet
with lots of people
saying, Robert, turn on.
That's just not a thing.
So if you decide that the
names are Robert and Lenard,
and I don't know, Jeremy,
and Alicia, or whatever.
Sorry if there are people
of those real names.
It was actually kind of weird
when you chose people's names,
but we just do that
for some reason.
But it turns out that
there is no large data set
on the internet of lots of
people saying, Robert, turn on.
So if you want to
train a neural network
to detect if someone
has said this phrase,
you need to collect
that data yourself.
So let me then ask
you another question.
Say you've done a
literature search,
found some open source
code you can try,
but that has led
you, say, to conclude
that you need a data set of
people saying, Robert, turn on.
You need a data set to train
to distinguish between someone
saying, Robert, turn on versus
not someone saying, Robert,
turn on.
How would you approach
getting a data set like that?
Yeah.
Go for it.
[INAUDIBLE] text-to-speech.
Text-to-speech.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
Cool.
Yep.
You use text-to-speech
as one method.
I'll come back to that later.
So you need ideas.
Go ahead.
[INAUDIBLE]
Sorry.
Yeah.
Cool.
Yeah, I like that.
Yeah.
So walk around and ask people.
Tell them what you're doing.
Get the permission to
record and use their voice.
And if they're OK
giving permission,
just record their voices.
Yeah, I like that.
Anything else?
Cool.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
Step where it triggers.
Sorry.
[INAUDIBLE] sample.
We should have samples
where they're [INAUDIBLE]
and there's [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah, cool.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
Cool.
Yep.
So samples of people saying
not Robert or not people.
Yeah.
Cool.
Go ahead.
[INAUDIBLE] I would also have to
[INAUDIBLE] Robert [INAUDIBLE].
I see.
Cool Actually, [INAUDIBLE]
what you're saying, Robert,
but you don't want
that to be mistaken.
That's a good point.
I'll come back to that later.
Yes.
Do you want to say something.
[INAUDIBLE]
Same thing.
Interesting.
Cool.
Awesome.
Great.
All right.
So one of the--
yes, so I really like the idea
of just going around and asking
people for permission
to record their voices.
And by the way, in today's
world, privacy is important.
Consent is important.
So don't do anything
sneaky or weird.
Just tell people clearly
what you're doing.
Ask them for permission.
Make sure any permission
is freely given.
And if they don't give
permission, it's fine.
Move on.
They really respect
people's privacy.
That is really important.
Having said that, I find that
a lot of people in the world
are very nice.
Not everyone, but the vast
majority of people in the world
seem very nice.
And you ask them nicely.
I know this because
I've done this myself.
They will give permission for
you to provide their data.
And then just one of the framing
I encourage you to think about,
as always is the speed.
So how long will it take
you to wander around campus
or wander around San Francisco
and collect a sample of voices?
And I think you
actually get a lot done,
you'll get many dozens of
samples, maybe hundreds
of samples, easily in a day.
So I think those
are good tactics.
And then let me share
with you some things.
And then it turns
out synthetic data
using text-to-speech is
an interesting tactic.
I would usually not use that
as the first thing I do,
mainly because it
turns out, it's
hard to know how accurate
synthetic data is
compared to true natural data.
And maybe just show you
one thing I've run into.
I've actually done a
lot of synthetic data
for speech recognition.
One thing you have
to watch out for is
if you go to a lot of
synthetic sources of data,
how many voices, how many
different voices does it
provide?
And is it going to be a
pain to get enough diversity
in different people's voices?
So it turns out, I don't
know, for example, I often
talk to OpenAI voice on my
phone, instead of typing.
But the number of
voices there is limited.
And if you go to TTS
provider, I guess,
there are now some services
with a larger number of voices.
But these are things you
end up worrying about.
And it's all solvable.
Synthetic data does work
for speech recognition.
But it turns out that
there often enough details
associated with fiddling with
the synthetic data generation
process that that
ends up taking longer.
So for a lot of machine
learning applications,
using synthetic
data is a good idea.
And eventually, you
might get around to it.
But using synthetic
data is usually
not the first type of
data I would collect,
because usually, there are just
too many hyperparameters and too
many knobs you have
to worry about.
And then at the back of
your head, you're wondering,
what if there's something
weird about the synthetic data
that I've not thought of before?
And once you collect natural
data, collect real data,
it's just one less
thing to worry about.
Maybe just to tell
one more story,
not in speech, but
self-driving cars.
So if you're building
self-driving cars,
you want to detect other cars.
Where do you get
pictures of cars?
It turns out that
a lot of people
will have the idea oh, there
are lots of video games
with cars driving around.
Why don't we use video
games to get pictures
of cars out of the video game?
But it turns out a problem
with a lot of video games
is there could be 20 different
cars in the entire video game,
depends on the video game.
But it turns out that to
have a realistic video game,
you don't need 1,000
different cars.
And there are tons of different
cars designs on the road.
But you need a very
narrow set of cars.
And so to a human, seeing the
same 20 cars over and over,
looks like the road, looks fine.
The video game plays fine.
But for a lot of
video games, the data
just isn't rich enough
to capture anywhere
near the richness
of the real world.
Whereas in contrast, if
you got real pictures,
there's just one less
thing to worry about.
So I find that for
synthetic data, it works.
It's very valuable
to use it a lot,
but I usually get to it
only later in the process.
Make sense?
Cool.
So thank you.
And then in the interest of
building these things quickly,
let me share with you the types
of things that my teams have
done to collect data for this.
And I feel like when you
read research papers,
you take courses, often, you
get a very clean view of data.
I'm going to tell you about
one of the weird random hacks
that one of my teams
has used to build,
like a very serious, working
really well commercial system.
And at least as part of the
journey to do so, which is--
let's see.
So collected 100 training
audio clips and 25 development
set to tune too, and zero test.
One thing I'll often do if
my main goal is to just build
a system that works, as opposed
to publish a research paper,
is to not have a test set.
We just have a dev set that we
will tune the parameters to.
And if I want to publish
a research paper,
I probably need to
clean unbiased test set.
But if my goal is to just
build something and have
it work and ship it,
sometimes, I just say,
I'm not going to bother
to collect any test data,
just a training
set and a dev set.
And I'll just unapologetically
to my system, to the dev set.
And one thing you
could do is let's see.
So audio clips-- so audio is--
let's see.
So you may have seen
the audio waveforms.
[INAUDIBLE] this time.
X-axis is time.
And audio waveforms kind of
are these wiggly time series.
And sound is very rapid
vibrations in the air
that your ear
perceives as sound.
And what the
microphone does is it
records these very rapid
changes in air pressure.
So that's why you see all the
waveforms that look like this.
And so one thing that
one of my teams once did
was collect 100 samples
of audio waveforms,
where somewhere in the middle
of it is someone saying,
Robert, turn on.
So hey, how are you going?
Oh, yep.
And let's say, Robert, turn on.
And we can now talk
about some other things.
And so the phrase
Robert, turn on
takes about one second to say.
And one way to collect
construct a training set
would be to take a
three-second clip.
So this is where Robert,
turn on was said.
This is where they just
finished saying Robert, turn on.
And so if you collect 100
audio clips like this,
one way to turn this
into a training set
is to take these
long audio clips.
And then this becomes a training
example with a label one,
because that's an utterance
where the end of the utterance
corresponds to when
someone just finished
saying, Robert, turn on.
And in contrast, this
would be an example.
It would be a negative example.
And this two is a
negative example,
and this two is
negative example.
Does that make sense?
So given a say 10-second clip,
given 10 seconds of audio,
we will have cut out a phrase
where you get a positive label
if that three second audio
corresponds to someone just
finishing saying Robert, turn
on, which is when you should
turn on the lamp.
And anything else is labeled 0.
And so this is a
way to take, say,
100 training examples and turn
that into 3,000 binary examples.
So 100 audio clips.
Sorry.
I should say 100 audio clips.
And if we take 30
windows out of this,
then you can turn this into,
say, 3,000 training examples,
each with a binary 0 or 1 label,
that labels is this moment
in time when someone just
finished saying the phrase
Robert, turn on.
So it turns out that if you
do this, and we did do this,
then we wound up--
let's see.
We wound up with a system.
So we ran this and tested
this on the test set.
And we wound up with
a system that when
trained to predict
binary classification,
was 97% accurate.
But it turns out it did
this by outputting 0
all the time that
had 0 detections.
And so with this
training set, we
basically trained a very
large neural network
where I would have gotten
exactly the same result
with that one line
of Python code.
So this is the kind of stuff
that happens in real life.
And by the way, I'm sharing
these stories not just
to entertain you though,
hopefully you're entertained,
but because I think
it is by living
these experiences that you go,
oh, I could see this problem.
This is like I could
see this problem.
So my question to you is,
if you collected this data,
train the system, 97%
accuracy, isn't that fantastic?
But you realize that
you just implemented
a very huge neural network,
a print 0 statement,
or the equivalent of print
0 that has never finding
the phrase Robert, turn on.
What do you do next?
What's going On
[INAUDIBLE] Robert, turn on.
And so if we could [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah.
Cool.
Awesome.
So increase the
number of Robert,
turn ons in the
training example.
This is very unbalanced
And it did great by just saying,
I never hear this phrase.
How would you go about--
as you or anyone else,
how would you go about
increasing the number
of positive examples?
Go for it.
[INAUDIBLE]
But how do you do that?
We would [INAUDIBLE].
Audio as it is.
I see.
Wow.
Cool.
Yeah, interesting.
OK, yes.
That would work.
If that gets a
synthetic data again.
Which actually works.
And it also has all the
complexities of synthetic data.
But it turns out it does work.
So I know it works because
I've done that too.
I see.
Go ahead.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
Yep.
That works too.
So one thing you could do is
take your positive examples,
the examples of Robert,
turn on, and just
duplicate those
examples, or maybe just
give those examples more weight
to the training objective.
Yeah.
Any other ideas?
[INAUDIBLE] similar results.
Make an example of
the [INAUDIBLE].
Increase the
[INAUDIBLE] example.
Yeah.
Cool.
So a few variations of
synthetic [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah.
So I think the
easy things to try,
one would be to take the
examples and duplicate it.
Mathematically, this
is equivalent to taking
your positive examples and just
making multiple copies of that
in your training set.
It turns out that will work.
They'll largely solve it.
And by the way,
unbalanced data sets
is a common issue in
training neural networks.
I'll tell you the
rule of thumb I use.
And is many neural
networks are pretty
good at handling up to a 1 to 10
ratio of unbalanced data sets.
So people often worry what
if an unbalanced data set.
In this example, we
have a 1 to 30 ratio.
And your mileage may vary.
Sometimes it works, sometimes
it won't, and do that.
In this case, it didn't work.
But I find that if
you have a 1 to 2
ratio, just usually not
that worried about it.
Your network is fine
training like that.
Maybe up to 1 to
10 is when I start
to worry about it
being a little bit too
unbalanced for standard
training procedures
and what I might do
something to make it
a little bit more balanced.
But duplicating the examples
would be one tactic.
Go ahead.
What if you also feel
like [INAUDIBLE].
Yes.
Penalize false negatives.
Yes, that would work too.
So I think there are
a few ways to train--
to change the cost function.
You can give the positive
examples more weight or yes,
or penalizing false negative
would be another way
to change the cost function.
That will work.
OK.
Yeah.
Go ahead.
[INAUDIBLE] some
increase the amount
of the negative examples
of the [INAUDIBLE].
Yes.
So you can also decrease the
number of negative examples.
That would work too.
The one downside of that is--
like, it's OK.
I think it's fine
to do what you said.
The one slight
downside is if you
are reducing the diversity
of the negative examples,
then the neural network has just
a little bit less information
to learn from.
I think this is
what I just said.
There's a small
difference, though.
I think that will also work
as a quick thing to try.
Yeah.
And I'll just tell you another--
I'll tell you what
my team actually did.
And I'm telling you
this not because it's
a brilliant technique I'm
proud, but because I just
want to tell you the examples
of the types of hacks
that actual commercial
machine learning
teams do that actually works.
So I'll tell you what we did.
It was very close to duplicating
the positive examples,
but we had just a slightly
different variation,
which was we said that instead
of the positive example,
being the one window where
Robert, turn on, just finish.
So here, we're having a
sequence of labels walls,
where 0 corresponds to--
is that moment in time when
someone just finished Robert,
turn on.
And in the architecture
I describe,
we are detecting a very,
very narrow window in time
where someone just
finished Robert, turn on,
and you got to turn on.
But the hack that we
used was actually just
extend this out a little bit.
So instead of saying, did
someone just finished saying,
Robert, turn on in the
last 100 milliseconds,
we extended that out to
half a second or a second.
And so if someone
finished saying,
Robert, turn on any time
in the last half second,
let's turn on the light.
And so this actually generates
a few more training examples.
The reason we did
that, and again, this
is a small difference,
is this actually
creates a little
bit more diversity
in the positive examples
than just duplicating it.
Because now this red rectangle
is a positive example,
and so is this one, and so is
this one, and so is this one.
So it just creates a
little bit more diversity
in the positive examples.
I expect this would make a very
small difference in the training
and the learning
algorithms performance,
but it's just maybe
just slightly better
to have slightly--
yeah, cover the space
of positive examples
just a little bit.
Just a little bit better.
Make sense?
So again, just to keep
going with the story,
let's say you do this.
And now, you still do
well on the training set.
95% accuracy on training set.
But 50% accuracy, so not
good enough, on your dev set.
So you fix one problem
and another one comes up.
So what do you do next?
Go for it.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
Cool.
Awesome.
Yep.
Overfitting and [INAUDIBLE].
Go ahead.
[INAUDIBLE]
Is it the training set
distributions are not the same.
In this example, because we
collected the training and test
sets and we randomly shuffle
between training and dev,
then there would be the
same distribution, actually.
Yeah.
But sometimes there's
one other thing I do see,
which is it turns out early in
the history of machine learning,
there was always this
assumption or obsession
with making the training
set in a dev set.
And a test set have
the same distribution.
I think it's because if the
training set and a test set
are the same distribution,
it's easy to prove theorems,
easy to give guarantees,
whatever, kind
of academic machine learning.
There was always this
theoretical assumption,
which makes the theory work way
better than your training set.
And your test set come
from the same distribution.
It's just from a publishing
papers point of view,
that makes life much better.
From a practical point of view,
what I see is a lot of the time,
your training set
distribution is
just different than your
tested distribution.
That's just life.
Because it's hard to demand
data of a certain [INAUDIBLE].
And so for example,
one common thing
is if you do use synthetic data
generation, you can come up
with really clever ways to
generate synthetic training
data, like using TTS or
editing audio or whatever.
There, these techniques let you
generate a massive training set.
But the price of that
is your synthetic data--
I mean, that's not
how users talk.
Users don't speak
synthetic data.
They speak real data.
And so to make sure that
your test metric truly
reflects how users will
perceive your product,
I would put true data
in your test set.
And so you end up
with a lot of systems,
where your training
set distribution is
synthetic data or other
things you fit it with.
And then your test set is
whatever the world actually
cares more about.
And two distributions
is very different.
And then I think the
question you just
asked is, is the training
set distribution too
different from your
synthetic data.
That is a problem.
Those would be good
questions to ask.
All right.
So if you see this,
this is overfitting
because we're doing
great on training set,
not so well on dev.
So one thing to try would
be-- the first thing to try
is [INAUDIBLE] regularization.
So that would be a
good thing to try.
And then beyond
using regularization,
I find that for a lot of speech
problems, if you're overfitting,
getting more data is nice.
And so just to share with you--
I know your suggestion of
synthetic data earlier.
I'll share with you one
thing for synthetic data
that does work, which we
eventually wound up using,
which is it turns out that--
sorry, this is audio stream.
It turns out that
there are a lot of--
if you can get audio clips
of background noise--
so for example, in this
room, if I'm quiet,
we can hear a little bit
of air conditioning noise.
So a lot of rooms have
little background noise.
Or if you're near a highway,
there's a car in the background.
So there are
actually-- most people,
where they may use
the lamp, there's
a little bit of
background noise.
So if you're able to get
audio of background noise,
and then additionally record
some very clean audio clips
of Robert, turn on, it
turns out that if you
take two audio waveforms
and sum them together,
you end up with an
audio waveform that
sounds like someone saying this
in the presence of background
noise.
I think it's called the
superposition property of sound,
but basically sound
adds, which is
why if you take two
audio clips and you just
add the audio waveforms
together, then
you end up with an
audio recording that
sounds like both sounds
going on at the same time.
So we can do is take
background noise.
There's actually a lot of
audio clips of background noise
on YouTube as well, and so on.
Check the licensing terms
before you use stuff like that.
But there are actually
quite a lot of openly
licensed audio clips of
just someone like a quiet,
like a coffee shop
noise or someone
sitting in a house
studying or whatever.
And so if you can take some
background noise audio clips,
and then take a clean voice,
someone saying, Robert, turn on.
And if you add
these two together,
then you end up with
background noise,
Robert, turn on, and
more background noise.
And this becomes a positive
example using the process
that we talked about just now.
And if you have a handful
of clips of Robert, turn on,
and a lot of clips
of background noise,
so you can synthesize the
phrase Robert, turn on,
it means a lot of different
types of background noise
and create a prelaunch
training set.
It turns out one
problem with what I just
described is if you do
exactly what you just
said, you won't actually find
the Robert, turn on detector,
you end up with a voice
activity detection detector.
Because you have a lot
of background noise.
And anytime anyone
says anything,
the only thing people
say is Robert, turn on.
It's much easier to
just decide, is there
a loud sound, someone talking
to actually recognize things.
So the other thing
we should do is
instead of adding Robert,
turn on, pick a dictionary
or find other types of audio.
I think that's where you
had to come in just now.
Make sure don't
confuse other things.
And add, I don't know--
get someone to say the word
cardinal, or
whatever, other words.
So you have a bunch of
examples of people saying words
other than Robert, turn on, and
then also a bunch of examples,
people saying, Robert, turn on.
And by having a handful of clean
recordings of Robert, turn on,
and a handful of clean
recordings of people saying
other stuff and synthesizing
a data set like this,
you can get a data set with many
thousands of examples of Robert,
turn on pretty efficiently.
And if you train a
neural network on this,
you get a decent wake word
or trigger word detector.
That makes sense?
Yeah.
So with a process like this--
so this is what working on
a machine learning project
feels like.
You try something,
it doesn't work.
You find out that you
have a skewed data set.
Be creative in how you
create and collect data.
You may find a skewed data set.
It just doesn't work.
You may find this overfitting.
And I find that
it is the ability
to drive iterations on a system
that determines how quickly you
can get something to work.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
How would you sample
[INAUDIBLE] differentiate
between X and [INAUDIBLE].
For the Robert, turn on example?
Yeah.
So if I found that there were a
lot of users that are listening
to music, then I would
probably synthesize data
with music in the
background, and then have
someone say, Robert, turn on.
So if you think a lot
of users listen to music
and there's our
desk lamp and you
want to make sure we catch
them saying, Robert, turn on,
then I would probably
synthesize more training data
to include loud-ish
music in the background.
[INAUDIBLE] music
that you can't really
predict [INAUDIBLE] be
vastly different even more.
So one of the genre of music?
Like classical
music, [INAUDIBLE]
which you don't know what they
use, [INAUDIBLE] and then you
train different genres
of music [INAUDIBLE].
It's extremely different.
Yeah.
So it turns out
that if you have--
I feel like as a
rule of thumb, if you
can have a more diverse
set of training data,
it's usually better.
So maybe I'm not sure
what music my user
base likes to listen the most.
Is it classical?
Is it rock?
Is it EDM?
Is it whatever?
If you could collect
a very rich training
set that includes all of
the above, and even more,
usually they'll do better
than going to narrow
and risking picking wrong.
And the one asterisk
to what I said
is so long as you can train
a neural network that's
big enough, usually,
more diverse data.
More data, more
diverse data is better.
If you're neural
network is too small,
then it may lack the
capacity or the intelligence
to memorize all
this stuff, which
could be a problem if you
need a very small network that
runs at the edge.
But usually, if you
have the capacity
to get more rich, more
diverse training data,
that ends up delivering
better results.
That makes sense?
Cool.
All right.
Now I want to share with you--
so it turns out when you're
building a machine learning
system, very common experience
is you try something
and it doesn't work.
And then you have to figure
out all the wonderful ways
it could be not working,
and then go and fix
whatever is not working.
And even in this
example we went through,
is the training data too skew?
Is it overfitting?
So you need [INAUDIBLE]
regularization or more data,
or is it something else.
Or the synthetic
data distribution not
match the real
data distribution.
It turns out that when you're
training a neural network, when
you're training-- when
your building AI system,
it's really difficult
to know in advance
what's going to go wrong next.
I find that in
software development,
if I'm writing
traditional software,
you kind of control
all the code.
And so it's more OK to write a
spec and then you just build it
and then it kind of works
as soon as you debug it.
But the bugs are it's
like my own bugs.
In contrast, when you're
building a machine
learning system, it's much
more like I don't what's
going to happen next.
Maybe because I don't what
the data will give me,
how to predict, how the
algorithm will perform.
And so the workflow
of machine learning
feels much more like
debugging than development.
And by debugging, I
mean, there is a process
where you build a system and
you just repeatedly trying
to find how it doesn't
work and fix it.
If you're trying to do a
task that humans can do,
then the bugs or the
gaps in performance
is often, whatever a
human can clearly do,
but the AI system
is unable to do.
So for many machine learning
teams that have led or worked
in, if you can get the team to a
healthy rhythm of this debugging
cycle, you can make
really rapid progress.
So for example, it turns
out-- let me give one example.
I've been on teams where
we would do the following.
We say morning,
afternoon, evening, night.
So we run our training
jobs at night.
And for example, it turns
out for some of these models,
we're training for
speech recognition.
And it takes, let's say,
it takes four hours.
So the training job
takes about four hours
to train a neural network.
So training at night.
In the morning, we
look at our results.
You look at the results,
do error analysis,
try to figure out what's wrong.
And the afternoon, we
write code to figure out
how we're going to fix
whatever thing we discovered
the day before.
And then in the evening,
right before we go home,
we launch the training job.
And then it runs overnight.
And the next morning, we do
it again and again and again.
And it turns out that if you
can fix one problem a day,
that's actually pretty good.
And then you saw me walk
through three or four problems.
When I built this for
real, there are slightly
more problems than that.
But I find that if you can
get a team into a cadence
where you train stuff, look
at the results, figure out
is this bias variance
data mismatch--
actually, this should
be code or get data.
Fix it.
And then the evening, before
you go home, launch the job.
Maybe if you have time
evening, just maybe
the training job a little bit,
which is still running, but then
come back in the next
morning to see how it did.
Then you just do
this over and over.
And you can make
really rapid progress.
And I find this often,
this discipline,
that lets you make progress.
In contrast, the teams
that kind wake up
and they go, what do we do next?
Let's call a meeting
this afternoon.
Wait, where's the data?
OK.
I guess we'll meet tomorrow
to look at the data.
And then oh,
[INAUDIBLE] is down.
And teams like that
move much slower
than the really
disciplined teams that
just keep on rolling forward.
And one more observation.
It turns out that
iteration cycle sometimes
is driven by this.
So I've worked on
machine learning jobs
where it took us about four
hours to train a model.
And for us, it's long enough.
Don't want to wait for it.
But running overnight
is just fine.
I've also worked on teams, where
a typical training job took
about three weeks on average.
And so if it takes three weeks
to train a neural network
for a particular type of
model we're working on,
then the pacing
is very different.
So how long it takes to
train a neural network really
drives the pacing of this.
Where sometimes we would
launch a training job and then
hope for the best.
We would monitor it
during those two weeks.
It's not that we do nothing
for those two weeks,
but you just got to
launch the training job.
And then frankly, hope that
it works three weeks later.
But we take three weeks.
And after that, tons of
analysis and debugging,
whatever work that would
take us one to two weeks
to set us up for the
next training job.
They're going to take us another
three weeks to get a result.
And then we're
also parallelizing.
While launching this job,
we're analyzing the result
from a previous job,
and we launch a few jobs
asynchronously.
But I find that
how long it takes--
this is a huge driver
for how you do this.
The other end of the
spectrum is if it
takes 10 minutes to
train a neural network,
then that's wonderful.
You just train it, get a
result, train it, get a coffee,
come back, then do the analysis.
And then the bottleneck is how
quickly can you analyze the data
and get more data.
So this really drives the
design of this process.
And one of the
things that happens
is for a lot of
projects, you start off
with a small thing that
takes 10 minutes to train.
But then as you get more and
more data, then you're bigger,
But now it takes four hours to
train because you're bigger.
Then it takes two
weeks to train.
It's like, oh, now this thing
takes a month and a half
to train.
So I've experienced
that as well,
where unfortunately,
as a performance climb,
we decided we had to train
bigger and bigger models
with more and more data.
And then it went from this
really fantastic 10-minute
iterations to these
month long iterations.
But they just had to be done
because we were training
bigger and bigger networks.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE] as you get into
the model, you see a problem,
you have to stop the
model or [INAUDIBLE].
We probably didn't stop
the model that much.
So sometimes you can
look at checkpoints.
And if you see that
for some reason--
so actually, if you're
training like a three-week job,
you expect the performance
to be at a certain level
after a couple of
days or after a week.
And if it's way off, then before
burning another two weeks,
you may ask, is my learning
rate clearly wrong?
Or maybe this new data set
we try is clearly wrong.
So you can actually start
to run some analyzes
on the checkpoints.
And sometimes, we would yank
the job and just kill it.
I would say that
happened very rarely.
Yeah.
OK.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yes.
So once you learn about--
the online videos is
transfer learning.
We train a large data
set and then maybe
fine tune on just a
much smaller data set.
And then if your process of fine
tuning, a much smaller data set
takes half an hour,
then that's great.
Then you can also drive
much faster iterations
based on that half hour, the
limiting factor for the training
time.
Cool.
All right.
One reason I obsess
about speed is because.
it turns out that
if the x-axis--
imagine you're building a
startup to launch this product.
I find that if a team takes
twice as long to do it,
they're just much less
competitive in the marketplace.
So here's what I mean.
So if this is error
and this is months,
there's some machine
learning systems
that we work on for months to
keep on trying to improve it.
And if this is you.
And if a competitor, say,
it takes twice as long
to reach the same
level of performance.
So instead of taking
this long to get here,
they take this long to get here.
Instead of taking
this long to get here,
they take twice as
long to get here.
So if a competitor
kind of does that.
It just takes twice as long.
They take two days instead
of one day to do something.
But it always takes
two days to do what
you would take one day to do.
Then the performance over
time looks like this.
And what the customer
cares about is
a certain moment in time is you
are so much better than them.
So these two
differences in speed
really translates into
massive difference
in the performance of your
system versus someone else's
system in the marketplace.
And I find that the fast moving
teams are just so much more
effective.
And you might think,
yeah, I took two days.
They took one day.
What's the big deal?
The big deal is not
that your day slow.
The big deal is you're
two times slower.
And it's very-- just
in the marketplace,
it's just not competitive
if you take twice as long
for some applications.
OK.
All right.
There's one other
example I want to cover.
Let me try to do that quickly.
So what I've talked about so far
is speech recognition, your wake
word detection, which is more
of an end-to-end deep learning
system, where your input
audio goes to neural network.
And in this outputs, is
this RTo, Robert, turn on.
So the entire system
you're trying to build
is just a single neural network.
For a lot of
applications you build,
you end up building pipelines
or sometimes call them cascades.
I'm going to use
the term pipelines.
You saw one example
of this last time,
where to detect people coming
up to unlock a door with face
recognition, we had video that
fed to visual activity detection
to see if anyone is
even in front of it.
And then that fed to the
neural network to recognize,
is this an authorized person.
And then 0 or 1 to say,
is this a person that we
should unlock the door for.
What I want to do is
use a different example
of a pipeline of an AI
[INAUDIBLE] researcher.
So it turns out
that all of the--
I think all of the leading--
well, almost all of the
leading LLM providers
have deep researches,
where you can ask a query
or go and search the internet,
look at a lot of web pages
and come back and synthesize
a very thoughtful report.
But I actually use the OpenAI
researcher quite a lot.
I know some of the
team that built it,
and it's really well built.
I think some others also
did a good job.
You input a query like--
this is example I'm taking from
the agentic AI course online.
But if the query, show me the
latest research on Black holes,
some query like that.
And then One thing you
might do is take a query
like whatever Black
hole research.
And then use an LLM.
Use a large language model
to generate search terms
to feed to a web search engine.
So may generate a few
terms like black hole
research, latest in astronomy
and black holes or whatever.
So generate a handful
of search terms.
This, then, call out
to a web search engine,
be it Safari, Google,
DuckDuckGo, Bing.
I don't know.
I use [INAUDIBLE] quite a
lot, but then multiple--
actually more and more
web search engines
designed for AI rather than
for humans, which I think
is pretty neat.
So this can call the
web search engine,
and then fetch the top URLs.
Sorry.
I mean, fetch the top
pages and then top URLs.
So the web search
engine returns 10 pages.
You may not want to
fetch all 10 of them.
You can read the
snippets, decide
which ones are most relevant.
Again, maybe with an LLM
with a large language model,
to decide what are the
pages you want to download.
So just like a human,
do a web search.
I won't click every single link.
I'll take a glance
at it and decide
which ones I want to click.
So identify and
fetch the top URLs,
and then feed all
that into writing.
And this gives the final output.
So this is a-- by the way,
this is a more traditional
deep researcher article.
So deep researcher architecture.
The more modern deep
research architectures
let the system decide when
to do more web search, when
to fetch more web pages, and
more autonomous, more agentic.
But this is what the
early deep researcher
architectures look like.
There's more of a
linear pipeline.
There are more
modern architectures
where system will
fetch some pages
and autonomously decide,
do I need to go back
and do more research and so
on, what topics and iterate
a few times.
But this would be a pretty
decent basic deep researcher.
And it turns out
that if you actually
built this, in the speech
recognition system, Robert,
turn on lamp example,
we talk a lot
about how to improve
one component, which
is the neural network.
If you have a
pipeline like this,
the other thing you need to do,
which is critically important,
is to decide of all the
different components
in the pipeline,
which one do you want
to focus your attention on.
So I find that one
thing that makes
a huge difference in
a team's performance
is, again, being able to drive a
disciplined evaluation and error
analysis process to
decide what to work on.
I find that a lot
of machine learning
is not wildly doing
things to see what works.
It's actually a very thoughtful,
very disciplined process,
where the system, maybe it's
not doing as well as we wish.
So we should look
at it to decide.
It turns out lots of
things could be wrong.
Is it generating search terms
that aren't quite right?
Or maybe we're
using a web search
engine that is returning
results that aren't that good.
So for example, is my web search
engine comprehensive enough
or is it just maybe I
picked a lower cost web
search service or
something that's just not
returning the latest materials?
It turns out for some
internet articles,
many web search engines
will do really well.
But if you ever want to fetch
news, really fresh news,
there's actually a lot of
difference in the performance.
Some web search
engines are much better
at having really fresh content.
Some just don't
update as frequently.
So do I need to switch
web search engines?
Or am I successfully
identifying the best web pages
to fetch So if I have
black hole signs,
I think nasa.gov is very,
very authoritative web page.
But if a web search
engine returns,
I don't know,
bobsbackyardastronomyblog.com.
That's less authoritative
than nasa.gov.
Am I correctly fetching the
most authoritative scientific
articles versus
whatever is hyped up?
Or maybe am I fetching a
lot of random TikTok videos,
rather than released scientific,
authoritative things?
And then lastly, given
all this information,
am I writing a thoughtful
article with an LLM
from a final research output.
So it turns out that with
a pipeline like this,
there are lots of steps
that could go wrong.
And your ability to decide
what is the component,
you should focus your effort
on, that's a massive driver
of your productivity and
improving a system like this.
And the good news
is there's actually
one other thing I've seen.
Sometimes I've seen a
few experienced machine
learning people.
It's actually one
thing I've seen.
Sometimes a team will
build a system like this.
And if it's a less experienced
team, they build system.
It's not quite working.
Trying to decide
what to do next.
One thing I've
seen many times is
if you get a few senior machine
learning people around--
at Stanford, I've seen
this quite a few times.
Sometimes the students
done a project,
maybe build a system like this.
If you get a few
experienced professors
to look at the system,
you find that our opinions
on what to do next, there's
remarkably little variance.
So you find that many
experienced AI people look at it
and go, well, based on what
it seems, we think this
is a problem or this is wrong.
You should try this.
It's not that we always
agree with each other 100%
but the variance is much
less than you might think.
And to me, I think there's
a methodology behind how
to approach these problems.
Whereas the variance
and what to try next
among less experienced
engineers is much larger.
So to me, I think
there's actually--
if you have a systematic way of
doing error analysis to figure
out where it's actually
underperforming
experienced people, all kind
of-- doesn't mean experience
people are always right,
but it's just low variance.
But there really
is a methodology
to figure out what to do next.
And one of the key
ideas is error analysis.
And I talk about this
online videos as well.
But this is so important.
Let me just go through.
And one thing to do is to
look at the outputs of each
of these intermediate steps.
And it's one of these things.
I'll say it.
You probably even
agree it's a good idea.
But the percentage of
people that actually do it
when the time comes are found
to be far lower than 100%.
But that's just take
a handful of queries.
Is it latest in
black hole science
or should I rent or buy
an apartment or help me
make fun plans for a weekend
in Santa Cruz or whatever.
Some handful of queries
for a researcher.
And then look at what
search terms it generates
and see if it makes sense.
Look at the web pages it
fetches, see if they look good.
Look at the top pages
in fetch and see
if the top web pages
selected is similar
or materially different
than what you would pick.
My example, what if
this decides to fetch
bobsbackyardastronomypage.com
rather than nasa.gov.
And you go, OK, maybe I need
to change how to do that.
And then also look at
the final writing to see,
given this source
articles, is it
writing the
appropriate articles?
And what I find is for
a process like this,
it turns out error analysis
is often a very manual process
because when the system
isn't performing,
error analysis or
gap analysis is often
a manual process of
figuring out what
a human would do that is better
than what the AI system would
do.
And we're trying to inject
knowledge from the human
into the AI system.
So because the AI doesn't
have this knowledge yet,
usually you, do need a
human time to do this.
And people are talking about
automating some of this
and maybe there'll
be progress there.
So far I find error analysis.
It just takes
human to look at it
and have the insights
into where AI system is
doing something different than
the expert human would be.
And as that insight
that then points you
in the direction for
how to improve it.
And so often, I would
build a spreadsheet
like this, where I have a
query that is black hole size.
And then another one.
Do I rent versus buy in
whatever in San Francisco
or weekend activities
in Santa Cruz, whatever.
Just have, I don't
know, maybe up to 100.
I find that I often
have patients look it
up to 100 examples beyond 100.
Sometimes more than
100, but it's somewhere
between 10 and 100.
Have a list of queries
and have a list of steps.
And so the steps
would be search terms.
What's that?
Web search.
Fetch pages.
So this is what it feels
like to do error analysis.
It is a labor-intensive
process because this
is a process of identifying
where a human outperforms
AI to try to close the gap.
We just do this over and over.
So what I would do
is I would sit down,
often with a spreadsheet in
front of me open like this.
And I will run
black hole science
through the whole
system, and then
just read all the search
terms satisfactory.
And if I'm not an expert
in black hole science,
I need to get an expert or do a
bit of work to figure that out.
But if I find that the search
terms to send to a web search
engine are completely
satisfactory,
then I'll just say,
OK, this looks good.
Then, given those
search terms, I'll
look at the web search
results and say,
did the web search engine
retrieve reasonable things?
And it looks good, then great.
And then I'll look at, did
my system, maybe an LLM,
did it make a good choice
in the top web pages
to actually go and fetch?
And maybe I found
this retrieving--
it chose to retrieve Bob's
backyard astronomy blog,
but skipped nasa.gov,
then I'll say,
OK, there's a problem there.
And then I'll [INAUDIBLE] make
a note, Bob, instead of NASA,
just take notes on
what you're seeing.
And then I'll say, given these
sources, is this writing, OK?
Maybe it's OK.
And then the process is to
take a handful somewhere
between 10, 20, and
100 of articles, where
the performance is subpar.
And it's called error
analysis, because I
want to focus on where
it's underperforming.
So there's some articles where
it's doing a great job on.
I would tend to pay
less attention to those.
But I'll focus on finding
anywhere from 10, 20,
to 100 queries, whereas
clearly underperforming what
I think a human should be doing
or what I hope this will do.
And then going
through to just try
to get a sense of how often the
hot spots are in different parts
of the pipeline.
And so maybe for
rent versus buy,
I might say, boy, this is really
authoritative blogger that
talks about this, but
somehow web search misses.
I don't know.
Maybe I'm using the
wrong web search engine.
We can, in Santa Cruz, buy into
some hyped up tourist things
rather than actually finding
locally interesting web
pages and so on.
And then by doing this,
20, 30, 50 queries,
you can then start to
get a sense of where
the hot spots are.
So again, all of these
are subpar results.
I'm focusing on queries
where the performance is not
good enough.
And then if I find that--
I don't know, 40% of
the time is failing
to fetch the top web
pages, only 5% of the time
is failing to do that.
Sorry.
Let me find that
70% of the time,
I'm really not happy with this.
5% of time, web search
is not good enough.
Maybe 20% of the time,
search terms are wrong.
And maybe 20% of the time, the
writing is not good enough.
So these all have
to add up to 100%.
Sometimes you have problems
in more than one column.
But if this is what it turns
out to be, then we'll go,
well, clearly a lot of my
dissatisfaction results
is because it's just not
choosing good pages from the web
search to return.
So let me go focus on that.
And the thing about a lot
of machine learning systems
is if you don't do this
analysis ahead of time
in terms of what
component to focus on.
And so I find that
the teams that
know how to drive this
process systematically.
And it sometimes takes us hours.
Ever heard that
daily schedule thing?
Sometimes it takes us a few
hours to go through this process
and reach conclusions.
But then the benefit
of spending whatever,
three or four hours
on this, is that it
can save you weeks of otherwise
heading in the wrong direction.
So teams can drive this evals
and error analysis process
in a very methodical way.
You are much better at picking
what direction to work in.
And that allows your
team to go way faster.
And this is way more
than a 2X difference.
I've actually
literally visited teams
that have been working on
something for six months
and go like, gee, I could
have told you six months ago
this wasn't going to cut it.
And imagine if this
was the problem,
we're not writing
the right web pages.
But for some reason, the
team kept on trying out
different web search engines.
Maybe there's someone trying
to sell a new web search
service to you.
So you spend a lot of
time with the sales team,
do a lot of integration
with your website.
There's actually more web
services than most people.
And I actually swap between
them whenever I feel like it.
So imagine, you
spend all your time
trying to come up with a
better web search service
for six months.
It's entirely possible.
It just won't move the needle
for the overall performance,
which is why this type
of error analysis process
is so important.
I walk through this with
the example of one pipeline.
The online videos go through
other examples as well.
But both are building
deep learning pipelines
and for AI agentic pipelines.
I think this is a very
important concept to master.