What I want to do today is
give an overview of this class.
I'm actually curious
before we get started.
This is now September 2025.
How many of you just
started at Stanford?
Raise your hand.
Wow.
Cool.
Awesome.
So others, pay attention to
who just raised their hands
and do say hi to
them and help welcome
all of the people
that just joined
Stanford in whatever program.
CS230 is a class that we offer
in the flipped classroom format.
And what that means is
that instead of listening
to me or Kian, my co-instructor
that you meet next week,
instead of listening to us
lecture at you for an hour, hour
20 minutes, or
whatever, we'll actually
ask you to watch
a lot of the video
lectures online so
that we can then
make use of the precious
in-classroom time for much
richer, deeper discussions.
So both today and for
the entire quarter,
I would really warmly welcome
anyone raising questions,
raise your hand.
And in fact, I find that
instead of you sitting there--
oh, and even though with
a longer session schedule
by the registrar,
we'll use usually
only up to an hour and 20
minutes for this course.
And the goal is to--
it turns out that a lot
of Stanford students
were watching the
lectures on Seagull,
on the online videos anyway.
So rather than us delivering
that same lecture year
after year, we put
a lot more effort
to put very high quality
lecture videos online
and we'll ask you to just watch
that online, which people are
doing anyway, but just highly
edited for offline watching
and spend a classroom
time doing the things that
make sense for us to get
together in-person to.
So because you haven't watched
any of the lectures yet,
or I assume most
of you have not,
today we'll even maybe have
a slightly shorter session
to introduce the class, talk
about logistics, and so on.
As many of you
know, deep learning
is one of the latest,
hottest trends technologies
of computer science and AI.
If we look at, say our PhD
admissions or even master's
admissions, a very
large fraction
of all students that
come to Stanford
or applying to come to
Stanford want to work on AI.
I'm not sure if I'm
allowed to say the numbers,
but they are extremely
high, as you can imagine.
And so my goal and my
co-instructor Kian's goal,
our collective goal,
is through this quarter
to help you get to near or at
pretty much state of the art
with regard to deep learning
and make sure that all of you
walk away from this class
highly skilled at applying
deep learning.
And so it turns out
that a lot of progress
in AI over the
last, I don't know,
decade, maybe 10, 15
years, was made by scaling.
And one of the reasons why
deep learning was so successful
was because it's good at
absorbing a lot of data.
So if I draw a figure
where on the x-axis
I plot the amount of data
we have for a problem,
then using more traditional
machine learning algorithms, so
logistic regression,
maybe decision trees,
but using all the generations of
AI machine learning algorithms,
as you gave it
more and more data,
the performance or the
accuracy of the more
traditional algorithms
would plateau.
It was as if--
So take speech recognition.
With all the generations
of algorithms,
even as you fed it more and more
data, hundreds and thousands
and tens of thousands
of hours of speech data,
the accuracy would
often plateau and it
was as if the older
generations of algorithms
didn't what to do with all
the data that we now have.
But what we start to find
about 10, 15 years ago
was that if you train a small
neural network, also known
as a small deep learning model,
its performance would maybe
get better and better.
And if you train a
medium-sized one,
and if you train a very
large neural network,
the performance just keeps
getting better and better.
And I think the reason that deep
learning has dominated the AI
scene for the last
10, 15 years is
because there is a
recipe for training
very large neural networks
that we could then
shove a lot of data
into the results
in exceptional performance.
So I think we started to see
this because of, frankly,
some Stanford research papers
about 15 years ago when
we did the first early work
on using CUDA programming
and GPUs to scale
up deep learning.
Oh, by the way, actually,
it's one fun fact.
My first GPU machine used
to train neural networks
using CUDA, which is a
controversial thing at the time.
It was built by a Stanford
undergrad in his dorm room.
His name was Ian Goodfellow.
But I think that compute
server, built in the Stanford
undergrad dorm room,
allowed us at Stanford
to lay the early foundations
of using CUDA, at that time
a modern language
for training GPUs
to train large neural networks.
And then obviously, that
influenced a lot of people
and helped scaling up
deep learning take off.
So I tell that story
because sometimes the work
that some of you can do in a
dorm room or graduate student
housing or whatever, or
in a lab at Stanford,
looking back over
some number of years,
it can really have
a huge impact.
And maybe in this
class, some of you
will do work as impactful
as that someday as well.
But so what you
start to find was
that as we train larger
and larger neural networks,
they could soak up
lots of data and drive
exceptional performance.
And then there was a
research paper out of Baidu,
which showed that as you scale
up neural networks, as you scale
up deep learning algorithms, the
performance gains are actually
quite predictable.
So you can forecast, if
you buy this many GPUs,
throw this compute and
this much data at it,
what would the performance be?
And then later, OpenAI
popularized the idea
with a really influential
paper on scaling laws.
And that predictability of
how deep learning gets better
in performance then drove
a lot of the investments
in data centers and building
very large AI models
with lots of data.
And so let's see.
In terms of where this class
sits, so in computer science,
all of us build on
each other's work.
A lot of the way that computer
science and AI has made progress
is we build on
top of other ideas
that are, in turn, build
on top of other ideas
that in turn build on
top of other ideas.
So maybe I want to give you a
little map to show you maybe
where deep learning sits.
So I think there are--
machine learning is built
on top of computer science.
So I think it's actually helpful
to learn CS fundamentals.
And even though I
use and I suspect
vast majority use
AI-assisted coding,
be it tools like Cloud Code
or Gemini CLI, or OpenAI
Codex, or Cursor, or
Windsurf, or whatever,
I find that people that know
CS fundamentals, that really
understand computer science,
that really understand how
computers work, rather than
I'm going to vi code this,
when you understand
CS fundamentals,
you get things to
work much better.
But on top of CS
fundamentals, there's
a set of machine
learning skills.
So how do you build algorithms
that can learn from data?
And then deep learning
is a special type
of machine learning.
Well, that's really the most
effective type of machine
learning, as far as
I can tell, in which
we train neural
networks, we train
certain types of
algorithms to learn
from large amounts of data.
So far in the last
10 minutes, you've
probably heard me use
the words deep learning
and neural networks.
And I think today
those two terms
are almost interchangeable.
Some purists will insist on
some technical differences.
For all practical purposes,
they mean the same thing.
But what happened was the term
neural networks had been around
for decades, but around 10 or
15 years ago, a number of us
realized that deep learning, it
was just a much better brand.
And so even though
neural networks
have been around for decades,
starting about 10, 15 years ago,
it was deep learning
that took off,
because who doesn't want
learning that is really deep?
It's just a good brand.
But you hear me use those
terms interchangeably.
But deep learning
algorithms, neural networks,
they give us a way to take
advantage more and more and more
compute capacity so they
can build very large AI
models with a lot of
parameters to soak up
the large amounts of data to
get more and more intelligent
or to make better and
better predictions,
or to generate more
and more accurate
outputs using the large amount
of data that's available to us.
Ever since I was a
teenager, my mom's
been trying to convince
me to stop mumbling,
but now, many years later,
I still struggle with that.
So I'll try my best.
So please, wave at me or let me
if I start to drift lower again.
Yeah, all right.
I think my mother would
be very happy to have
to practice like this now.
All right.
So CS fundamentals, machine
learning, deep learning,
and then the recent
generative AI revolution.
Generative AI-- sorry,
bad handwriting.
Generative AI, which
is mostly built
by a specific type
of neural network
called the transformer
neural network, which
you learn about in this class.
You actually learned what is
the transformer architecture
later in this quarter
as well, is in turn
built on top of deep learning.
So I assume all of
you are regularly
prompting LLMs, large
language models,
to help you get work done.
And what I find is that while
I use LLMs all the time,
for a lot of applications,
just prompting LLMs,
it doesn't cut it.
There are a lot of things
that I cannot get to work just
by prompting an LLM.
And so I'll often have
to go a layer deeper
into the deep learning
layer of abstraction
and fill it with deep
learning algorithms
in order to get
certain things to work.
And in fact-- so what
this class covers
is we'll try to make
sure that you are expert,
near-expert in deep learning
by the end of this class,
but we'll also dip a little bit
into machine learning concepts.
We'll talk a lot about objective
functions and tips and tricks
for optimizing parameters
in efficient way.
And then we'll also actually
reach up a little bit
to cover some GenAI.
In particular, we'll talk about
what is the transformer network?
And then through this
quarter, Kian and I
will also chat a little
bit about the job landscape
as it relates to GenAI
and deep learning,
and how deep learning is
enabling certain types of AI
applications.
OK.
I have more to say
about this, but let
me just pause for a second and
see if you have any questions.
Yeah, go for it.
Did you say machine learning is
a prerequisite to this course?
Oh, good question.
What I say?
Congratulations.
You've won the prize for
the first question asked
in CS230 2035, so well done.
[APPLAUSE]
Yeah.
So is machine learning
a prereq to this course?
Not really.
So I think two common entry
points to AI at Stanford
are CS--
well, a few common entry points
are CS129, CS229, and CS230.
If you don't know
any machine learning,
this course may end up
going a little bit fast,
may seem like it's going a
little bit fast in the first,
I don't know, two
or three weeks,
but some people do pick
things up quickly that way.
And maybe actually--
So a few courses that
you may hear about.
So 129 is a relatively
easy entry point
into machine learning that
tends to-- it takes a longer
time to go through the core
concepts of machine learning.
Like, what's the
optimization objective?
How do you implement
gradient descent?
What is logistic regression?
What's a very basic
neural network?
So this is a relatively
applied easiest of this list.
CS229, which I'm also
involved in co-teaching,
is much more mathematical and
theoretical, very high-paced,
very intense, and
very mathematical.
And this is less applied
than 129 and 230,
but this will go over a lot
more of the theory and the math
derivations behind machine
learning algorithms.
So, for example, if you want
to learn how to do calculus
not using real
numbers, but calculus
using matrices and vectors,
that's a bunch of, I don't know,
mildly complex math
that's worth knowing.
CS229 goes over that.
CS230, this class, is
relatively applied,
and it focuses just
on deep learning.
So of all the machine
learning-- there
are a lot of machine
learning algorithms
out there, supervised
learning, unsupervised
learning, a lot of machine
learning algorithms out there.
And many, many of
them are very useful
and so they're all
worth learning about.
But of all the machine
learning algorithms out there,
the one category that is
most useful that's taking off
the most is deep learning, and
this class focuses just on that,
but the other arm is also
worth learning about.
So 129 is the easiest on-ramp.
But if you've done
either 229 or 230,
I would probably skip
129 at that point.
But if you are getting started,
there are multiple on-ramps.
Yeah.
If we take 229 and 230 together,
do you think it's redundant?
Oh, yeah.
Can you take 229
and 230 together?
Yeah, thank you.
Prize for the second question.
All right.
If you want to clap,
sure, go for it.
[APPLAUSE]
Yes, you can take CS230
and CS229 together.
We designed the two curricula
to be relatively low in overlap.
So the very small amount of
overlap between these two.
We won't clap for every
single question, but go ahead.
Are you going to cover more
recent deep learning algorithms
that are used in recent
LLM developments,
like five or two more?
Yeah, so when we cover the
recent LLM developments,
we will touch on the transformer
neural network, but not
the latest LLM variations
in this course.
I think a lot of
it, it turns out
that when you go out to
get a job, well, maybe,
if assuming you go
and work in industry,
the number of people training
LLMs is actually very small.
Some of those jobs tend
to be incredibly well-paid
so we hear about very high
salaries in the news media,
but the vast majority
of application builders
end up sometimes working
the GenAI level, not that
often training a
transformer from scratch,
but then often using deep
learning tools as well.
So maybe one example, something
that many of my teams have done
is we have trained
transformer models--
foundation models from scratch
with relatively small ones
in, say, startups.
But one thing we
do do quite a lot
is take a pre-trained
transformer network
and then engineer our own
data to further fine tune it.
Sorry if I'm using words you
may not totally understand,
pre-trained, fine-tuned, you'll
know what all those terms
are by the end of this quarter.
So those are things that
we actually do day-to-day.
This is important for
getting a bunch of products
to work so you will gain
the foundations needed
to do the type of
work in this course.
One thing we don't
do is talk a lot
about how to train the largest
cutting edge transformer
networks.
I think that is a very
important skill set,
is relatively
niche one for which
some people are getting
paid really, really well,
but the number of people
doing that in the world
is actually small, whereas
the number of people
building applications with this
set of skills is very large.
Do you have any courses
that you cover that?
Do I have any courses
covering that?
I think Percy Liang was
thinking about doing something,
but I don't remember he's
doing it this quarter.
Few people are thinking about
doing something like that.
Yeah.
Go ahead.
This is a question
about the course itself.
Do you know about what
the portion of the course
is going to involve.
mathematical analysis
and multiple coding?
So just repeating for the
mic for the home viewers,
what portion is coding
versus what proportion
is mathematical analysis?
This course is
relatively math light.
Sorry, maybe that was
too strong a statement,
but I think this course
is very practical.
I remember many
years back, I was
speaking with a mathematician
and we're just chatting
and he was asking--
he was just talking
about his career, why
he chose to be a mathematician.
And I still remember,
he had stars in his eyes
when he told me that he chose
his career path because he felt
his role is to pursue truth
and beauty in the universe,
and that's why he
became a mathematician.
In this course, I'm not going to
do any truth and beauty stuff.
Truth and beauty
is good, but you
find that I want to take a very
practical approach to talking
about how to build applications
and build software that works.
Yeah.
Cool.
Anything else?
All right.
Cool.
Awesome.
All right.
Thank you for all the questions.
Please keep them coming.
And feel free to interrupt me or
Kian throughout this quarter as
well with questions.
Love it.
So just to flesh this
out a little bit more,
this is what I see in
terms of teams building
practical applications.
And I'm excited
about applications
because with improving
machine learning algorithms,
deep learning algorithms,
GenAI algorithms,
there are a lot of applications
that you can build now
that just were impossible
or really inaccessible
to any person to build
even a few years ago.
And so I find that
when I prompt GenAI,
it works really well for a lot
of text-based applications.
And there's work on multimodal
LLMs, large multimodal models.
So making inroads into vision,
making inroads into audio.
But really GenAI algorithms,
especially transformer networks
trained to output text, like
ChatGPT, Claude, Gemini,
and so on, really fantastic
for text-based applications.
And I find myself regularly
working with deep learning
algorithms directly when I'm
working with audio data, image
and video data, and then also
a lot of structured data.
Sorry, my handwriting is awful.
So structured data refers
to large tables of numbers,
like giant Excel or Google
Sheets spreadsheets.
So that's structured data.
Unstructured data refers to
text, audio, images, maybe
video.
And because a lot of GenAI,
large language models,
like ChatGPT, had grown
up being text in text
out kinds of machines, they are
remarkable for a lot of text
processing applications.
But for other types
of data, I end up
often dipping down directly
to use various deep learning
algorithms.
And then it turns out that for
text-based data, if all you do
is prompting, you could
usually go quite far.
So a lot of applications
are built by prompting LLMs.
But I've been on quite
a few teams where
after fiddling with the
prompts for a month,
you just can't get the
performance to be better
just by tuning the prompts.
Or another good problem to have,
it turns out use of GenAI tools
are relatively inexpensive
when you're prototyping.
It's like a few dollars
per million tokens,
so you can do a lot.
But sometimes, if
you're lucky enough
to be on a product that
hits product market
fit and a lot of
users want to use,
multiple times
I've been on teams
where we basically did not care
about our large language model
bill.
It was like, whatever, $20 a
month or $100 a month was fine.
But when more and more
users start using it, then
to your team's
positive surprise,
your AI bill really
starts to skyrocket.
And then at some point,
you look at how much
you're paying for your AI
bill for the large language
models and to bend the
cost curve back down, often
a lot of the techniques in deep
learning become very relevant as
well.
So I'm thinking just some of our
bills were really breathtaking.
I don't want to say the
numbers, but just definitely
more than we want to pay.
As much as we love the
companies providing LLMs,
our bills that we're paying
them were significantly larger
than I wanted to pay.
And then knowing how to use deep
learning to fine-tune smaller
models, that was really
the critical skill
set that just bend
the cost curve back
and just made the whole
thing affordable to keep
on providing the service.
So yeah.
So that's what--
so that's the skill
set I hope you get
from this course.
All right.
Let's see.
And to give a--
oh.
Sorry, let me use this one.
So to give a quick
overview, this course,
the online materials is
broken down into five modules.
So just to give you an
overview of the five of them.
First one is on the basics
of neural networks, NN,
Neural Networks, and
DL, Deep Learning.
So you learn how to build a
neural network or deep learning
algorithm from
scratch in Python.
I find that sometimes if you use
the frameworks, like TensorFlow
or PyTorch, it hides
a lot of the details.
So we actually work through how
to build a basic neural network
and how to build a basic
deep learning algorithm just
in raw Python so you
really understand it.
And then the second module,
the second mini course
will be on how to improve, how
to tune your neural networks.
So you may have heard
that when you're
training a neural network,
there are a lot of parameters
or we call them hyperparameters.
Hyperparameters are parameters
that control the parameters.
So the weights of
parameters, hyperparameters
are things like
the learning rate
or what's the size of
the neural network.
And so there are actually
a lot of hyperparameters
that we end up tuning
and try to give you
a sense of what are
the most important ones
and practical skills
for tuning them.
It turns out that if you
look at my PhD students,
I think every one of them that--
well, I think probably
every one of them,
definitely every one that--
every PhD student that I know
that became great, I think at
some point wound up up at 2:00
AM tuning hyperparameters.
And I still have very clear
recollections of being
in the office, 2:00 AM, 3:00 AM
fiddling with parameters to try
to get it to work.
And it turns out that,
literally, your skill at tuning
hyperparameters, it
really makes a difference.
So there was some evenings
that I knew my skill at tuning
hyperparameters, frankly, it
made the difference between
whether I went home to sleep at
3:00 AM versus when I went home
to sleep at 7:00 AM.
Maybe there's not--
maybe don't do what I do.
I'm not encouraging
this behavior,
but this is just my
personal experiences.
But it really makes a big
difference, your practical skill
at how quickly
you can figure out
the recipe to get these
neural networks to train.
And related to that is--
one thing we chat a lot
about in this course
is strategies for building
machine learning projects.
So it turns out that if you
build a complex system, let's
say you build-- this
one example we'll
go through later this quarter.
Say you want to build a system
that recognizes your face,
a camera that recognizes your
face, your friend's face,
unlock a door, security,
safety, or whatever.
So something like that.
I've worked on
something like that,
Kian's worked on some of that.
These are complex systems
with multiple components.
There's a camera.
Do you subtract--
clean up the image?
Do you cut out the face?
How do you register the face?
How do you compare a face?
How do you decide to take
another picture before you
unlock the door or just--
or someone trying to fake--
or hold up a picture
printed on a piece of paper.
There are actually
a lot of decisions.
And so what I found
is that the biggest
difference between a team that
knows how to drive forward
a project like this
well and get it
done in days rather than
weeks, or weeks rather
than many months, is the
ability to drive a disciplined
development process.
It turns out when you
have a complex system,
less experienced teams will
often almost pick things
at random to work on.
They'll read one research
paper and say, oh, I
read the research paper we
should get more data, well,
because some newspapers
said AI needs lots of data.
So let's go spend six
months to collect more data.
Turns out, a of the time
collecting more data
does not help your application.
But sometimes it's a huge help.
So given your application,
how do you decide,
should you spend more
time collecting data?
Maybe you should buy more GPUs.
I actually definitely know
people that read in the news,
a lot of GPUs are helpful.
And then I've literally met
fairly senior business leaders
that have spent a very
large amount of money buying
GPUs and then--
some funny stories.
And then I go talk to
them and say, what are you
doing with these GPUs?
And then sometimes--
There was one meeting I
was in where literally
a very large family-run business
had bought a lot of GPUs
and the CTO then pointed to his
nephew, who's a current college
student undergrad and said,
oh, my nephew knows AI.
I'm giving him this very
large budget in GPUs
and I think he'll do AI for me.
But so I think that knowing
how to make these decisions
and not just buying
into the hype
that you read about in the
newspapers is really important.
And one thing I hope to do in
this course is share with you
what driving a disciplined
development process looks like,
because this is one of the
things that really makes a 10x
difference in the speed with
which you can get something
to work.
I've literally seen teams
take six months or 10 months
pursuing an approach that
experienced engineers would
go in and go, you know what?
I could have told
you six months ago
that spending all this
time collecting data,
this was not going to get
your application to where
you want it to go.
But so how do you
examine an application
and figure the
diagnostics to figure out
what are the productive things
you do for your application?
We'll actually spend
a lot of time on that.
And in fact, I'm excited about
doing some simulation exercises
in this classroom with
you later this quarter,
where I'll invite you
later this quarter to say,
in this scenario,
what would you do,
and see if you
could make decisions
in a more systematic way.
Then course four we'll talk
about convolutional networks.
Very useful for computer
vision applications.
And then-- so ConvNets
are specialized models
used mostly for
vision applications,
dealing with images.
And then we'll talk finally
about sequence models.
So sequences could be time
series or sequences of texts,
like words.
So I'll touch on the
transformer network
that power law the
GenAI revolution.
And so throughout
learning-- through learning
all of these things,
I hope that you all
gain a large tool
chest that will
enable you to tackle an
almost bewildering range
of applications.
I think one of the
things I've most
enjoyed as an AI
person is it turns out
when you work in
AI, there are so
many other teams that have data
and that could use our help.
So I feel like as an AI
person, I somehow bizarrely
had the right to play in
building autonomous helicopters
or helping companies, I don't
know, place more relevant ads.
Maybe not the most
inspiring thing I've
worked on, but certainly very
lucrative for some companies.
Or improve web search
rankings or improve safety,
get rid of the negative toxic
results that you may not want,
search results to come back on,
or improve e-commerce retailing,
or improve speech
recognition, or help
ships be more fuel efficient.
All these are real examples.
Or fight fraud, which is
actually really exciting
when you're fighting financial
fraud, which is obviously
a bad thing but when
you're fighting fraud,
sometimes you wake up in the
morning and your team's alerted
you that there's a
new scam, and then
you just have to go and fight
them and build algorithms
in real-time and you
know that every hour you
take, more money actually
leaves the financial system.
So it's kind of awful that
there's financial fraud,
but it's actually one of
the most exhilarating things
I've worked on, because
literally every hour you
are slower to
formulate a response,
you know more dollars are
leaking out every hour.
Anyway, so somehow when you have
this two sets of deep learning,
you just have a bewildering
right to play or ability
to play in a huge
range of applications
that could use your help.
And I think on
campus too, there's
so many departments
across campus,
in the sciences, engineering,
humanities, business that
have interesting data where
your skill set will let you,
if you choose, collaborate with
them to do interesting projects.
And I find, for
example, bizarrely some
of my PhD students are
working on climate science.
It's like, what do I know
about climate science?
I wish I knew more.
But using machine
learning tools,
we could actually work
on climate modeling
and geoengineering
and just play in all
of these hopefully important
and interesting places.
So I hope that you have
that skill set as well
by the end of this quarter.
Yeah.
Do you have enough data for
neural network versus it's
better suited for other
like machine learning?
Yeah.
So how do you know if
you're enough-- how
do you know if you have enough
data for a neural network?
It turns out to be
really difficult to know.
So if it's an application
that others have worked on
or that you've worked on before,
then you may have a sense.
So for example, because I
worked on face recognition,
I have a sense, if you want to
train a face recognition system
from scratch, having
50,000 images,
50,000 unique faces
is pretty good.
So if you worked on
it or if you read
the research literature for
something people have worked on,
that would give you a good
sense for how much data could
be enough to get you started.
But then for greenfield
brand new project
that no one in the world
has worked on before,
if you can't find parallel
projects that are comparable,
it could be really hard to tell.
And so common advice for
completely greenfield-- sorry,
greenfield I mean a
brand new project,
just to more than things--
So for example, if someone has
invented a new medical device
and no one has collected this
type of blood specimen data
before, it's really
hard to tell.
And in that case, the
most common advice
is get a little bit of data
and just try training a model.
And the degree to which your
initial model works or does not
work, that will help you
hone your perspective
on how much data may be needed.
And you may be surprised, maybe
100 data points is all you need.
Sometimes we've been
surprised by that.
And then sometimes we've also
worked on applications where
100 billion data
points later, we're
still trying to get
a lot more data.
And I find it really
difficult to tell.
OK.
Good questions.
Anything else?
So this is a good time for me
to pause and take questions
because--
so what I'm going to do is--
what I'm going to do
after this is switch
tracks and talk a little bit
about exciting trends in AI,
recent trends in AI
that I'm excited about
and how I view the AI landscape.
So this is actually
a good breakpoint
to see if people have
other questions before I
talk about some trends in AI.
Anything else?
Yeah, please.
When you were
differentiating between AI
and deep learning for
those different tasks,
what were like the
distinguishing features
of GenAI?
Was it this transformer versus
non-transformer or how would
you describe the difference?
So I guess-- let's see.
many of these terms are
blurry and fuzz a little bit
into each other.
But when I refer
to generative AI,
generative AI is
this body of work
that generates texts and
sometimes also images,
sometimes also audio, using
deep learning algorithms
in certain ways.
So I think GenAI refers to
this body of work with most
of the center of gravity on
generating text, maybe also
images, and the text generation
algorithms have been mostly
implemented using transformer
neural networks trained
on large amounts of data scraped
off the internet and elsewhere.
So when I refer
to Gen AI, I guess
that's one particular
application of deep learning
models that has given
us large language
models, like ChatGPT
and Claude, and Gemini,
and Meta Llama, and so on.
Does that make sense?
Yeah, cool.
Great.
Anything else?
Cool.
All right.
So let me-- can we go
to the slides, please?
One of the nice things
about this clause is Kian
and I can occasionally
just share with you
things we're seeing
in the broader world.
Hey, while we're doing
that, I'm actually curious.
How many of you use a
specialized AI-assisted coding
tool, like Qodo, Cursor,
Gem CLI, Codex, [INAUDIBLE],
Windsurf?
Awesome.
Almost everyone,
but not everyone.
Interesting.
Oh, I thought-- interesting.
OK, cool.
So yeah, one of the
most exciting things
has happened in programming
is AI-assisted coding.
And I feel like I personally
hope I never, ever
have to go back
to coding by hand.
It's just-- it's
actually interesting.
I often work in coffee
shops on the weekend.
And a few weekends ago, I
was sitting in a coffee shop
and sitting next to me was
someone that was coding by hand
and it looked so strange.
I just asked them,
what are you doing?
Well, in a respectful way.
And it turned out that
they're doing a homework
from some other university
that required the code by hand.
But one of the things
I find exciting
is that individual programmer
productivity is much higher
than it ever used to be.
And maybe I want to share with
you just one thing, what I see.
So I find that in the
software work that I do,
I maybe categorize
it into two buckets.
One is building quick
and dirty prototypes
to see if something works,
and then sometimes I
write production grade,
enterprise grade,
robust, reliable software
that has a scale.
And I find that's where
AI-assisted coding has
made the biggest
difference, is building
the quick and dirty prototypes.
Whereas I think
actually literally
one of my collaborators
used one of the agent
decoders that I named,
but I won't say which one,
but literally this morning he
sent me a Slack message saying,
sorry, this agent decoder had
a database migration error
and we just wiped out all
of the database records,
fortunately for a test
application with five users.
But it did happen.
So I find it--
oh, great.
Thank you.
So I find that my
use of the agent
decoders for the
production grade software
is more careful,
whereas for building
quick and dirty prototypes, it--
so long as you're
not shipping software
in an irresponsible way,
quick and dirty prototypes
have a lot fewer dependencies.
You actually don't need to
integrate with legacy data
infrastructure.
And then I'm going
to say something
that feels like something
I'm not supposed to say,
but I'll say it
anyway, which is I
find that when I
am running code,
I find that people
often worry about safety
and reliability of software
or security of software.
So one thing I often
say to my teams
is if you're building
a prototype that
only runs on your own
laptop and doesn't
use any sensitive
information, so there's
no risk to sensitive
information,
then unless you are
planning to maliciously hack
into your own laptop,
the security requirements
can be lower.
And so I find that when building
quick and dirty prototypes,
having a sandbox environment
that lets you operate within it
quickly means that you can
just make a lot of decisions
faster without worrying as much
about scalability or security
or reliability, so long as
the sandbox environment means
this stuff isn't going to get
out there, or leak information,
or create a security loophole.
So that's part of what
lets us move much faster.
And so I find that because
of the speed of prototyping,
so long as you can do
so in a responsible way
to pursue innovative
ideas, my teams
will increasingly try 20
things and see what sticks.
And because-- and I
know that a lot of teams
are lamenting that many
proof of concepts never
make it into production.
You try something
and it doesn't work.
And some teams are
feeling angst about that.
I actually have
a different view.
I think if the cost
of a proof of concept
is low enough, then who cares
if you have to do 20 of them
and that's the price for
finding the one or two
things that works really well.
So one thing you hear
about in this course
is both when you're building a
machine learning application,
you usually don't know
what's going to happen.
And there's a specific
reason for that.
The reason is the output of
a machine learning algorithm,
it depends both on
the code you write
as well as on the data
you're training on.
And while you control
the code 100%,
you don't really know usually
what's really in the data,
in the weird and wonderful data
that the world has given you.
So, for example, worked on
speech recognition a lot
in multiple companies,
in multiple contexts.
And even now when I work
on speech recognition,
I'm still sometimes a
little bit surprised
that, oh, this data has people
of a certain accent more
than I realize, or people
somehow speak faster,
or, boy, there's a lot
of background noise
when people use it in a car.
So even though I worked
on speech recognition
multiple times--
oh, and actually one recent
example or application,
I was actually surprised by the
number of background speakers.
They talked to us, they come
and talk to a different person,
then they talk to us and
then we get confused.
So I find that the data
that the world gives us
is often weird and wonderful.
And so it is only by building
a system that you then
start to discover these
things in the data that
lets you make progress.
And with a lot of
software applications
as well, separate from
machine learning applications,
a lot of what I end
up having to discover
is what do users actually want?
So again, I control
my code 100%.
I can write whatever
code I want.
I control that.
But you don't get to
control how your users will
react to your system.
And I find that our ability to
build quick and dirty prototypes
rapidly, both to discover
what's in the data
and also to particular users to
see if they like it, that allows
us to drive faster
feedback loops than
was ever possible
before to then help
us build more and more
valuable software.
And I think--
I know that the mantra move fast
and break things got a bad rep
because it broke things.
And I find that
some teams took away
from this that we
should not move fast,
but I think that's a mistake.
So what I usually tell my teams
is move fast and be responsible.
And despite all the hype about
AI extinction risk or AI--
all that somewhat bizarre
hype in my opinion,
I find that when teams
move really fast,
we can then implement
things, test it out
in a responsible way, and much
more quickly identify problems
and fix them.
So I find that a lot of most
responsible teams I know, teams
able to really get stuff to
work really quickly, they
tend to be some of the fastest
moving teams, because it's
that speed of execution that
lets you finally implement
it, figure out
what's in your data,
figure out what your users
want, and that's the best
way to figure out
what could actually
go wrong to then make sure
things don't actually go wrong.
Ans somewhat related to that
is AI coding assistance.
And I assume almost everyone
or everyone in this class
knows how to code.
If you are where you
haven't learned to code yet,
you probably might not want
to take this class yet.
But I find that there have
been people, including
very senior business
leaders, advising others
to not learn to
code in the grounds
that AI will automate it.
And I want to share
this with you,
not because I think you
need to learn to code,
but because I hope you
help me spread the word.
Go to all of your friends and
other departments to tell them
this advice do not
learn to code I
think we'll look back on this
as some of the worst career
advice ever given.
And the reason is, when
coding becomes easier,
more people should do
it rather than fewer.
So when humanity went from punch
cards to keyboard and terminal,
that made coding easier, and
so more people learn to code.
When we went from assembly
language to modern--
well, at that time, modern
programming languages,
that made coding easier,
more people learn to code.
I went back, I actually
found these papers on when--
these articles on when COBOL,
very old school programming
language, was invented,
and there were actually
people that said, oh, wow, now
we have the COBOL programming
language.
Coding is so easy.
Who needs programmers anymore?
And obviously, the
opposite happened.
Went from text editors to IDEs
and then AI-assisted coding.
As coding becomes easier,
people should code a lot more.
A lot more people
should learn to code.
And the other thing
I'm seeing is, just
something that's been
on people's minds,
I know that unemployment
of recent computer science
graduates has ticked up to
higher than it's been compared
to, I think, the last decade.
And so I know that to
people learning CS, that
has caused some consternation.
So I'm going to share
my view on that.
So it turns out that what
I see in Silicon Valley
and beyond Silicon
Valley is we just
can't find enough people
with these skills.
I know many businesses
that would--
I know large businesses that
would love to hire 1,000 people
with skills in GenAI and deep
learning and machine learning,
but they are struggling to
find people with these skills.
Conversely, there are still
universities with curricula
that has not changed since--
has not changed
much for the last,
I don't know, since 2002,
before the rise of GenAI.
And so I do see that many new
CS grads, not from Stanford,
but from around the country,
are struggling with finding jobs
because, unfortunately,
that older non-AI
enabled skill set that
is not as much in demand.
And maybe just for myself,
today I will not hire someone--
I will not hire a software
engineer that doesn't how
to use AI to help
them with coding.
It just doesn't make sense.
Same reason why
I just won't hire
someone that uses a punch
card, keyboard, and terminal.
And I think when the world
evolved from punch card
to keyboard and
terminal, people still
had punch card jobs for
a while, but eventually
the punch card jobs
just went away.
It just doesn't
make sense anymore.
So today, there are still
coding by hand jobs around.
Maybe some specialties,
some very low level
coding where AI
is not very good.
It turns out AI is not very
good at some types of GPU
programming.
There are some niches
where coding by hand
actually still makes sense.
But for building applications--
So I actually-- I remember
just a few months ago now,
many months ago now, where
I interviewed two engineers
back to back.
One had not yet
graduated from college,
but was highly on
top of GenAI coding.
So spoke with that candidate,
knew how to use AI,
built programs and
could sell them quickly.
Right after that, I
also interviewed someone
with 10 years of experience
as a full stack engineer,
but whose skill set was exactly
the same as their 2002 skill
set.
Had not tried out any
AI-assisted coding.
Really good skills,
full stack engineer
with 10 years of experience.
And it was actually
really clear to me,
I picked the fresh college
grad where he had not--
he was about to
graduate, over someone
with 10 years of experience.
So I think making sure you
master these skills are
really important.
And what I'm seeing is there is
a very large gap that businesses
are having a hard time filling
for people with these skills.
But the demand
for the 2022 skill
set, software engineering, full
site engineering skill set,
that is not there.
So I think--
And then in terms of
AI-assisted coding,
I find that CS fundamentals
really are important.
So in addition-- so I
know I hired someone,
a fresh college grad over
someone 10 years experience.
True story.
There's actually one other
part to this story, which
is with respect to all of
the above, the graduate
from college, the best
programmers I know are also not
fresh college grads.
No disrespect intended
to fresh college grads.
Some are about to
graduate from Stanford.
The best programmers
I know are really
on top of AI-assisted coding and
additionally deeply understand
computer science fundamentals.
So it turns out--
maybe I'll illustrate
this with a quick story.
When I was teaching
an online course,
my team wanted to generate
background pictures
like this just for decoration.
So when I was
working on this, this
is, of course, generative
AI for everyone,
I was working with a
collaborator, Tommy Nelson,
that understood art history.
And so my collaborator
knew the language of art.
He knew the artistic genre,
inspiration, the palette,
so he could prompt Midjourney
AI image generation
with the language of art.
And so he could generate
beautiful pictures like these.
In contrast, I don't
know art history.
I wish I did.
And so all I could do
was go to Midjourney
or AI image generation
and type, please
make pretty pictures
of robots for me,
and I could never get the
control that my collaborator
Tommy could to generate
pictures like these,
which is why we use all of
his pictures and none of mine.
And I'm seeing the same
thing in computer science.
One of the most important
skills for the future
is to understand how
computers work and understand
how GenAI and deep learning
and machine learning
work so that you can
use the language of AI,
use the language of
these tools to tell
a computer exactly what you
want so the computer can do it
for you.
And there is actually
a huge difference
in performance
between someone that's
learned to just prompt an
LLM without understanding how
computers or how
AI really works,
versus people that can
look at the problem,
analyze it, and then
with AI-assisted coding,
tell a computer how to
take the next steps, which
is why I think that CS
fundamentals is very valuable.
CS fundamentals, machine
learning fundamentals,
deep learning fundamentals,
I and my teams,
we use that knowledge
like every day
in making pretty
consequential decisions.
So I hope that you get
that from this class
and the many other classes
at Stanford as well.
All right.
I think I might leave the rest.
There's more I could
say on trends in AI,
but I find that
AI-assisted-- oh,
but one thing I hope you do
really, go to all your friends
in all the departments
across campus
and encourage them to be a
builder, because the other thing
I'm seeing is clearly for
computer science professionals,
use AI-assisted coding, know CS
fundamentals, build cool stuff.
But for other
disciplines as well
that is not computer
science or not AI,
I'm finding that the education
professional or the climate
scientists, or the
mechanical engineer that
wants to know how
to build software
are just more productive
and get a lot more done
and the barrier to
entry to AI, to coding
is the lowest it's
ever been in our lives.
And so this is a good
time, frankly, for--
I wish every single
Stanford student
will learn to build
software with AI assistance.
So I hope you go help
your friends across campus
to master those skills as well.
OK.
Yeah.
Any other questions?
Yes, go ahead.
What do you say about
the trend of someone
knowing [INAUDIBLE] but
also [INAUDIBLE] AI?
I've had a lot of
industry folks talking
about how they would
rather hire someone
with 10 years of experience who
knows just generative AI as is,
like just using coding, rather
than a fresh undergrad that
does have that deep
understanding of deep learning,
machine learning, and generative
AI as fundamentals just
because they have more
experience building.
Do you see that also?
Yeah.
So let me rank productivity,
and I'll give you four levels.
I think-- and again,
and I say this
with a lot of respect
for individuals.
So if I talk about
productivity, it's
not with any disrespect or any
lack of affection for anyone
or for their work.
But I think least productive
are people with no experience
and don't know AI.
One step on top of that is
people with less experience
but on a--
sorry, one step
on top of that is
people with, say, a
decade of experience but
that don't know AI.
On top of that, I would rather
take a fresh college grad that
does know AI, but then
even more productive
is someone with a
decade of experience
and also really on top of AI.
So I think between
the two factors,
really harnessing AI
is very important,
but experience is
also important.
And so the best developers I
know, we just work and we just
ship code like no
one's ever done,
I think, even two
or three years ago,
are very experienced developers.
They're also very on top of
how they use the latest AI
technologies.
Yeah, please.
Oh, sorry.
And just one other thing
about the job market.
I find that a lot of employers
have not yet figured out
how to hire appropriately.
This has contributed--
frankly, a lot of employers,
if a company has no one that
knows GenAI, how do they even
how to interview appropriately?
So that is a problem that
we need to solve as well.
Go ahead.
What's the value of
taking classes that are
super into programming and--
like, for example, I'm
thinking of classes
like C2107, 111 where we're
not encouraged to use tools
and we're encouraged.
Is that to build
the fundamentals,
and do you think
that's necessary still?
Yeah, boy.
So CS107, CS111 are
great, so do take them
if you're considering them.
I find that the
fundamentals are important.
How do I put it?
Yeah, I'm not sure what
else to say other than that.
I think honestly,
Stanford we're known for--
CS Department we're
known for really--
I know I'm biased, but I want
to say probably the best entry
level CS program classes of
any university in the world,
I'm pretty biased, so
maybe I shouldn't say that,
but I think the
excellent course if you
want to learn the fundamentals
and really solid way,
and the instructors
are routinely
thinking about how to
update the curriculum
and realities of GenAI.
So I think they do an
excellent job with that mix.
Yes, please.
[INAUDIBLE] use GenAI compared
to just [INAUDIBLE] Cursor
and type a prompt, so.
Yeah.
How do I find someone
that really knows GenAI
compared to someone that just
use a tool and types of prompts.
So I feel like in GenAI there
are two buckets of skill.
And again, by the way,
deep learning is not GenAI.
Deep learning is also
a very valuable skill,
but this is about GenAI.
I think there are two things.
One is I find it really
useful to know how
to use AI coding assistance.
That's really valuable.
But having fundamental
knowledge helps you do that.
And then the other
thing is in GenAI,
there's a number
of emerging tools.
I'm going to toss
out some buzzwords.
OK.
So if you don't know what
any of these words mean,
don't worry about it.
But I think there are emerging
tools, like RAG, Retrieval
Augmented Generation, or
how to-- vector databases,
how to do evals
and error analysis,
how to build guardrails,
how to use knowledge graphs
and interface that with LLM,
maybe how to do multimodal LLMs,
how to fine-tune the model.
What else?
I'm probably blanking
on something.
Oh, how to build
agentic workflows.
But I feel like there are these
categories of new techniques
built on top of GenAI that
are like a useful bag of tools
for building applications.
Well, frankly, when I'm
interviewing candidates,
we still do a fair
amount of, it is
very GenAI role, is these
skills I tend to look for,
this set of tools as well
as AI-assisted coding.
And then-- yeah.
Yeah, please.
I don't know if this
question is best close to you
or if I'm considering taking
229 and 230 at the same time,
both of those classes
are final projects.
So how would you recommend
thinking about ideas to pursue?
Yeah.
So let me just give one
tip about CS courses
in general, not just
229 and CS230, which
is I encourage you to think of
AI courses at Stanford a bit
like Pokemon.
You got to catch them all.
But in all seriousness, I think
taking more CS courses in AI,
it is a good thing to do.
Definitely encourage you
to take multiple courses.
I think in some years we've
had students do joint projects,
where the standard is higher
expectations for sure,
but that's one
option to look at.
Yeah.
All right.
Go for it.
[INAUDIBLE] so I
guess [INAUDIBLE],
but what is the difference
pedagogically between 229
and 230?
And what are the projects
that can be overlapped?
So let's see.
229 and 230 are very
different courses.
229, well, in 229 we
have live instructors
doing the lectures in-person
rather than online content.
So it's not the
flipped classroom.
So in CS230, we have
most of the materials
prepared in online videos,
highly edited online videos.
And then I think the
other biggest difference
is CS229 is more
mathematical theoretical,
but it's important math,
whereas CS230 is more practical.
And so I don't know if we
do even want a single--
maybe we do one proof
somewhere in the lectures,
but we just don't do a
lot of math in CS230.
And it's very-- a lot of machine
learning is very empirical.
You try and see what works,
but have a disciplined approach
for exploring what works.
So we focus a lot
more on that in CS230.
And oh, and 229 covers
a lot more techniques.
So there are a lot of machine
learning techniques, supervised
learning, unsupervised learning,
decision trees, boosting,
K means clustering.
So CS229 covers a
much broader survey
of a lot of machine
learning techniques,
whereas CS230 is just one thing.
We go really deep
into deep learning.