I'm Kian Katanforoosh and I am
the co-creator and collector
with Andrew for
this class, CS230.
And I will teach about half
of the in-person lectures
this quarter.
Outside of Stanford,
I work in industry.
I lead a company called Workera
which uses AI to measure skills.
And with the history
of CS230 students that
have started AI startups and
companies, what I try to do,
usually, is to bring a lot
of examples from industry.
So what you should expect
from these in-class lectures
is not as much of the
academic side of things, which
we learn anyway in
the online videos,
but also the industry
specific input.
And some of the topics that
we'll cover this year together
includes decision-making
in AI projects,
which we're going to see today.
I want you to come out of
today's lecture feeling
like you had some fun,
it was interactive.
And also you have a better way
to make decisions in AI projects
because you've seen how
deep-learning researchers,
engineers, and scientists make
their decisions solving problems
in industry.
Other topics later in the
quarter for in classroom time
include things like adversarial
attacks and defenses.
We might have some
time to cover it today.
Deep reinforcement
learning, which
is really hot in the
market right now,
and I think it's very
important to about it.
And then all the stuff
that is very practical,
like retrieval
augmented generation,
AI agents, multi-agent system.
As we go deeper into
the class, and you
get the baggage of
neural networks,
we'll be able to cover
even more fun topics.
So today's lecture is
going to be structured
in three parts,
maybe four depending
on whether we have time.
We'll start with a
little recap of the week.
What you've learned online
about neurons and layers
and deep neural networks.
Then we'll get into a set of
supervised learning projects,
including a day and night
simple vanilla classification,
the trigger word detection,
which is actually
a project you're going to
build at the end of the class
yourself.
And then face
verification, which
we'll see also variation
of how face verification
algorithms work.
In the third
section, we'll focus
on self-supervised learning
and weakly supervised learning.
Don't worry if you
don't these terms.
We're going to
learn them together.
And we'll talk a
lot about embeddings
because embeddings are the
connective tissue of many AI
systems online today, and it's
important to know about them.
And finally, if we
have time, we'll
also talk about adversarial
attacks and defenses.
With more and more AI
systems in the wild,
knowing how to defend
them is very important,
and knowing how to
attack them can also
teach you how to defend them.
So we'll cover that as well.
Sounds good?
Please interrupt me as we
go through the lecture.
We want this to be very
conversational as much as
possible.
So recap of the
week is the core way
that AI learns from data in a
traditional supervised learning
setup.
You can think of it as an
input, such as this little image
of the confused
cat and an output,
in this case, a
number between 0 and 1
that represents the
chance that there
might be a cat on the
picture 1 or there
is no cat on the picture 0.
What the model is, and
oftentimes you'll see
me refer to the
model as two things.
There's an architecture
which is essentially
the blueprint of the model,
the skeleton and parameters.
It might be a few
parameters, it might
be billions of parameters
like the models
that OpenAI, DeepMind
and others work on.
Outside of that--
And so when you think about
AI models being deployed
in the wild, when you
think about what's
happening with
ChatGPT, you can really
come down to there's two files
somewhere on the cloud, one that
describes the architecture
of the model, one
that describes the
parameters that
are part of this architecture.
And you keep calling
to those two files,
and you get your
inference or your output.
That's really what's
happening behind the scenes.
Much more complicated
than that, obviously.
But those are the two critical
components of a neural network
architecture, and its
parameters that are trained.
How does the model learn?
Is through a gradient
descent optimization.
Meaning I send the picture
of the cat through the model,
and the model, at the
beginning, is not trained,
so it's probably wrong.
It tells me I think there
is no cat, I think it's 0.
And then I use something
called the loss function
to compare the ground truth.
There is a cat on the
picture with the prediction
from the model at
this point in time.
Those two numbers are
far from each other.
That should be a penalty, which
the loss function describes.
And then, in order to give
feedback to the parameters,
we use this gradient
descent update.
We do that many, many times.
What it means is that we take
our parameters and we tell them,
hey, you should go
a little bit more
to the right or
to the left until
that number, that
is the prediction for the cat,
is closer to the ground truth.
We do that with batches
of data, millions
of images of cats and
images of anything
else, and we give that feedback
repetitively to the model
until the parameters
are calibrated
and the model is, in fact,
finding the cat on this picture.
Nothing new here.
You've seen it in the videos.
Any question on
that learning setup?
No.
OK, easy so far.
There's many things that
can change in this setup,
and you'll see in the class.
First thing is the input.
The input does not
have to be an image.
It can be text like when
you chat with ChatGPT.
It can be audio,
it can be video,
it can be structured data, it
can be spreadsheets and numbers.
Those we'll see a variety
of examples in the class
and how it influences
the architecture.
The output again doesn't
have to be 0 and 1.
This is an example
of a classification.
You could turn this
problem into a regression.
For example, if I was asking
you, what's the age of the cat,
estimate the age of the cat.
That would be a regression
task, not a classification task
anymore.
Later in the class, we'll
also see generative tasks.
In fact, lecture 4 is going
to focus on diffusion models
generative adversarial networks
where the output, actually,
is much bigger than
the input, typically.
So you can have a low resolution
of a cat as input and the output
is a high-resolution
of the same cat.
The output is bigger
than the input, which can
be counterintuitive to people.
Other things that can change
include the architecture.
You've learned about the
vanilla multilayer perceptron
or the fully connected
neural network.
That's what we're learning
right now online together.
By the end of the class,
you'll have many architectures
that you'll be
familiar with from RNNs
and convolutional neural
networks, transformer models.
All of these, at
the, end of the day,
use the basis neural network
that you're learning right now.
They're just stacked on top
of each other differently.
The loss function is actually
a big focus of today's class
and of the class in general.
The loss function, which is what
gives the feedback to the model,
you were right or you were
wrong, and what to do about it
is an art.
Designing good loss functions.
Great deep learning
researchers are
very creative when it comes
to designing loss functions.
And in fact, when we built
the algorithm called YOLO,
it is called YOLO for
you only look once,
not you only live once.
But YOLO has a very, difficult
to understand at first loss
function.
And there's a reason
why the loss function
was designed like that.
So by the end of
this class, you'll
also have a better
intuition on how do
we design great loss functions.
Other things I'm not
going to cover right now,
the activation functions in your
neural network, the optimizer
that you use for your gradient
descent loop, and then the
hyperparameters that
might come in when
you train your algorithms.
OK nothing new here.
This is the basic setup.
You've also learned
this week about neurons.
The easiest way to
think about a neuron
is the classic logistic
regression algorithm.
Where I'm taking the
image of the cat.
So an image in computer science
with the way the machine reads
it is three channels.
RGB for the three
colors red, green, blue.
And we take all these numbers.
We put them in a vector.
The vector is then
fed into a neuron.
And the neuron has two
components the linear part
W transpose X plus B.
W being the weights
and B being the bias.
And then an activation
function, in this case,
the sigmoid function, which
is very handy because it takes
any number, and it
puts it between 0 and 1
so that the output can
look like a probability.
Classic setup.
And here the probability
is 0.73 which is above 0.5.
Which tells me the model thinks
there's a cat on the picture
because 1 is a cat 0 is no cat.
So question for
you to get started.
How would you modify this
binary classification
that detects cats
in an algorithm that
would be able to detect
multiple animals,
such as a cat, a
dog, and a giraffe?
What do you need to change
about this neural network?
Yeah.
OK, so you would
change the output layer
to match to the number of
animals you want to detect.
Yeah, correct?
Anyone wants to
add anything else?
Yeah.
The data that goes in there.
How would you change the data?
It has to be for
the animal data.
OK very good.
Yeah, you need data
from dogs and giraffes
and also maybe
nature in general.
What else do we
need not to forget?
Yeah.
Maybe you could add a
neuron for each node,
and then your prediction
would be whichever
output is the highest.
Yeah, OK.
Add 1 neuron per animal.
Those neurons will be
independent from each other.
And each neuron would
focus on one animal.
Yeah good point.
It's actually what
we're going to do.
So yes, I think your
suggestions were the right one.
We could multiply
this output layer
to have three neurons
instead of one.
All of them, because it's a
fully connected neural net,
see the entire pixels
flattened in the vector.
And then each of them will
be focused on an animal.
The number one mistake
that we see in projects
is that people add more data,
but forget to adjust the labels.
So how do the labels
need to be adjusted here?
It's not any more 0 and 1.
What type of labels do
we need to train this?
Yeah.
The number of the
number of range.
You know how we call that?
Or no.
OK.
So yeah.
Yeah.
Use vectors.
Vectors, yeah.
I think you're seeing
the same thing, but.
Yeah So here you would use a
one hot vector or a multi-hot.
One hot means you'll
have a vector of size 3.
And if there is a
cat on the picture
the label is going to be 0, 1
0 because the second neuron is
going to be responsible
to detect cats.
In fact, that would be
called a one hot vector.
Oftentimes you'll have
multiple animals on the picture
because cats and dogs
can appear together.
Cats and giraffes less so.
And dogs and
giraffes, I've never
seen one in the same
picture, but anyway.
You'll have a
multi-hot vector if you
have a cat and a
dog on the picture,
you'll probably label it as 110.
And the reason I'm
mentioning that it
may sound silly, but in
a lot of projects people
change their data.
They forget to
change their labels,
and then they wonder
why it doesn't work.
OK, cool.
Now in the class, we
use a specific notation
with a superscript
and subscript.
So when you see me refer
to something like a 1 1,
the superscript
in square brackets
indicates the layer
that you're in.
So you're in the first layer.
The subscript refers to the
index of the neuron, OK.
And a is for activation.
So a subscript three
square bracket 1
is the output of the third
neuron of the first layer, OK.
Again if I continue second layer
would be written like that.
And then you'll get
your probability.
The deeper the network is,
the more capacity it has.
This is the word
we use, capacity.
What it means is that if you
send a million pictures of cats
and a million pictures of non
cats to a shallow network,
it might not have the capacity
to learn what's in the data set.
It's just not flexible enough.
The deeper the network,
the more capacity it has.
So in fact, the network
that is super deep.
Imagine a billion
parameters transformer model
with one million pictures
of cat and non-cat,
it will just overfit
to those pictures.
Meaning it's not going
to learn what a cat is,
it's just going to learn
by heart those million
pictures because its capacity
is way bigger than the data set
it's fed.
So it's very important
to understand the amount
of data you're going to feed.
And the complexity,
diversity of that data
will probably
dictate the capacity
of the models you need to use.
Now, just to give you a little
bit more intuition on what
happens inside those
neural networks.
We take these relatively
shallow network,
but call it three layers.
And we train it on a data
set of facial images.
Ignore the task.
In face data sets, there's
a lot of tasks you could do.
You could do a
face verification,
you could do a face recognition,
you could do face clustering,
things like that.
We'll talk about that later.
But let's say it's
been trained really
well on understanding faces.
If you now unpack this network
and you query each neuron
and look what's going on
inside, what you'll notice
is that the first
layers are going
to be better at encoding
low-complexity features,
while the deeper networks are
going to be better at encoding
higher complexity features.
So here's how it goes.
Nothing too complicated for now.
The neuron in the
first layers, they're
looking at pixels because
you're giving them him
directly the pixels.
So they're going to be good at
stitching those pixels together.
And maybe the first
neuron will be
good at detecting diagonal
edge, the second neuron
will be good at vertical
edges, and the third one
at horizontal edges, because
they're just looking at pixels
and trying to make
sense out of them.
Now you go one layer deeper
in the middle of the network.
Those are not seeing
pixels, they're
seeing the output of the
first layer, which is already
slightly more complex.
So what you can
expect the layers
in the middle of the
network to give you
or to activate for is
higher level features,
like an eye or a nose or an ear.
Because it turns out if
you have a few edges,
you can start detecting circles.
And so you would
see a neuron that
is really good at
detecting circles, eyes.
The deeper you go
in the network,
the more you get closer to the
task itself, which in this case,
facial analysis.
Let's say you would see
the last few neurons,
detect larger
features of the face.
Because again, they're seeing
higher complexity information.
Does that make sense?
This concept we
call it encoding,
we'll also talk
about embeddings.
It's very important because
when you train neural networks,
you want to make sure
first that they're
understanding what they're doing
and that's one way to see it.
We'll have an entire lecture
on interpreting and visualizing
neural networks
later this quarter.
And on top of that
you probably can
make use of some of those
encodings and embeddings.
We'll see that later.
But why in the vector space the
distances between those concepts
are important.
You can already imagine that
for tasks like search searching
in a database, having a
neural network able to encode
information in a
very meaningful way,
can allow you to
find concepts that
are close to each other and
associate them with each other,
and concepts that are
far from each other
and dissociate them
from each other.
OK.
So this was the
warm up for today.
How much time we spent.
OK, 15 minutes in the warm up.
That's good.
So we learned a few new words.
Model, architecture, parameters.
I didn't talk about it,
but feature engineering
versus feature learning,
that's the core concept
in deep learning is
feature engineering
is what we used to do
before deep learning.
Which is you might actually
build an algorithm that
is good at detecting eyes.
It's just a good
at scanning eyes.
You manually build it.
And then you build
another one that
is good at detecting a mouth.
And then you put them
together to detect faces.
We don't do that anymore.
We do end-to-end learning.
Meaning we let the data speak
for itself and train the model.
This is called feature learning.
It's automatic, and that's how
the neural network actually
learns those features without
you needing to tell it eyes
are important to detect faces.
You don't need to do that.
Encoding and embedding.
The real difference is encoding
is any vector representation
and an embedding,
though-- sorry,
it should have been--
an embedding is
when an encoding has meaning.
meaning The distance between
two encodings has meaning.
They might be close or
far from each other,
and it tells you something.
There is a logic to it.
And then we talked about one
hot and multi-hot vectors.
So end of the recap.
Now let's go into
supervised learning projects
and we're going to make
decisions together and walk
through it.
The first case study is day
and night classification.
So here's my problem for you.
Given an image that I
give you, classify it
as whether it's the day
or whether it's the night.
OK, open ended problem.
Ignore that foundation
models exist.
You don't have access to
ChatGPT or Claude or whatever.
The point is to
get under the hood
and have those discussions
because obviously it's
a toy example.
So what do you do?
What data do you want to
collect to solve this problem?
Start yes.
Check on the grid pixels
in the same rows, column.
So tell me more.
Check how pixels in
the same row are?
Different rows.
Just see how they are different.
And if they are
very different, it's
a possibility that [INAUDIBLE].
What does it tell
you that if you
look at a row of pixels
and the row next to it,
if they're very different.
What does it tell you?
It has more colors
than just [INAUDIBLE].
OK.
So you say if the
delta between pixels
that are close geographically
to each other is high,
then there's probably colors--
color changes so it's
day, most likely.
Is that it?
So that's an example
of feature engineering.
It's like you're going
for it and great.
You're going for it
and you're trying
to understand what's a
pattern that tells me
that a picture is day or night.
What else can you do in the
world of neural networks.?
Any other ideas?
Yeah.
Just feed in a
bunch of pictures.
Half that are during
the day half du--
OK, good.
Yeah.
So yeah, I agree.
I said 10,000 images, but how
do you even determine how many
pictures you need to get
started with this project?
Feed some data.
So you start with 10 pictures
and then you continue to go.
Yeah.
You could do that.
Might take some time.
I think the question is how
easy is it to collect that data.
How would you collect that data?
Probably from the
same location you
could get pictures
from day and pictures.
OK yeah.
We could put our phone out there
and record the day and the night
and have a stream of pictures
and add it to the data set.
Same location, but
different lightings.
Yea.
And you mentioned that this
was a very hard problem,
because in my opinion, also it
depends on what kind of model
you want to operate.
For example, if you
were building something
for one location to set,
whether it's day or night,
then that one location
would be really nice.
But then if you were trying to
look at anywhere in the world,
like in any kind of climate,
whether it's day or night,
then you would have to have an
extremely diverse set of images.
And because the
problem is so broad
we would also need, so
many-- a huge amount of data.
That's a great point.
So just to repeat for
the people online,
you have to define
the task first.
Because the task can be easy.
You can be in a park in
a very specific location
and say, just detect
if it's day or night,
or you can have a problem, which
is your camera can be anywhere.
And that makes it
more complicated.
And also the amount
of data you need
is probably much more
for that second problem.
That's what you said right.
Now-- actually,
that's a great thread.
Tell me about cases
where this problem would
be really hard to solve?
Yeah.
Pictures of places like inside.
Yeah, indoor.
Indoor pictures.
Actually, how could you tell
if you took a picture of me
with the screen here
what time it was?
You couldn't.
You actually can.
Yeah.
There's a clock here.
So that's very interesting
because if that
was part of the task then
our problem would be hard.
And 10,000 images is not going
to cut it to understand time.
And so it's very important
to define the task very well.
What else can be hard
other than indoor pictures?
The clock could be AM/ PM.
Also.
Also the clock can be, AM or PM.
But you can probably take
additional information, which
is how people are dressed
and think that it might
be warmer outside than colder.
You could-- again, it
can be very complicated
at the end of the
day, but a human
would say someone is teaching,
students are in class.
It's probably not 12:00 AM.
Or so I mean, it
gets complicated.
What else can be hard?
Sunny versus cloudy.
OK.
Sunny, cloudy.
Yeah.
If you're in the
part of the world
where the sun doesn't
set during the day.
Great point.
If you're in the North of
Norway right now or Sweden,
even the clock can't tell you
probably if it's day or night.
Yeah.
Dawn and dusk.
Yeah, exactly.
Those are great examples.
Actually, this is
a good semantic one
because you need also to define
exactly what's the definition
of day and night.
So long story short, the
problem can seem easy at first,
it can be very complicated.
And trust me, if you wanted
to do this really well,
even the foundation models today
couldn't do it in certain cases.
OK, let's say we
have 10,000 images,
and you talked about the
split of images earlier.
And I agree with you, you want
a mix of different situations
in order to be able
to cover all of them.
And going back to our
discussion on model capacity,
if it's just a simple
problem, you probably
need just a small
capacity model.
If you want to add
all these edge cases,
you probably are looking for
bigger-capacity models and more
data.
What's the input to our model?
I think someone said it already.
So let's say a picture of--
a picture of day or
night or whatever.
What's the resolution
we're going to work with?
How do you determine resolution
when you build a data set,
and why does it matter?
Yes.
Give a number of pixels that
would [INAUDIBLE] values
and round them of to
be the same vector.
So you want to choose
a resolution that's
going to be the same
across the board.
You're going to vectorize
everything that's going
to fit in the same size matrix.
Yeah.
Why is it important to have
the right resolution let's say?
It's going to have the
super resolution so
that it can recognize patterns.
If the picture is
the same to us.
But it's in a
limited resolution.
So you're saying
we want homogeneity
in the data set in
terms of resolution.
I would say that
could be a thing
but, today, you
can actually write
scripts that downsize high
resolution images before it
gets in the model.
And so it would probably solve--
upsizing is slightly harder.
You will need another algorithm.
But, it's OK to have
different resolutions,
but you still want to what's the
target resolution that you're
looking for.
If you have too low resolution,
you lose some of your features.
If you have too high resolution,
you have too much data
and you have a lot of
weights to optimize.
Exactly.
Low resolution, we
lack information,
so we might get things wrong.
For example, the clock might
not appear in the picture
if it's too low resolution.
High resolution means
more compute needed.
If you have big
pictures, it's going
to be heavier to
train your model
and you're going to pay more.
And also your
cycles of iterations
are going to be longer.
In an AI project, that's why
your resolution matters a lot.
So my question is, what
resolution do we go for?
Is there a way to
just get to a number
really quickly in the next
10 minutes, let's say,
if we were doing this project?
Yeah.
Who's--
[INAUDIBLE] you
stick the image size
and see whether you can detect.
Yeah, exactly.
I think that's a great idea.
You're saying use
the human as a proxy.
Yeah so actually,
this is how we did it.
Back in the days we
would print pictures
in different resolutions and run
it through our friends and say,
can you tell if it's
the day or the night.
And it turns out that
below a certain resolution,
they can't anymore.
It's just like, I don't
have the information I need.
And where we ended is
somewhere around 64 by 64 by 3.
And I stress the 3 because
later this quarter we'll
see that OpenAI and DeepMind--
DeepMind is [? well ?] in
reinforcement learning.
It turns out for one of the
famous algorithms we learned
together for reinforcement
learning discovered that you can
actually remove colors, and
the model is not impacted,
but your training
is way simpler.
In this case, I think colors
matter because of the blue sky,
because it does have an inherent
information about whether it's
day or night.
And it turns out the task,
if you give it to humans,
is much harder without colors
than it is with colors.
So those type of
insights we could
get over the next 10
minutes, literally
by using humans as a proxy.
This is a toy
example, but I want
you to think about that
in your AI project.
You're going to
be at points where
you want to validate
a hypothesis,
and the best proxy
you'll have is the human.
Yeah.
OK, what's the output
for this model?
Day or night.
Yeah day or night.
0 or 1.
Yeah.
The other question.
Is there a relationship
on how many input you have
and how many neurons you
have in the proxy in there.
Do you just start
from and then you
look at the number of their
relationship in seperate.
Yeah good question.
So does the size of the
image impact the input layer?
The size of the input
layer, is that it?
Yeah it doesn't.
You can make your decisions.
You can have three
neurons and you send
a massive picture inside it.
Oftentime, and
that's why I often
say deep learning is
an engineering field.
You have to try it or you
have to know the hacks.
Typically the network-- in
a binary classification,
you're going from a
high-dimensional input
to a very low
dimensional output.
So by nature, you'd imagine
your network is going
to be like this, probably.
Meaning you need
more edge detection
at the beginning and then higher
feature and higher feature,
until at the end it
detects the face,
so it's going to be like that.
We're going to see
examples in week four
where the output is bigger
than the input and your network
is probably like this.
So you'll build intuition
during the class
to when you want to
downsize your input layer
or upsize your input layer.
Yeah.
And by the way, these
hacks are valuable.
Why does meta go out
and give crazy offers
to a few researchers?
Because they know stuff.
They know those
hacks, literally.
OK.
So again, someone said it.
The output is 0 or 1.
The last activation is
going to be a sigmoid.
Yes question.
Yeah.
So forcing yourself to
pick a specific resolution,
you come up with a more general
model by taking any image
and then sampling.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah you can do that.
You can probably say in the data
set, I don't care of the sizes
because I'm scraping
data from everywhere.
I'm collecting data on my phone.
I'm putting it
all in a database.
I write a script that
downsamples or upsamples
everything to the
same resolution,
and then I send those lower
res images in the network.
Because what I care about is
the training of my network.
I want it to be fast
and inefficient.
You could do that.
Yeah, for sure.
Yeah.
And there are networks
we're going to see in the--
YOLO is an example
of a network where
in the later versions of YOLO
it does that automatically.
It can take any resolution and
it just samples it accordingly.
OK last activation is
going to be sigmoid.
We wanted the output
to be between 0 and 1.
And the architecture most
likely a shallow network.
We don't need too much
capacity unless the task
is highly complex.
And a convolution should
do the work really well.
You don't what a
convolution is yet,
you're going to
know in a few weeks,
but those are known to be good
for sequences and for images.
And finally, the loss function.
What loss function
would you use?
Uh.
Which one?
Sigmoid.
No, sigmoid is the activation.
What's the loss function?
Logistic loss.
Yeah, logistic loss also called
binary cross-entropy loss,
which is the one you've seen
in the videos this week.
Yeah.
When you're like selecting your
images and your resolution,
how much is designing that
around the hardware limitations
matter?
If you have certain
memory bandwidth,
adder sizes, caching, is that
an issue or do you just let that
come out raw.
So repeating the question how
much the amount of hardware
and the quality of the hardware
you have at your disposal
influences those decisions?
The answer is a lot.
But, in fact, I'm
assuming you're
training it on your laptop
right now, which will work.
But you need to make
those trade offs.
And I think that's why
those skills matter.
Now, if the task is
more complicated,
you look at the hardware
you have available,
you'll make a quick back of
the envelope calculation.
The calculation is
really about how fast
our iteration cycles can be.
It's not about necessarily
the performance of the model.
In the end, you want to be
able to iterate super quickly.
And if your model takes
one year to train,
you're not going to
be able to iterate.
You need to reduce it somehow.
So there are situations that
we're going from 64 by 64 to 65
by 65, will double your
compute time depending on--
Yeah.
Yeah, for sure.
Are the features of the
model, every scaler in the 64
by 64 by 3 array?
What do you mean?
The--
Like the features is every
single scalar value in this--
So the 64 by 64 by 3 is like
literally, you look at a picture
and you look at one pixel.
These have three values
that describe the color.
And then you just flatten it.
And then those numbers
are given to the input
layer of your neural network.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah right.
OK let's move on just
for the sake of time.
This was just the easy warm up.
The two things I just want you
to remember from that project
is we're going to build
a lot of proxy projects,
and it's important to remember
them for your own projects.
So you remember, oh, I
remember this experiment
we did on humans.
Or I remember how many images
we needed for that project.
And then that can help
you make decisions faster.
And then the other thing
that is worth highlighting
is the human experiments.
We're going to do a lot
of human experiments
starting with the next example.
And those are usually helpful
to make quick decisions
in your project when
you're in the industry.
So second project,
trigger word detection.
Let me give some
context on this.
The general problem--
OK, you're familiar with
Alexa and all these--
let's say Siri and
things like that that you
might have in your
kitchen listening to you.
Everybody knows.
So the way these
networks typically
work these models is
it's not a single model,
it's a cascade of models for
energy and efficiency purposes.
So for example, if you
have a virtual assistant
in your kitchen, the first
model is activity detection.
It just detects if
there is any volume.
Because you don't want to
listen with the heavy model
at all times, it just
uses a lot of energy.
You want a very
lightweight model
that understands when
volume is playing.
And so let's say this
network detects volume,
it calls another network that
is focused on the activation
word the trigger word.
Alexa, hey Siri, OK Google.
That's usually the second layer.
And that one is only listening
for a specific keyword.
If the keyword comes
in, it would typically
call a better model
that's slightly slower,
that might be heavier and
more energy consumption,
and that might understand
what you're trying to do.
And then I'm not going
to go into the details,
but you have architectures
that get very complicated.
Back in the day, some
of these companies
were doing one model to
set up a timer, one model
to buy something online.
One model was very complicated.
Today it's slightly
simpler and more end to end
but I just want you to
know the cascade of models
that are being called
because this case
study is about the second model
is about the trigger word.
So here's my problem for you.
Given a 10-second audio speech,
detect the word activate.
How would you build that off the
shelf like that starting from 0.
What data would you collect?
Yep.
So we are looking at frequencies
that we might receive.
And from those frequency we want
to figure out what was the word.
And we also want to
look at [INAUDIBLE].
OK.
How long does this usually
take to say the word, and then
we will run some
kind of algorithm
to translate our
frequency to [INAUDIBLE].
Like a Fourier transform, or--
what you described is
a Fourier transform
or plus the preprocessing.
You're right.
So you're saying audio
is a bunch of frequencies
with values.
And we want to first
pre-process that, then
to give it to an algorithm.
And the length of the
sequence matters as well.
Because if you want
to detect the word
activate you know that
the length needs to be--
there's a minimum length.
You can't say activate in
less than 10 milliseconds.
So the length matters as well.
That's good insight.
What else?
What data?
How would you collect that data?
Yes.
Microphone like with your phone.
OK.
You would go around
campus and record people.
How would you-- what
would you ask them to say?
The word activate.
You would ask-- you would
record a bunch of people
saying the word activate.
You would ask them
anything else?
Other words.
State--
Yeah.
Say a sentence.
It turns out you have websites
that are random generators,
and you just say, say
this and say this,
and you record everything.
Yeah.
Say the word deactivate.
Oh good one.
So you're saying you want
to find negative words that
are close to the positive
word, just to make sure
that the model learns that.
That's a great one.
Yeah.
Actually, it turns out activate
is a really bad word to choose.
The reason Alexa,
and actually, there
was a lot of
discussions at Amazon
back in the days around
what would the word be.
And it turns out it's very
important, what you choose,
because you want to
choose a word that is not
used in common language,
otherwise your assistant
is always turning on.
And Alexa is not ideal either.
It's not bad, but
it's not ideal either.
OK, so let me just
narrow down the problem.
Let's say we've
gone around campus,
and we've collected a bunch
of 10-second audio clips.
Do we need to think about
the distribution of the data?
Why does it matter?
Why campus only might
be limited, let's say?
Yeah.
Maybe [? I'd ?] get
a lot of accents.
OK, accents.
Turns out the first
version of this model
that I built with Andrew,
my German friends,
could not make it work.
None of my German friends
would make it work.
And we had to collect
more data from--
and I had two German
roommates at the time,
so we had to collect
more data from them,
because there's just a certain
way that people would say words.
OK good insight.
What else other than accents?
Yes.
Average age.
Good point.
Average age on
campus is probably
younger than if you
actually cross campus and go
to Palo Alto.
And in fact, the frequencies
are going to be different
that younger people use.
That's correct.
Yeah.
There is also the cadence.
How fast you say words.
How fast-- some
people speak fast,
some people-- and it has to do
with the language of origin.
Some people just speak faster.
Correct.
And look at this.
When you hear someone
who speaks fast
versus someone who speaks slow,
it doesn't make a big difference
to you as a human.
But if you actually
just had access
to the numbers and
the frequencies,
it would look
completely different.
So the model actually struggles
a lot with that problem.
Yeah.
I don't think this is very
important for the ratio of male
to female voice.
Yeah for sure.
Ratio of male to female.
Anything that would
modify the frequencies.
And on average, yes, there's
different frequencies
or distribution male to female.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE] noise or other
people like talking to them.
Background noise.
Very important.
Turns out on Stanford campus,
you don't hear the metro.
So it's very likely that
your algorithm will not
work for people in New York
that are taking the subway all
the time because of the
background noise behind it.
Yeah OK.
I think we get a sense of
the again, the complexity
of the task ahead of us.
Let's say the input is
a 10-second audio CLIP.
I'm going to call X.
And this audio CLIP
has a few things that
are special to it.
So one of the things
is a negative words
which are in purple, positive
words which are in green,
and then the background
is in orange.
So this is for example,
someone saying hi,
activate yourself, whatever.
You see what I mean?
Activate is the positive word.
What's the resolution we want?
OK I'm not going to
ask you this question
because we don't have speech
expert-- a speech expert would
know it.
What you can do, though,
without being a speech expert,
is to go on GitHub and find
another speech project,
and you actually search for the
hyperparameters they're using.
And if you're using
human audio, you'll
find that the same numbers
will work for your project.
OK.
So you do that little
search, and you'll
find that there is just a
certain sample rate that
works well with human voice.
What's the output?
0 or 1.
OK, let's try something.
So let's say the
output is 0 or 1.
0 meaning there is
no positive word.
The word activate is not there.
One meaning there is a positive
word in that 10-second audio
clip.
So we're going to do a
little human experiment.
I've selected three-- let
me turn the volume on.
I've selected three audio
samples of around 10 seconds.
OK.
I'm not going to tell
you what the language is,
because the model
doesn't language
when we start training it.
So you're acting like the model.
That's the experiment.
I'm just telling
you that the first.
And the third sample have the
word that we're looking for.
And I'm not telling you
what the word is again,
because the model
doesn't what the word is
at the beginning of training.
So now up to you to
guess what the word is.
And I hope one of you will
save us and find the word.
OK let's try it.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
To loud.
Second sample.
Wait let me see if I can
put the microphone here.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Anybody has it or.
No, no.
No way.
Impossible.
Third one.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
OK.
Who has the word?
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
OK, maybe.
That's not it, but maybe.
Yeah in the back?
Sounds like [NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
You're Italian?
You speak-- OK.
[LAUGHTER] Yeah it's funny.
Nobody finds it usually in the
first try, but you did find it.
Yeah that's correct.
OK, let's try again and do it
with a different labeling scheme
this time.
OK, let's try again, I'm
going to play it again,
but the labeling
scheme has changed.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
It's the first one.
Third one.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
What's the word.
Someone who's not
Italian speaker.
I'm not sure people heard so
I want to try someone else.
Yeah, you've heard it.
Something like promojo.
OK not far promojo, it's
pomeriggio But you're close.
Was it easier the second
time or the first time?
The second.
Way more.
Way easier.
So if it's easier for you, it's
easier for the model, basically.
And so what is the
question I'm posing here
is we could go with the first
labeling scheme which is
easier for us to label frankly.
You don't need to indicate
the location of the word.
But how much more
data do you think
we'll need in order for
the model to figure it out?
It's probably 1,000x data.
And so the question is is the
second labeling scheme 1,000
times harder for us to
label than the first one
and the answer is no.
So the answer is very clear.
You would rather have the
second labeling scheme,
and your model is
going to learn way
faster than in the first case.
So that's the type of human
experiment you can do.
Now we're going to use
that labeling scheme.
Yeah question.
For the label.
This is Marvin, right?
Yeah we'll talk about it.
Question is it manual
labeling or not?
Yes right now it's
manual, but I'll
explain some tricks we can use.
Yeah.
Is there a tradeoff where
you spend a lot more time
to label something.
But then it does do
better on the model.
How do you think that
would [? trade off? ?]
Yeah how do you
pick the trade-off
between the different
labeling strategies and not.
In fact, today you could
have a pre-training
and a post-training that have
different labeling schemes.
The question is
for pre-training.
You want the model
to get really good
and you don't want to-- you want
to avoid a cold start problem.
The problem of the cold start is
with the first labeling scheme,
maybe even with 1,000 data
points that you collect
and label manually, it's
not even going to understand
anything.
So you need-- the
second labeling
scheme can be a great way to
work around the cold starts.
You might need less data, but
it will start understanding
what you mean and then
the rest of the data
might be labeled
differently, essentially.
OK, let me talk a little bit
about the labeling scheme.
We're actually going to
use a slightly different
labeling scheme.
And the reason is the
one with 1, 1 and only 0
the risk is you can,
actually, have a model that
performs 99.9% accurate that
is, all zeros just predict 0
all the time.
It's very accurate.
But the thing is there's
just one one to find,
and it's very hard to find it.
And so the network is
going to lean toward zeros.
Meaning the data is-- the
labels are so skewed towards 0
that it's going to be hard
to find any signal in it.
And so the trick that
deep learning researchers
use generally is
can we actually do
a little more balanced
between the positive
and the negative labels.
Just a pure engineering hack.
Not much science behind it.
The last activation we're
going to use a sigmoid.
But because it's a
sequential problem,
we're going to use
sigmoid in sequence.
At every time
step, there's going
to be a sigmoid activation.
And then the
architecture, we're going
to learn it later in the
class, you don't need to worry.
This would be likely an RNN.
You'll learn later in the
class what that means.
And then the loss
function-- can someone
guess what loss function,
we would be using?
Yes yeah.
Binary cross-entropy, but we're
going to use it sequentially.
Meaning at every
step, we're going
to compute that with
the sigmoid output.
Yes.
Sorry.
On the output.
So you just label the activate
word as multiple ones.
Correct.
You take your 10 second inputs.
You look at where the
positive word activate is
and you put ones in
there when it plays.
And you force the model
to predict, hey, activate
has been played.
There is a lot of
nuances you see,
because you actually are
going to build this project
with do we want
the ones to start
exactly when the words start.
Do we want to have a delay?
There's a lot of technical
questions around that.
Yeah.
The other question.
I was wondering what
do you mean by steps.
Are they like [INAUDIBLE]?
What I mean by steps is
audio is sequence data.
And so it's time
step by time step.
And so what I mean is that
at every time step, whatever
your sample rate
is, you're going
to have a prediction
at every step.
So what is critical to the
success of this project
is really the labeling strategy.
Here is how we did it.
And you just have to
it or not know it.
It actually takes a long time to
figure something like that out.
And so thankfully, when
I was a grad student,
one of my senior PhDs helped
me with these methods,
and he was able to guide me
and saved me probably a month
because I would not have figured
out myself this probably.
So here's what we did.
We took three databases.
We created three databases, one
that would have positive words.
So as you were
saying earlier, we
record people for
the word activate.
One that would have negative
words, other words including
deactivate, but also kitchen
and lion and dog and whatever.
And then we have
background noise.
Turns out background noise
in audio data is almost free.
There's just a ton of
background noise online.
You can go on many platforms,
online video platforms.
You can just take the audio.
It will be background noise.
So background noise is free.
You don't need to go and
collect it, most likely.
The other two,
though, are harder.
Yeah question.
Did you record those
first two yourself.
Yeah.
How many?
So I'll tell you--
I'll tell you how we
do it in a second.
But yes, we recorded
everything manually.
What we did is we went online.
We scraped free license data.
Actually, it's a skill to
know the licensing models.
You're going to learn that
in the project mentorship
with the TAs.
What licensing allows
you to do what with data
it's good to know forever.
You learn it once
and then you know.
What is CC BY, what is CC BY NA,
what is the MIT license, what is
the Apache license, et cetera.
And so we take
10-second audio clips.
We CLIP the background noise.
And we went around
campus and we literally
recorded people saying
activate and other words.
And we cut it when they said it.
So the word was contained
exactly to the amount
that it was needed.
Then we created a Python script
that randomly inserts words,
randomly.
Non-overlapping words.
So for example, this would
be created synthetically.
I would have tens
of background noise.
I would insert two
negative words,
and I would insert
one positive word, OK.
The trick is that
because the Python script
did that, the Python script
knows where activate was put
so it can label automatically.
And so it turns out that
we went around campus,
we used an app even to get help.
So we hired a couple of
people to come with us.
Each brought their
phone, and we went all
around campus
recording people to say
activate, and other words.
And we created those data sets.
Within three hours, we had
millions of data points.
Because think about it.
Let's say you have 1,000
activates across campus,
10,000 other words,
infinite background noise.
Imagine how much data
you can create with that.
When you actually write
the Python script,
you can also add some
data augmentation.
You can reduce some frequencies.
You can augment
some frequencies,
you can accelerate it,
you can decelerate it.
So you can actually create a
pretty meaningful data sets
for this problem in three hours.
Now I'm talking
about training sets
because you don't want to
use that data for test sets.
For test sets, you want data
to be as real as possible.
You're familiar with the
concept of train and test set.
So for the test set, we
had to manually label data,
but it was a much smaller
set than the training set.
So it's much more convenient.
The second important part
was architecture search.
I'm not going to talk
about it too much here,
but there are architectures
that just work better
for these types of problems.
And this is an example
of an architecture,
on the right, that
works way better.
And my learning
from that project
was just go to the expert and
ask them what they've tried
and try to learn
from their mistakes.
And in fact, I
remember Ani Hainan,
which was in the first level
at the gates computer science
building, and he knew that this
architecture was going to fail.
And he knew why, because he's
done so many speech projects,
and he just knows what
works and what doesn't work.
So that's why your TAs are here
for actually in your projects.
So you should give
them a call, and say,
hey, is what I'm
doing good or give me
a pointer for what I might
spend my next week doing.
OK.
So learnings from this
section, this case study.
Data collection strategy
is extremely important,
including the data
labeling strategy
using human experiments
matters as well,
and then referring
to expert advice.
That's the type of thing
you want to do in a project.
Do you understand
conceptually how such project
is built now at a high level?
OK, good.
Yeah question.
At the application
layer, how often
do you have to create
your own architecture?
How often it's just like
top the shelf [INAUDIBLE]?
So how often do you need to do
an architecture search nowadays?
Less often than before.
But this class is all
about understanding
what's going on under the hood.
So we're going to
walk you through that.
In practice, it depends
on your problem.
I'll give you in
the industry you
might be building a company
that requires the model
to be running on the browser.
And so you have additional
constraints that
push you to create
your own architecture,
collect your own data fine tune
the model the way you want.
For many startups out there
and companies out there,
you're going to start
from a foundation model.
You're going to start
from a foundation model,
and then you might,
actually, quantize it
or prune it or modify it to meet
your needs in terms of latency,
in terms of memory, in
terms of hardware capacity.
And knowing what's going on we
did is important in those cases.
Yeah.
OK.
Super.
So we're one hour in.
We are about halfway through
the class, a little bit ahead,
and I have a few more case
studies to cover with you.
By the end, we will have a
full set of proxy projects
to work with.
So this one is cool.
It's face verification.
A school wants to
use face verification
to validate student IDs
in facilities like dining
halls, gym, and pool.
So let me explain what it is.
It's like you arrive
at the Arriaga gym
and instead of just normally
you would swipe your student ID.
And your picture will
show up on the screen,
and there's someone
sitting there.
It's going to compare
the picture they're
seeing on the screen
to the picture they're
seeing with their eyes.
And if it's the same, they're
going to say can go ahead.
This is slightly different.
Here you're going to be
verified by a camera.
So there's actually
a camera ahead.
And you're walking in and
you're swiping your card.
And we're going to compare
the picture in the database
to the picture that is
being taken by the camera
to make sure that
it's the same person.
How do you get started?
[INAUDIBLE] students
[INAUDIBLE].
So everybody who got admitted
uploaded pictures at least one.
So we have that already
in the database, correct?
Yeah.
What else?
You would probably
use cameras that
are going to be used for
detecting fakes later.
You're saying the
camera matters?
Yeah.
Yeah for sure the
camera matters.
In fact, we talked
about resolution.
You think the resolution is
lower or higher than the day
and night project?
[INAUDIBLE]
Probably higher.
In fact, it's
going to be higher.
And again, I would go
back to literally doing
a human experiment and
showing pictures of twins
and asking people if they
can differentiate the twins.
And you'll see that the
resolution matters, actually.
OK yeah.
You wanted to add something.
Oh, yeah.
You also need noise.
Other people that
are not used to.
Also, data from
outside the University.
We could look at the features.
Which features.
The person's human features
that we could compare.
Understand the
person's human feature,
but they're already
in the picture.
So the picture would
have the feature
or you would add
anything on top of that?
So you typically
would not actually
want to get the
feature level, you
would just want to say we need
to make sure it's in the data.
If it's in the data, the
neural network will learn it.
We likely use like the
same person multiple
times [INAUDIBLE].
Absolutely.
Same person multiple
times because the angle
matters, the time
matters, the-- et cetera.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
OK.
Same thing.
Try to crop the image
so that the [INAUDIBLE].
OK, so you're saying we
might do some pre-processing
to crop all the images so that
it's centered, or at least
that the image that we're
training the model with
looks like the image
that the camera is
going to take because the
model will run on the camera.
All of these are good.
So let's say our data set is
picture of every student labeled
with their name.
So this is one of
my friends Bertrand.
And he has his picture, which is
his picture from the student ID.
And then the input is--
OK.
He shows up in front
of the building.
He's a little bit confused.
But he showed up and
a picture was taken.
The resolution, we
talked about it.
What we use here
is 412, 412, by 3.
It's much higher
than before, OK,
as we were expecting because
we need small details.
Even eye color is identifiable.
So these things we cannot find
without a higher resolution.
In fact, if you actually go
through airport security and you
use some of these FasTracks
which take a picture of you.
Trust me, the
resolution is going
to be even higher than that.
Much higher than that because
they're actually getting
into the iris at that level.
So what's the output?
The output is 0 or 1.
Yeah it's Bertrand
or it's not Bertrand.
We're good so far?
The architecture.
Let me actually ask how
would you do this comparison
without neural networks?
Let's say a very basic way.
If you have to start
with the first method.
Yeah.
We have like average
list of characteristics
that [INAUDIBLE] applies.
So you would feature engineer.
You would say, for example--
you would define 10
features that are
good for identifying people.
And you would have a
filter for each of them
and you would run it
on the picture and say,
yes do we have this feature
or not, essentially.
OK.
Yeah, it's a good one.
Even more basic than that
would be a pixel comparison.
Just compare the two pixels.
What's the problem with
doing a pixel comparison?
So the idea is I take the
two pictures, I compare them,
and if they're close enough
in pixel-wise comparison,
then it's the same
person, if they're far,
it's not the same person.
What can go wrong?
Difference in lighting.
Difference in what?
Lighting.
Yeah actually,
what's interesting
with the lighting
is if you look here.
So in this one you take the
top left pixel right here, OK.
It's bright.
You take the top left
pixel on this one,
it's dark or at
least dark green.
The difference between
these two pixels is massive.
It's close to 255 yet the
pixel doesn't even matter.
So why would you use that?
It would penalize the
comparison without actually
mattering at all.
So that's a good point.
Yeah.
Background noise
can be [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah, absolutely
background difference.
Translation invariance.
Imagine the same
picture, but the person
is like three
pixels to the right.
The comparison will be
completely different
because it's a pixel comparison
rather than a semantically
meaningful comparison.
What are other things
that can go wrong?
The distance from the camera.
Distance from the camera.
Again rotation invariance,
translation invariance,
scale invariance,
all of these matter.
What are other things that are
not geometric modifications?
Yeah.
Wearing glasses or a hat.
Wearing glasses or hats.
What else?
Hairstyle.
Yeah.
The big beard.
And in fact, you look
here he has much more
beard than on the picture.
And he was much younger, by
the way, on the first picture.
And often time we look-- were
younger on our student IDs
than we actually are in person,
and that may make a difference.
OK, so these issues
we all talked about.
I think people get it.
Good.
So our solution is to use
the concept of encoding.
Remember what we talked about
earlier with the face example?
It turns out a network
that has been trained
to understand faces should
have meaningful information
in those layers that you
can use as comparison
that is more meaningful
than a pixel comparison.
So this is how it goes.
We have Bertrand picture
from the student ID
we run it through a deep neural
network and we get a vector.
What is this vector?
It's a vector that we grab
in the middle of the network
somewhere.
Remember what I said
if the vector is
taken earlier in the
network we're going
to get lower level features.
If you go deeper, it's going
to get more facial features.
So you probably go
slightly deeper.
You go much deeper
actually for this example.
And then same thing.
You run the exact same network
on the picture from the camera,
and normally if the
network was trained well,
those two vectors should
be close to each other.
Distance is 0.4.
You set the threshold.
You might do a little study to
see what's the right threshold.
And of course, this
threshold is going
to determine the number
of true positives
that you're going to get
versus false positives
versus false negatives.
The higher the threshold, the
more likely you make a mistake.
The more relaxed you are.
So here let's say I set
a threshold of a 0.5.
Hey, I'm confident enough
that this is Bertrand.
And again, airport security
might have a much higher lower
threshold than the dining
Hall at Stanford, obviously.
OK, so this is the general
idea behind what we want to do,
but I still haven't
talked to you about how
the network is trained.
The network right
now is not trained.
We haven't learned
how to train it.
Yeah.
Question.
Question about the
[INAUDIBLE] networking use.
Is it like just a regular
picture classification or as
a binary output or is it--
What's the network?
We'll learn it, actually.
We're going to see it together.
Yeah, I'll describe it.
But I don't want to get into
the architectural nitty gritty,
I want to focus on the
general training scheme
that we're going
to use, and then
you're actually
going to build that
at some point in the quarter.
Yeah other question.
Yes.
This 128 dimensional vector,
what exactly hidden features
are there?
What are the hidden features
in the 128 dimensional vector?
We don't know.
That's the point
of deep learning
is you have to create
a loss function that
will modify your
parameters in a way that
forces it to learn features.
But I can't tell you that a
dimension number 3 is for eyes,
and dimension number
6 is for ears.
I can make a study, we'll
study it later this quarter,
and tell you that this
neuron is actually
good at detecting certain
types of features,
but right now, I can't tell
you unless I do that study.
Yeah.
OK.
So question for you.
How would you build a
training and a loss function
to make that possible
to train that network?
Do you have ideas?
It's not an easy question.
OK.
Try.
Where to start?
Yes.
Supporting two vectors I
think mean square error
is going to be better.
So mean squared
error between what?
You're right, actually.
Two vectors mean squared
error because it's a-- yeah.
But--
[INAUDIBLE] the loss
function probably--
the cost function probably
cross entropy [INAUDIBLE].
So are you saying we would
take pairs of pictures.
We would run it
through the network.
We will then take the
two vectors that we get
and apply the loss function
some distance L1 distance,
L2 distance, and
then trace it back
and say these were the same
people should have been closer.
That's what you mean?
Yeah it's a good idea.
Yeah someone else
wanted to say something.
I was gonna say it's like
the cosine similarity of two
vectors or any other
distance [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah, that's another one.
Cosine similarity.
That could also be
our loss function.
We could also add some
data manipulation.
OK like what?
Like create a data set
from the original picture
and play around with
the [INAUDIBLE].
Great idea.
Data augmentation.
So you say I can take
the picture of Bertrand
and probably mirror it,
flip it, rotate it, crop it
and I would use
more data that way.
Yeah, absolutely.
That would help a lot actually.
So all of these are good ones.
If I summarize
your point though,
because that's really
the key to the designing
a good loss function,
what we really
want is that similar
picture of the same person,
end up with similar vectors
and picture of different people
end up with different vectors if
we rephrase it in plain English.
So what we'll do is that we'll
build a data set of triplets.
The triplets includes
a picture that
is the anchor, a picture
that is the positive.
The reason it's called
positive is because it's
the same person as the anchor.
And a picture that is called
the negative because it's
a different person than the
anchor, and by definition
also a different person
than the positive.
Well, what if we only have
one picture of a person.
One picture of a person.
Great question.
If you have one picture of a
person, then you can't do that.
We'll actually
see another method
that would allow
us to do it even
with one picture of a person.
Yeah.
You could kind of rotate.
You can rotate it.
That's true.
You could actually do
some data augmentation,
as he was mentioning,
and build a data
set starting with one picture.
But this approach will
not be the best one.
We'll see another approach right
after that would work better.
Yeah.
Why are we comparing like
a vector from the model
from the vector
from another model
instead of just comparing
the output to the output?
A good question.
Why do we compare
a vector rather
than the output of the model?
So what's the
output of the model.
We actually haven't talked
about the architecture,
but I'm assuming you're
saying it's a binary number.
It's between 0 and 1.
Because it's a single dimension,
it cannot hold meaningful
information.
So you probably want to have
a vector that is big enough,
where you believe it
has enough flexibility
to hold information
that can allow
us to verify if the same
person is on the picture.
Yeah, essentially.
OK, I'm going to move on.
And if there's-- so what we
want is to minimize the encoding
distance between the
anchor and the positive,
and we want to maximize the
encoding distance between
the anchor and the negative.
So question for you.
What I'm going to ask you
is to take 10, 15 seconds,
look at the slide.
And you're going to start voting
for A, B or C. By the way enc
is encoding.
Is just how I call the vector
that we get out of the network.
A is the anchor, n is the
negative and p is the positive.
So A is the anchor picture N
is the negative picture, which
is different from the
anchor, the different person,
and P is the positive picture,
which is the same as the anchor.
And anchor of A is when you
run A through the network,
you get the vector anchor of A.
OK, let's look at the results.
A 47 for A 23 for B 3 for C. So
someone who said good job first.
That is correct.
Someone who selected A
wants to tell us why?
Yeah.
Because we're to minimize the
distance between the anchor
and the positive.
You just minimize the
distance right there.
But to maximize the
distance between the anchor
and the negative that's the
same as minimizing the negative.
Correct Correct.
Great so actually the
keyword here is minimize.
If I had said maximize
the answer indeed,
as you say would have been
different because here,
we're looking at minimizing
the distance between the anchor
and the positive.
And in fact minimizing this or
maximizing the opposite of it
that's why the answer is a.
OK good stuff.
Let's keep going.
So going back to the
initial setup, we had a cat
and we were predicting
a binary number.
Here instead, we
have three pictures
going through the
network in parallel
so you can imagine
it's batch processing.
It's like the three are
going in the same network
at the same time.
And then you're
getting three vectors.
You're computing the
loss function OK.
You're doing this loss
function we talked about.
I'm not going to talk here
about the alpha number
but you're going to
learn when you build it
why the alpha number matters.
Hint is maybe 0 would have been
a correct answer if you didn't
have the alpha number,
so it would have created
instability in the model.
But you do that
many, many times.
You push the parameters
to the right or the left.
And because of the way you
created your loss function
and your data labeling,
the way you structured
your data and the loss
function, essentially the model
is going to learn by itself
to create similar encoding
for pictures that are
of the same person,
and separate encodings
for pictures that
are not from the same person.
And you didn't need to
do feature engineering,
you didn't need to talk
about eyes and ears
and whatever because
it will figure it out.
You know that you created
the learning environment
to allow that to happen.
So congratulations, you designed
your first loss function,
and we're going to design
many more in this course.
This, by the way,
is from facenet.
It's a paper from 2015
from Schrott et al.
And you'll see in
the slides I used,
I always put the reference
to the papers in case
you want to go back and
study the actual paper.
Many students do it
for their projects.
This is a great one.
Great, great paper to look.
A lot of citations as well.
Let me make it slightly
complicated-- more complicated.
We learned face
verification, now
we want to do face
identification.
How is that different?
Identification is a
school wants to use--
to recognize students
in facilities.
So imagine face verification
is you swipe your card
and then that
picture was compared
to the picture of the camera.
That's verification.
The two are they
the same or not?
Identification is
you have this picture
in the database somewhere.
The person enters immediately
you can identify them.
So the difference for those
of you who fly in the US
is when you go
through global entry,
many people don't even need to
put their passport or anything.
They just want to look at
the camera and they move on.
That's identification.
But actually, when you're
in Europe, for example,
you put your passport
in, then you walk in,
then it takes a picture,
that's verification.
You see the difference or no.
Yeah.
You choosing for verification
the negative, for the input, how
would you [INAUDIBLE]?
The negative or how do
you create those triplets
essentially?
When you have to
do it in real time?
No in real time--
that's a great question.
I didn't talk about it.
So at train time
you have a databases
and you create the
triplets automatically.
Like you pick pictures
from the same person,
or you use data augmentation,
and you add a random picture
from someone else.
You create millions
of triplets like that,
or billions of triplets.
At test time, you only take
the picture from the camera,
run it-- you don't
use the negative.
You just take the
picture from the camera.
You run it through the network.
The person swipes.
You, take the picture
from the swipe,
run it through the network.
You do the comparison,
you let them in or not.
So there's no more negative
at test time in practice.
It's just a trick
to train the model.
OK, so how would you
do face identification
using what we learned
for face verification.
Is there any small
tweak you can make
that would make this network
work for identification?
Yes.
[INAUDIBLE]
Correct.
What is it called
in machine learning?
There's a machine
learning algorithm
that we can stack on
top of what we just did.
He said you can compare--
so because we don't have
two pictures anymore,
we just have one
from the camera.
You just compare the vector of--
you run this by the network,
you get the vector.
And then you compare
it to the database--
[INAUDIBLE]
No, but you try.
You have a database of
all the student pictures.
You run everything
through the network.
Instead of storing
the image, you
store the vectors and
then someone shows up
and you're looking
in the database.
Is there any vector that
is super close to this one.
That's identification.
What is this algorithm
called in machine learning?
It's pretty simple algorithm.
[INAUDIBLE]
No.
OK I'm going to make it easier.
What if instead of
having one picture
of a student in the database,
you had three of each student.
You have three vectors
for each person.
And then you're trying
to find the nearest
vectors in the database from
the one that the camera takes.
I used the keyword.
[INAUDIBLE]
No.
K-Nearest neighbor.
Yeah.
K-Nearest neighbors.
That's a K-Nearest
neighbor algorithm.
It's essentially-- you want
to explain what you meant.
Why is it K-Nearest neighbor?
Well, I was just thinking about
what's the nearest vector--
Yeah.
--closest to the
vector [INAUDIBLE].
Yeah.
It's K-Nearest neighbor for
high dimensional vectors.
So here is a simple example
of K-Nearest neighbor
per two dimensions.
In practice, it's 128
dimensions so I can't put it
on a slide, of course.
But let's say in green,
you have the query point.
The query point is the
camera picture, OK.
And then you run a nearest
neighbor algorithm,
and you say, are there three
vectors in the database that
are close to this vector.
And you can add additional
checks are these three
vectors from the same person.
If they are, then it's very
likely the person is correct
because you just prove
that the three closest
vectors in the database are
from three the same person
three times, so it's
higher likelihood.
You could even do it
for 10 nearest neighbor
if you want to be really secure.
Let's say you go to
the airport every time.
And every time they
take a picture of you,
and now they can do a 10
nearest neighbor on that search.
Does that make sense?
Now it's slightly
more complicated,
you want to do face clustering.
So in your phone,
sometimes, it says
it put automatically all
the pictures from your mom
in one folder and from
your dad in another folder.
How does it do it?
How could you make a tweak
to again, what we created
or encoding network?
How can you use
that to create that?
K-Means.
K-Means yeah, exactly.
K-Means algorithm, which
is an unsupervised learning
algorithm clustering.
So you have a bunch of pictures.
You have vectorized all of them
with the network you trained.
And normally the vectors
that are from the same person
should be clustered
around the same place.
And that's very simply how big
companies do it on your phone.
Yes.
What happens if the person's
not on the database?
Yeah so if the person
is not in the database,
then you shouldn't
find any vector that
is close to the vector
you're taking a picture of.
The closest vector might
be above your threshold
in terms of distance, and you
wouldn't let that person in.
Yeah.
I think that's why they make
you, sign up for global entry.
Yeah for sure.
Yeah, they make you sign up.
So it's interesting because
companies know that they
need to build these algorithms.
And then some-- the
admission process the sign up
process might include
certain data points.
And now you're starting
to understand how
it's used in the background.
OK Let's move on.
Yeah one question.
Are you comparing every new
example with each vector
or with a centroid?
Oh, a good question.
So are you comparing
each new picture?
So I take a picture of
my mom with my phone.
What's going to happen?
This picture is
going to likely--
if you're doing clustering
is going to be compared
to the centroid of my mom.
So the phone keeps probably
a centroid of my mom.
And if it's close enough to the
centroid over another centroid
it's going to probably put it
in that folder, essentially.
Yeah one more question,
and then we'll move on.
Yeah what algorithm do
you use to determine
how many centroids you want?
Yeah there is-- how
do you figure out
how many centroids you want?
There is an algorithm.
You'll study it in
CS230 not in CS230.
What we learned here is
what an encoder network is.
We learned about positive anchor
negative for the triplet loss.
The loss I showed you is
called the triplet loss because
of the triplets.
And then we learned the
different variations
of face verification
identification and clustering.
Now we're going to get to an
interesting section, which
is brand new around
self-supervised learning.
So note that everything we
did so far, the day and night
classification, the trigger word
detection, and the triplet loss
were supervised learning.
We had labels, essentially.
Day and night is very
classic supervised learning.
You label data with 0 and 1.
Same for trigger word
detection, face verification.
You can debate-- it
can be different.
But anyway, we focused
on supervised learning.
Now we're going to talk about
self-supervised learning.
And my question for
you is the following.
Labeling is expensive.
We know that.
So how would you redo what we
did with a different approach
that does not require labels?
Meaning you remember even
in face verification,
we had the name of the students
in the database with their face,
and we might have
multiple pictures of them.
Let's say you don't
even have that.
You just have faces
in the wild unlabeled.
How would you do
things differently?
Any idea?
Yeah.
So that's neural
network to decide
like to point out which
images are close to each other
and [INAUDIBLE].
OK.
Let the neural network
find the pictures that
are close to each other, but how
would you train that network?
You're starting with a network
that doesn't do anything
and you give it an
image, it gives you
a random vector at first.
So how would you train it?
Yeah.
Do some kind of
clustering offline,
and then use that as-- use
those centroids as your labels.
Do some clustering offline.
But again, my question is
the clustering algorithm.
How is it trained?
How do you cluster if you
don't have any encoder network?
Because the clustering
came after we trained
the encoder network.
The clustering only worked
because we had a good encoder
network.
But if you have for
example, a bunch
of pictures of the same
person, and then you
run that through the network.
But you don't know if
it's the same person.
That's what I'm saying is like--
Vectors would be similar.
No, because that's the
network you're training.
The vectors are not
similar because that's
the network we want to train.
Right now I gave you a network.
It's completely random.
You give it my
picture on Saturday
and on Sunday the vectors
are completely off.
So how do you start?
Yeah, yeah.
You want it.
You could do a carbon copy.
OK, tell me more.
You could just train the
model to [INAUDIBLE] image.
First create a layer of
representation of that.
And then given the
label representation,
and then another model that
given the label representation.
OK, OK.
Yeah you're ahead.
But we'll study that
in two weeks actually.
So we'll do a two encoders
two weeks from now in class.
Anyone else has an idea?
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
It's actually similar
to what he was saying.
To reconstruct the
original image.
Yeah, that's what we learned.
There's a lot of methods.
Diffusion models work like that.
Autoencoders we learn
about that in two weeks
when we focus on generative AI.
Generative modeling.
Here I want to present
also a generative method,
but it's really interesting
because it will be your Foray
into self-supervised learning.
Here is the idea.
If we have pictures in the wild.
Going with the methods you
had mentioned around data
augmentation, you can
actually force the network
to learn from the data itself.
So let me give you an example.
I take-- you look at
the picture of this dog
and you rotate it by 90 degrees.
It's still the same dog.
A human would say
it's the same dog.
What are we using in our brain?
We're using the ability to
understand rotation invariance
and to understand the
semantics of the dog.
And so technically, if you gave
those two images to the network,
you could create a loss function
that compares those two pairs
and has to have vectors that
are close to each other.
Does that make sense?
The other thing you can
do you can do a patch.
You can literally take
an image of a face
and put a patch on
half of the image.
And then you say--
and then you do the same
thing on the other image.
You put the other
patch, the other half.
And now you tell the
network, these two
should have the same
vector, pretty much.
So you use your
data augmentation
scheme on massive data sets
online to force the network
to learn from the data itself.
OK no need to forge
triplets, per se.
You just take a picture.
You make a variance of it
with noise, with rotation,
with cropping, with translation,
with whatever you want.
And then you put these two
in the data set and you say,
these are two the same person.
It should have the same vector.
Does that make sense?
That's why it's called
self-supervised learning.
Because you don't
have labels, you just
create a learning
environment that
makes the network learn from the
patterns of the data directly
itself.
So this is an example
called SimCLR.
Again the paper is right there.
And this shift from
supervised triplets,
facenet which was a paper from
2015 to self-supervised pairs.
That is why modern models
are trained on billions
of unlabeled images.
That's how we create-- it's much
simpler when you think about it.
You can literally write
a script and scrape
and it will label--
auto label the images
and put them in
pairs, do variations,
and then you'll end up with a
very powerful pre-trained model,
much simpler than people think.
It's not that hard at
the end of the day.
Most of the complexities are
going to come from compute.
So this method is called
contrastive learning.
We're going to talk about it
a little more in two weeks.
Self-supervision is not
only an image thing,
it's also used in
other modalities.
For example in texts the
principle is the same.
You predict what belongs
together and you push away what
doesn't.
That's for images.
And here.
What the core of
GPT, some of you
probably have heard of
that is a method called
next token prediction.
We're going to learn later
about tokens in the class.
But today, forget about
tokens, just think the words.
We're trying to
look at a sentence
and predict the next word.
Why is this
self-supervised learning?
Because you don't label data.
You just literally
grab data from online,
and you create a scheme
that forces the model
to learn from the
patterns of the data
using self-supervised learning.
But the self comes from
the fact that you didn't
label it manually yourself.
So let's do a few examples.
And the reason I want to do
the examples is because we want
to talk about emerging
emergent behaviors that
stem from the tasks we defined.
So give me the word
you're thinking of.
I poured myself a cup of--
some people said tea, coffee.
Anybody said anything else?
Water.
Water, a cup of water.
Healthy people said water.
OK yeah.
So what's the emergent
behavior that you
can expect the model
is going to learn
based on just that example?
[INAUDIBLE]
A good point, because you
that whatever is here first
fits in a cup, so
it understands that.
The second reason is poured.
So it's a liquid.
So just this sentence,
without even labeling,
is going to generate emergent
behaviors that we've never
trained the model for.
That's what's interesting
about modern AI, if you will.
You don't need to
define the tasks.
Frankly, the same way.
Think about face verification.
Back in the days, we used
to do what I showed you,
where we would create
triplets, and we
would be very specific about
this is for face verification.
You could actually scrape
all the images online
and do the contrastive
learning that I showed you next
and it will still be
good at detecting faces
without you having even defined
that task in the first place,
just by doing the
contrastive prediction.
OK.
First example.
Also, again, I was
trying to predict,
but people usually
say different things.
I think the majority
of people think coffee.
It's very cultural.
You go in another country,
it's going to be tea for sure.
And that forces the
model to really think
about everyday co-occurrence
pattern like them, being liquid,
being of a certain size
occurring together.
So for example, there's probably
a lot of sentences online that
says pouring a cup of
tea and there's a lot
saying pouring a cup of coffee.
Because of that,
the model should
understand that these two things
are probably close to each other
because their
context is similar.
Second example, the
capital of France is--
Paris.
Paris, OK.
What's the emergent behavior you
can expect the model to learn?
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
Learn about facts, exactly.
So this is really predicting
the next token forces
the model to encode real-world
facts, such as Paris
being the capital of France.
Oops, sorry.
What about the third example?
She unlocked her phone
using her body parts.
I don't what your phone--
type of phone you have, but
wait, what would you say.
Face.
Password.
Fingerprint.
Yeah, all of them are possible.
So again, the network
will learn probably
that password,
fingerprint, and face
can be used to unlock stuff.
And, in fact, here probably
fingerprint or face
might nowadays be the
more common because
of how the world has evolved.
But back in the days, it
would be password for sure.
And so these forces
semantic understanding
that these things are probably
all meant to unlock information.
The next one the cat chased
the dog or mouse or ball.
And again, the model we learn
probabilistic reasoning.
Meaning because
in the data set it
will find variations
of the sentence
with different
actually conclusion
it would say that
there's a lot of things
that the cat can chase.
And so that's
probabilistic reasoning.
What about the last one?
If it's raining, I
should bring an umbrella.
What's the emergent behavior.
It's reasoning and
inference is the model
we learn to connect conditions.
So for example raining requires
you to be protecting yourself
from the rain with an umbrella.
That's reasoning.
So long story short
emergent behaviors
are an expected
capabilities that
arise from simple training
objectives at scale
without being explicitly
taught or labeled.
Later in this class, we're
going to have a full lecture
on deep reinforcement
learning, where we're
going to talk about emergent
behaviors in robotics
or in gaming, where turns
out, the agent you're training
learns to do certain
strategies that you
didn't expect they would do.
AlphaGo is a good example, if
you've watched the documentary.
OK.
Self-supervision is not
just about text and images.
We've seen the next
token prediction for GPT,
and we've also seen contrastive
learning for images.
My question here
is the following.
What other examples of
modalities can you think of?
And tell me the task
that you would define.
Audio.
So for audio what would you do?
How would you do a
self-supervision in audio?
Mask out portions of the audio.
Exactly.
Mask out portion-- so
mask out 20 times steps.
And because you know what the
data was, you have a label.
You knew what the truth was.
You can do a
self-supervision task.
It would work great.
Again, the only limitation
is compute and scale.
What other modalities?
Maybe self-driving trains
with conditions of the--
Yeah so self-driving
is a good example.
It's very multimodal.
There's a lot of
different things
happening in self-driving.
We'll talk about it
in a future lecture.
What else.
What other modalities
can you think of?
Videos.
What would you do video?
Take some portions.
Take frames out.
You can take some frames out.
Same principle as audio.
Biology.
Some people work in
health biology here.
Yeah a couple.
Well you know about amino
acids and protein structure.
You can actually mask
portion of the inputs,
such as the protein structure
or DNA, and then complete it,
and it will force the model
to understand those patterns.
So great stuff in there.
But the world is
very multimodal.
We experience words, images,
sounds, and actions together.
How can we connect them?
When you think about
multi-modality,
you want to connect texts
and images, let's say.
What do you need to do those?
You actually need labeled data.
You need image captions.
So for example, you
have a bunch of pictures
online of the cat is
looking at the camera.
So there's a picture and there's
a label underneath just like
on Instagram.
Let's say people
put captions, right.
And the reason you can
connect those modalities
is because of that data set,
because you have a lot of that.
Now this is not typically
called supervised learning,
it will be called
weakly supervised
learning because you're not
actually labeling images
with captions,
you are benefiting
from naturally occurring
pairings in the world.
There is naturally occurring
pairings of images and texts.
OK, so now what I
want you to do is
to find other examples
that are not just images
captioned, but
naturally-occurring examples
of different modalities
that appear in the wild
together that we could
use to connect modalities.
The whole point of
connecting modalities
is that our vectors now can
represent different modalities
close to each other in space.
So think about that.
Please continue.
I'm going to read
some of the answers.
But we keep going.
So stock price sequence
is the single modality.
You would look at stock price
and you can mask and then
predict.
But I think maybe what you mean
is you would put additional data
points in there as well.
Let me see if I have something.
Audio paired with video.
Audio and video is a great one.
Audio and video is
naturally paired.
You take a YouTube video, it
has the audio and the video.
And so when a dog
is barking, you
have the audio of
the dog barking
and the video of
the dog barking.
And so you can create a pairing
between those two modalities.
Transcription so a lot
of movies have subtitles.
And so, by definition, a video
stream or a stream of images
will be naturally connected
to text, which would also be
naturally connected to audio.
Music and song title.
Again, that's a great one.
Audio and text are connected.
Genotype and phenotype.
Good one as well.
Medical imaging with ultrasound.
That's a great one.
Naturally occurring.
You usually if you
go to an ultrasound
you'll have the
different types of images
that occur together naturally.
Game footage and
keyboard action.
Again another great one.
So price and area code.
Good one.
Great examples.
Facial expression.
So TLDR is we have ways
to connect modalities.
Oftentimes some modalities are
going to connect very naturally.
Most things connect to text.
So that's what you want to use
as your shared space typically.
But here it is an example of
a paper called image bind.
And the interesting
thing about image bind
is it says that
most things connect
through a single modality.
So, for example, thermal
data connects to imaging.
Imaging connects to text.
So text is going to
connect through images
with thermal data.
And what's the
consequence of that
if I may show you
a little example.
Is that you can--
this is a demo from
Meta called image bind.
It's a cool one.
You can actually see
things occurring together.
So, for example, you
put a text drums.
And of course, you can
get an audio of a drum.
But you can also see what the
closest image in the vector
space is to that concept.
So all the spaces are
now bound together.
You can also do audio and image.
So you give it a dog
barking and a picture.
What can you expect?
A dog on the beach.
That's the
multi-modal embedding.
The connecting tissue between
those different modalities.
And that's probably one
of the biggest innovation
of the last few years
connecting those shared spaces.
OK.
I'm not going to
cover the full paper,
but the core insight is that
there are shared spaces.
There are spaces
like text and image
that connect to most modalities
that can allow us to connect
those modalities together.
We learned a lot of
things here embeddings,
self-supervised learning,
contrastive learning, data
augmentation, next
token prediction,
weakly supervised learning.
And then the shared embedding
stays with the central pivot
usually being text.
OK.
That's all for today.
We're not going to have time to
cover the adversarial example,
but we're going to cover
it in two weeks together.
You're going to have more
neural network baggage.